  <sect1 id="firewall_setup_for_remote_management">

    <title>Dedicated Firewall machine</title>
    
    <para>
      The choice of the hardware for the firewall depends on how much
      bandwidth is needed by the network it protects. Our experience
      indicates that an old Pentium machine is sufficient for a group
      of 2-5 people doing regular web surfing, sending and receiving
      email and doing some other not-very-demanding tasks. Small
      firewall appliances made by Linksys or DLink demonstrate good
      performance as well. These appliances do not allow ssh access by
      default, so fwbuilder won't be able to upload generated firewall
      configuration, however their firmware can be replaced with
      <ulink url="http://www.dd-wrt.com/site/index">DD-WRT</ulink>
      or <ulink url="http://openwrt.org/">OpenWRT</ulink> which
      enabled ssh and many other powerful features. Firewall Builder
      4.0 comes with direct support for OpenWRT and can generate a
      drop-in replacement for its standard firewall configuration
      (just choose host OS "OpenWRT" in the firewall object).
    </para>

    <para>
      We have ran firewalls like that at various times using
      Linux/iptables, FreeBSD/ipfilter and OpenBSD/pf combinations and
      can't say that any particular platform has better
      performance. They all just work. A firewall like one of these
      won't slow down file transfer on a DSL or a cable network,
      easily supporting download speeds of 1.5 - 2 Mbit/sec. Since
      hardware like this is very obsolete and can be had for almost
      nothing, we never saw the need to investigate which OS and
      firewall performs better on a slower CPU. People have had good
      results using old notebooks as their firewalls, too. The
      advantage of the notebook is that is has a monitor which makes
      troubleshooting easier in case you make a mistake in the policy
      rules and block your own access to the firewall over the
      network.
    </para>

    <para>
      For a larger installation (more people or long policy) a faster
      CPU is needed.
    </para>

    <para>
      The OS installed on the firewall machine should be
      minimal. Basically, all you need is the kernel, basic tools
      usually found in /bin, and ssh. This is true regardless of what
      OS you choose, so just follow installation instructions
      appropriate for your OS. Do not install development tools, X11,
      editors, graphics software and so on and you'll be fine. Make
      sure you get ssh, though, and in some cases you may need Perl.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once you install the firewall machine, check if the ssh daemon
      is running. It usually is, but some OS have different
      installation options and if you choose "workstation" install,
      they may not start ssh daemon automatically. Use <command>ps -ax
      | grep sshd</command> to check if the daemon is running, and if
      it is not, activate it.</para>
  </sect1>

