<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

  <sect2 id="cluster_server_fw_synch_local_rules">
    <title>Creating Local Firewall Rules for a Cluster Member</title>

    <para>
    In the previous recipe we showed how to use the Firewall Builder 
    cluster object to create a single firewall policy that gets 
    installed on multiple servers. When we finished the cluster 
    was configured with three servers as shown below.
    </para>
    
    <figure id="cluster_fw_synch_3_servers_local_rules">
    <title>Cluster with 3 firewalls sharing the same firewall policy with one firewall also using local rules</title>
    <graphic fileref="cluster_fw_synch_3_servers_local_rules.png" />
    </figure>
    
    <para>
    In this recipe we will show how to create a set of local rules 
    on one of the cluster members. Local rules are evaluated 
    <emphasis>in addition</emphasis> to the rules that are configured 
    for the cluster. 
    </para>

    <para>
    For this example we will add a local rule to the web-03 server 
    firewall allowing remote access to the server via SSH from a trusted 
    external vendor coming from a network defined as "Vendor X Network". 
    </para>

     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>Allow inbound SSH from network object "Vendor X Network" 
       </listitem> 
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
    The following steps assume that we are starting with the same 
    configuration that the previous example finished with.
    </para>

    <bridgehead>Step 1 - Create a new policy in the web-servers 
    cluster</bridgehead>

    <para>
    Since we only want this policy applied to <emphasis>one</emphasis> of the 
    servers in the cluster, not all of the cluster members, we need 
    to create a separate policy object to hold the local rules.
    </para>

    <para>
    In this example we name the new policy object 'local_rules'. The 
    policy name can be any name you choose except that it cannot be the 
    same name as the policy that contains the main firewall rules for 
    the cluster which by default is 'Policy'.
    </para>

    <figure id="new_policy_cluster">
    <title>New policy in cluster object web-servers</title>
    <graphic fileref="new_policy_cluster.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>
    After you are done, you should see the new policy named 
    local_rules under the web-servers cluster object.
    </para>

    <figure id="cluster_object_new_policy">
    <title>Cluster object web-servers with new policy local_rules</title>
    <graphic fileref="cluster_object_new_policy.png" />
    </figure>

    <bridgehead>Step 2 - Create a new policy in the web-03 server 
    object</bridgehead>

    <para>
    Next we need to create a policy object on the web-03 firewall <emphasis>
    using exactly the same name</emphasis> as we used for the policy object 
    on the web-servers cluster.
    </para>

    <figure id="new_policy_web-03">
    <title>New policy in firewall object web-03</title>
    <graphic fileref="new_policy_web-03.png" />
    </figure>

    <note>
    <para>
    You must use the same name for the policy on both the cluster object 
    and the firewall object.
    </para>
    </note>

    <bridgehead>Step 3 - Define the local rule in the new policy on the
    web-03 firewall</bridgehead>

    <para>
    Remember, the rule we want to add only to web-03 server is:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>Allow inbound SSH from network object "Vendor X Network" 
       </listitem> 
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
    When creating local rules use the interface objects of the 
    firewall that the local rule is being configured on.  For our 
    example we use the interface object of the web-03 firewall for
    the destination and interface fields. After you configure the 
    rule in the local_rules policy on web-03 the policy should look 
    like this:
    </para>

    <figure id="web-03_new_custom_rule">
    <title>New rule in policy local_rules on firewall object web-03</title>
    <graphic fileref="web-03_new_custom_rule.png" />
    </figure>

    <note>
    <para>
    Make sure to configure this rule in the local_rules policy object 
    on the web-03 firewall object. You can see which firewall policy 
    you are editing at the top of the Rules panel.
    </para>
    </note>

    <bridgehead>Step 4 - Setup a branching rule in the cluster policy to 
    jump to the local policy</bridgehead>

    <para>
    For the rules in the policy 'local_rules' to be applied we need to 
    setup a branching rule in the main policy called 'Policy' to jump 
    to the local_rules policy. You can define the branch rule anywhere 
    in the policy, in this example we are going to make the branch the 
    first rule of the policy. This will ensure that the custom rules 
    defined on web-03 will be run first, then the rest of the rules 
    for the cluster will be applied.
    </para>

    <figure id="new_cluster_branch_rule">
    <title>New branching rule in main policy on cluster object web-servers</title>
    <graphic fileref="new_cluster_branch_rule.png" />
    </figure>

    <note>
    <para>
    Make sure you set the branch target to be the 'local_rules' 
    object from the cluster object and not one of the member
    firewalls.
    </para>
    </note>
  
    <para>
    After you have configured the branching rule in the main policy your 
    rules should look like this. 
    </para>

    <figure id="new_cluster_branch_rule_example">
    <title>Cluster policy with branch rule on top</title>
    <graphic fileref="new_cluster_branch_rule_example.png" />
    </figure>

    <note> 
    <para> 
    Not all firewall platforms support branching, you can find out 
    more about branching in <xref linkend="multiple_policy_rule_sets"/>.
    </para>
    </note>

    <bridgehead>Step 5 - Compile and install policy</bridgehead>
   
    <para>
    Since changes were made to the web-servers cluster and web-03 
    objects we need to compile and install the updated firewall 
    rules to all cluster members.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    When the rules are compiled Firewall Builder includes the rules 
    defined in the local_rules policy object on the firewall cluster 
    member if they exist. If no rules are found in the member's 
    local_rules Firewall Builder will include the rules from the 
    cluster object's local_rules.
    </para> 

    <para>
    To see an example of this you can inspect the generated firewall 
    script for the web-03 server. You can see the new iptables chains 
    for the local_rules policy in red.
    </para>

    <programlisting>
echo "Rule local_rules 0 (eth0)"
# 
$IPTABLES -N <emphasis role="redtext">local_rules</emphasis>
$IPTABLES -N <emphasis role="redtext">In_local_rules_0</emphasis>
$IPTABLES -A <emphasis role="redtext">local_rules</emphasis>  -i eth0  -p tcp -m tcp  -s 198.51.100.0/24  \
   -d 192.0.2.13   --dport 22  -m state --state NEW  -j <emphasis role="redtext">In_local_rules_0</emphasis>
$IPTABLES -A <emphasis role="redtext">In_local_rules_0</emphasis>  -j LOG  --log-level info --log-prefix "RULE 0 -- ACCEPT "
$IPTABLES -A <emphasis role="redtext">In_local_rules_0</emphasis>  -j ACCEPT
# ================ Table 'filter', rule set Policy
# 
# Rule 0 (global)
# 
echo "Rule 0 (global)"
# 
$IPTABLES -A OUTPUT  -j <emphasis role="redtext">local_rules</emphasis>
$IPTABLES -A INPUT  -j <emphasis role="redtext">local_rules</emphasis>
$IPTABLES -A FORWARD  -j <emphasis role="redtext">local_rules</emphasis>
    </programlisting>

    <note>
    <para>
    The compiler will generate a warning for the web-03 firewall object 
    since there is a policy object named local_rules on the web-03. When 
    both the cluster object and a member object have a policy with the 
    same name, if the member object's policy <emphasis>is not</emphasis> 
    empty then the member's policy will be used in place of the cluster 
    object for that policy.
    </para>
    </note>

    <para>
    This results in the firewall web-03 having the following rules matching 
    applied.
    </para>

    <figure id="fw_policy_web-03">
    <title>Firewall rules sequence for traffic destined to web-03</title>
    <graphic fileref="fw_policy_web-03.png" />
    </figure>

    <note>
    <para>
    All the other members of the cluster will have an empty rule chain 
    created for local_rules. This means incoming traffic will go through 
    this empty chain first before being passed back to the main rules 
    defined in Policy.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    You can also create custom rules on other members of the cluster 
    using the same local_rules policy name.
    </para>
    </note>

  </sect2>
