	<sect2 id="double_nat">
        <title>"Double" NAT (Source and Destination Translation)</title>
  
        <para>
        There are situations where both the source and destination 
        IP addresses of a packet need to be NAT'ed. The diagram 
        below shows just such a scenario where an internal server 
        needs to be accessed remotely from the outside using the 
        Remote Desktop Protocol (RDP).
        </para>

        <figure id="double_nat_base2">
        <title>Network Configuration</title>
        <graphic fileref="double_nat_base2.png" />
        </figure>

        <para>
        What complicates this scenario is the fact that the 
        default route for the ms-server-1 server directs traffic 
        to rtr-1 instead of fw-2. If a remote user attempts to 
        connect from the Internet to ms-server-1, and there is a 
        destination NAT configured on the <emphasis>fw-2</emphasis> 
        firewall to forward traffic from a specific port on its outside 
        eth0 interface to port 3389 (RDP) on ms-server-1,  
        the ms-server-1 server will send the RDP response traffic 
        to rtr-1 because of the default route and the remote 
        desktop connection will never be established. 
        </para>

        <para>
        One way to solve this problem is to configure<emphasis> 
        fw-2</emphasis> with "double" NAT which results in 
        both the original source <emphasis>and</emphasis> 
        original destination IP addresses being modified. By 
        modifying the source IP to be fw-2's internal eth1 
        address, the return packets from the ms-server-1 
        server for the RDP traffic will correctly be sent 
        to fw-2 and the remote desktop connection will work.
        </para>
  
        <para>
        This recipe assumes that in addition to the fw-2 firewall 
        object the following objects and attributes have already 
        been configured in Firewall Builder.
        </para>

        <table><title>Firewall Builder Objects</title>
        <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Object Name</entry>
          <entry>Object Type</entry>
          <entry>Object Value</entry>
        </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>ms-server-1</entry>
          <entry>Address</entry>
          <entry>192.168.1.25</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>RDP-OUTSIDE-4080</entry>
          <entry>TCP Service</entry>
          <entry>4080</entry>
        </row>
        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>
        The NAT rule is created using these objects and objects from 
        the Standard Library. After the double NAT rule is configured 
        it should like the figure below.
        </para>

        <figure id="double_nat_rule">
        <title>Configured NAT Rule</title>
        <graphic fileref="double_nat_rule.png" />
        </figure>

        <note>
        <para>
        The Original Src is set to Any, this will match the IP 
        address of any remote PC on the Internet.  To connect the 
        ms-server-1 internal server using RDP, the remote PC will 
        connect to <emphasis>fw-2's </emphasis> outside interface 
        on port 4080.
        </para>
        </note>
       
        <para> 
        Here is the Firewall Builder generated compiler output for 
        configuring this rule on an iptables firewall:
        </para>

<programlisting>

$IPTABLES -t nat -A PREROUTING  -p tcp -m tcp   -d 192.0.2.2  --dport 4080 -j DNAT \
  --to-destination 192.168.1.25:3389
$IPTABLES -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth1 -p tcp -m tcp   -d 192.168.1.25 \
  --dport 3389 -j SNAT --to-source 192.168.1.3

</programlisting>

        <para>
        After the NAT rule is installed on the firewall the traffic 
        that is destined to port 4080 on the outside interface of 
        fw-2 will be translated as shown in the diagram below.
        </para>

        <figure id="double_nat_translation">
        <title>Configured NAT Rule</title>
        <graphic fileref="double_nat_translation.png" />
        </figure>

        <note>
        <para>
        The Source ports in the example above are random and generated 
        by the system originating the TCP connection.
        </para>
        </note>

	</sect2>
