<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

      <sect1 id="cisco_asa_pix">
      <title>Configuring Cisco ASA and Cisco PIX Firewalls</title>

       <para>
        This section of the Users Guide provides an overview
        of everything you need to know to get started configuring
        Cisco ASA and Cisco PIX firewalls using Firewall Builder. This 
        means there is some repetition of concepts and materiels 
        that are included in other sections of the Users Guide. Many 
        of these topics are only briefly covered here, so we still 
        suggest reading the other sections of the Users Guide that 
        go in to more details.
        </para>
        
        <para> 
        The examples in this section will be based on configuring
        a Cisco ASA 5505 with the configuration shown in the diagram 
        below. Note that configuring Cisco PIX devices in Firewall 
        Builder follows exactly the same steps.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_example">
        <title>Example Cisco ASA Configuration</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/example_asa.png" />
      </figure> 

        <sect2 id="gs_asa_step1">
        <title>Creating Objects</title>

        <para>
        Firewall Builder is based on the concept of objects. There are
        a variety of different object types that can be used to define
        IP objects that can be used as the Source and Destination in
        your Cisco ASA/PIX rules. Two of the most common IP objects used
        in Cisco access lists are <emphasis>Networks</emphasis> and 
        <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Network Objects</bridgehead>

        <para>
        To create a Network object, for example a network to represent the
        internal 10.0.0.0/24 network in the diagram above, go to the object
        tree on the left side of the screen and double-click the folder
        labeled <emphasis>Objects</emphasis> to expand it. Right click on 
        the folder called <emphasis>Networks</emphasis> and select “New 
        Network”. This creates a new network object. In the lower portion 
        of your screen, called the Editor Panel, you can modify the 
        properties of this object.
        </para>

        <para>
        Change the object name to something that matches the function, in 
        this example we are going to call it “Internal Network” to represent 
        the network connected to our "inside" interface. The address is set 
        to 10.0.0.0 and the netmask is 255.255.255.0.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_new_network">
        <title>New Network Object</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/new_network.png" />
      </figure> 

      <note>
        <para>
        When editing the attributes of an object there is no Apply
        or Submit button. Once you edit an attribute as soon as you move 
        away from the field you were editing the change will take effect 
        immediately.
        </para>
      </note>

        <bridgehead>Address Objects</bridgehead>

        <para>
        To create an object that represents a single IP address, similar 
        to the host parameter in a Cisco access list, go to the object tree 
        and right-click on the <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis> folder and 
        select "New Address". In the Editor Panel change the name of the 
        object to something that reflects its function, for example “POP3 
        Server”, and set the IP address.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_new_address_steps">
        <title>New Address Object</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/new_address_steps.png" />
      </figure> 
            
       </sect2>
       <sect2 id="gs_asa_step2">
       <title>Define The Firewall</title>

        <para>
        To create a firewall object to represent your Cisco ASA click 
        on the “Create new firewall” icon on the main window of
        Firewall Builder. This will launch a wizard that walks you through
        creating your firewall object.
        </para>

        <para>
        Enter a name for the firewall object, in this example we will use
        <emphasis>asa-1</emphasis>. Change the drop down menu for software 
        that is running on the firewall to be “Cisco ASA (PIX)”.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_create_asa">
        <title>New Firewall Dialog</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/create_asa.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Click the "Next >" button to continue to the next step in the wizard.
        </para>

        <para>
        When creating a firewall in Firewall Builder you have a choice of
        configuring interfaces manually, or you can use SNMP discovery if you
        have SNMP enabled on your firewall and you have know the Read-Only or
        Read-Write community string. For this example we are going to configure
        the firewall interfaces manually.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_interface_discovery">
        <title>Select Interface Configuration Method</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/interface_discovery.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Click the "Next >" button to continue to the next step.
        </para>

        <para>
        The firewall that you create in Firewall Builder needs to match the 
        Cisco ASA or PIX firewall that you want to deploy the access lists on. 
        This means that the <emphasis>interface names</emphasis> and 
        <emphasis>IP addresses</emphasis> in the firewall object that you are
        creating must <emphasis>match exactly</emphasis> to what is configured 
        on the ASA or PIX.
        </para>

        <para>
        Click the green <imagedata fileref="gs/green_plus.png" /> 
        icon to add a new interface to the firewall.  Enter the name of the 
        interface exactly as it is shown on the ASA or PIX command line when 
        you run “show interface" command. In our example the interfaces are
        Ethernet0/0 through Ethernet0/7, but we are only going to use interfaces 
        Ethernet0/0 and Ethernet0/1.
        </para>

        <para>
        Set the interface name as Ethernet0/0 and set the label to outside. 
        Click on the Add address button and set the IP address to 192.0.2.1 
        with a netmask of 255.255.255.240.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_interface_address">
        <title>Set Interface IP Address</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_interface_address.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Click the green <imagedata fileref="gs/green_plus.png" /> 
        icon to add another interface to the router.  Enter the 
        information in to the wizard to match the second interface as 
        follows:
        </para>
           
      <figure id="gs_asa_interface_address2">
        <title>Interface Tabs</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_interface_address2.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Click the "Next >" button.
        </para>

        <para>
        Firewall Builder will automatically set the <emphasis>security 
        level</emphasis> of the interface based on the interface label 
        and IP address. The outside interface is set to security level 
        0 and the inside interface is set to security level 100.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_interface_sec_level">
        <title>Interface Security Levels</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_interface_sec_level.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Click the "Finish" button to create the firewall object.
        </para>

        <para>
        After you create the firewall object representing the ASA or PIX 
        the firewall object will be displayed in the object tree on the 
        left side. The Policy object, which is where the access list rules 
        are configured, is automatically opened in the main window.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_firewall_object_tree">
        <title>Firewall Displayed in Object Tree</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_firewall_object_tree.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Firewall Builder uses the concept of <emphasis>Network Zones
        </emphasis> to determine network topology in order to correctly 
        create rules. Each firewall interface has a corresponding 
        Network Zone that must be set. The Network Zone represents the 
        set of IP networks that would be the source of traffic coming 
        inbound to an interface.
        </para>
        
        <para>
        For example, if you use 10.0.0.0/8 for your internal network, 
        the "inside" interface should have its Network Zone set to an 
        object that represents 10.0.0.0/8. Network Zones can be a 
        Network object or a group object that includes multiple Network 
        objects. An exmple of when you would use a Group object is if 
        your internal network used both 10.0.0.0/8 and 172.16.0.0/16. 
        In this case you would create a Group object that included 
        network objects for both these IP networks and use that Group 
        object as your "inside" interface's Network Zone.
        </para>

        <para>
        For the "outside" interface you will typically set its 
        Network Zone to "Any" which is all IP networks that aren't 
        associated any other interfaces. Set the Network Zone by 
        double-clicking the interface object of the firewall and 
        selecting the Network Zone from the dropdown list.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_setting_network_zone">
        <title>Setting Network Zone</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_setting_network_zone.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Before moving on you should save our data file that contains the new
        firewall object that you just created.  Do this by going to the
        File -> Save As menu item.  Choose a name and location to save the
        file to.
        </para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="gs_asa_step3">
        <title>Configuring Access Lists</title>

        <para>
        After you create a firewall object, for example <emphasis>asa-1
        </emphasis> from our previous example, it will be opened automatically 
        in the object tree and its Policy object is opened in the main window 
        for editing. The Policy object is where access list rules are configured.
        </para>

        <para>
        To add a new rule to the Policy, click on the green
        <imagedata fileref="gs/green_plus.png" /> icon at the top
        left of the main window. This creates a new rule with default values set
        to deny all.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_default_rule">
        <title>Default Rule</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/default_rule.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Every rule includes the following sections:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem role="cisco_getting_started"><para><emphasis>Source</emphasis> - 
          this can be one or more IP 
          objects. Default value is Any which is the same as the "any" parameter 
          in a Cisco access list that matches all IP addresses.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Destination</emphasis> - this can be one or 
          more IP objects. Default value is Any which is the same as the "any" 
          parameter in a Cisco access list that matches all IP addresses.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Service</emphasis> - this can be one or more 
          Service object. Example services include the TCP and UDP protocols like 
          HTTP and DNS. Default value is Any which matches any IP service and is 
          the same as the "ip" parameter in Cisco access lists.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Interface</emphasis> - this can be one or 
          more interfaces configured on the firewall (router) object. Default 
          value is All which means the rule will be applied as an access list to 
          all configured interfaces.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Direction</emphasis> - options are Inbound, 
          Outbound and Both. This defines whether the resulting access-group will 
          be applied to interfaces as "in" or "out". Both will generate an identical 
          rule for "in" and "out". Default value is Both.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Action</emphasis> - options are Accept and Deny. 
          This matches the Cisco access list parameters "permit" and "deny". Default 
          value is Deny.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Options</emphasis> - options are Logging On and 
          Logging Off. Setting Logging On matches the Cisco access list parameter 
          "log".  Default value is Logging On.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Source</bridgehead>

        <para>
        To set the Source of a rule, drag-and-drop at least one IP object from the
        tree to the Source field of your rule. For example, if you created a
        Network object called Internal Network you would drag this to your rule
        as shown below.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_new_rule_source">
        <title>Setting the Source</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/new_rule_source.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        After you drop the network object into the rule the Source fields will
        change from Any to Internal Network.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_rule_step1">
        <title>After Source is Set</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/rule_step1.png" />
      </figure> 

      <note>
        <para>
        You can have more than one IP object in the Source and Destination fields. 
        When Firewall Builder generates the Cisco command line access lists it will 
        automatically split the rule in to multiple lines if necessary.
        </para>
      </note>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Destination</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Setting the Destination is exactly the same as setting the Source, except
        you drag-and-drop IP objects in to the Destination field of the rule.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Service</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Firewall Builder comes with hundreds of <emphasis>predefined</emphasis> 
        objects including Service objects for almost all standard protocols. 
        To access these objects switch to the Standard library by selecting it 
        from the drop down at the top of the Object tree window.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_switch_library">
        <title>Switching Libraries</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/switch_library.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Services are located in the <emphasis>Services</emphasis> folder. 
        For example, if you wanted to define a rule that permitted HTTP 
        traffic you would navigate to the HTTP service by opening the 
        Services folder, then opening the <emphasis>TCP</emphasis>
        folder and scrolling down until you find the http object.
        </para>

        <para>
        Once you find the http object, drag-and-drop from the tree on the left in
        to the Service section of the rule in the Rules window.
        </para>
            
      <figure id="gs_asa_new_rule_service">
        <title>Setting the Service</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/new_rule_service.png" />
      </figure> 

      <note>
        <para>
        To switch back to the User library, which contains the objects that you 
        created, click on the drop down menu that says Standard and select User 
        from the list of libraries.
        </para>
      </note>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Interface</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Set the Interface for the rule by dragging-and-dropping an interface
        object from the firewall (router) object to the Interface section of
        the rule. This will define which interface on the router that the
        access list will be applied to as an "access-group".
        </para>
            
      <figure id="gs_asa_new_rule_interface">
        <title>Setting the Interface</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_new_rule_interface.png" />
      </figure> 

        <bridgehead>Setting the Direction</bridgehead>

        <para>
        The direction of the rule is based on the traffic you want to filter.

        Traffic coming in to an interface should have the rule Direction set
        to Inbound and traffic going out of an interface should have the rule
        Direction set to Outbound.
        </para>

        <para>
        The Direction, Network Zone and the Interface setting in a rule will 
        determine which interfaces should have this rule applied.
        </para>

      <note>
        <para>
        Inbound vs. Outbound access lists. Older PIX versions did not support 
        outbound access lists on interfaces, so by default Firewall Builder 
        emulates this behavior. This means if you create an outbound rule on 
        an interface, Firewall Builder will convert that to inbound rules on
        all <emphasis>other</emphasis> interfaces. You can change this behavior 
        by editing the Firewall Settings for the firewall object and clicking 
        the checkbox next to "Generate outbound ACLs".
        </para>
      </note>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Action</bridgehead>

        <para>
        The action controls whether traffic matching the rule should be permitted
        or denied. Remember, all Cisco access lists have an implicit deny at the
        end of the list, so any traffic that has not matched a rule that permits
        the traffic will be dropped.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Setting the Options</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Logging for rule matches is set in the Options section. By default logging
        is turned on. To turn logging off, right-click in the Options section and
        select Logging Off.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Example of a Complete Rule</bridgehead>

        <para>
        The following is an example of a complete rule that allows traffic from
        an internal network to any destination address arriving inbound on the
        "inside" interface for the HTTP and HTTPS protocols.
        </para>
        
      <figure id="gs_asa_new_rule_complete">
        <title>New Rule with Fields Set</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/new_rule_complete.png" />
      </figure> 

        <bridgehead>Additional Tips</bridgehead>

        <bridgehead>Adding a Rule</bridgehead>

        <para>
        To add a new rule click the
        <imagedata fileref="gs/green_plus.png" /> icon at the
        top of the Rules Editor window.  This will insert a new rule above
        the current rule. To add a new rule below the current rule right-click
        on a rule and select "Add New Rule Below".
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_add_new_rule_below">
        <title>Adding Rules</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/add_new_rule_below.png" />
      </figure> 
            
        <bridgehead>Copy-and-Paste</bridgehead>

        <para>
        In addition to drag-and-drop you can also copy-and-paste objects.
        For example, you can right-click on the Internal Network object in
        the first rule and select Copy. Navigate to the Source section of
        the new rule you just created and right-click and select Paste.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Using Filters to Find Objects</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Filters provide a way to quickly find objects in the tree without
        having to open multiple folders and scroll. For example, if you wanted
        to use the POP3 protocol in a rule you could use the filter to find it.
        </para>

        <para>
        The POP3 protocol object is located in the Standard library, so select it
        from the dropdown menu at the top of the Object Window. Type pop3 in to
        the filter field. This will display all objects in the current library
        that contain pop3.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_pop3_filter">
        <title>Using Filter to Find Objects</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/pop3_filter.png" />
      </figure> 
            
      <note>
        <para>
        After you are done with the filtered object, clear the
        filter field by clicking the X to the right of the input box and then
        switch back to the User library by selecting it in the dropdown menu
        at the top of the object panel.
        </para>
      </note>

        <para>
        For the following sections we are going to assume that the following
        three rules defined for the router configuration shown in Section 4.2.1.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_three_rules">
        <title>Three Rules</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_three_rules.png" />
      </figure> 
         
        </sect2>
            
        <sect2 id="gs_asa_step4">
        <title>Compile and Install</title>

        <para>
        In Firewall Builder the process of converting the rules from the
        Firewall Builder GUI syntax to the target device commands is called
        <emphasis>compiling</emphasis> the configuration.
        </para>

        <para>
        To compile, click on the Compile icon which looks like a hammer
        <imagedata fileref="gs/hammer_small.png" />. If you
        haven’t saved your configuration file yet you will be asked to do so. After
        you save your file a wizard will be displayed that lets you select which
        firewall(s) you want to compile. In this example we are going to complie
        the firewall called <emphasis>asa-1</emphasis> configured with the rules above.
        </para>

        <para>
        If there aren’t any errors, you should see some messages scroll by in the
        main window and a message at the top left stating Success.
        </para>

        <para>
        To view the output of the compile, click on the button that says Inspect
        Generated Files.  This will open the file that contains the commands in
        Cisco command format.  Note that any line that starts with “!” is a comment.
        </para>
            
      <figure id="gs_asa_compiler_output">
        <title>Example Compiler Output</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_compiler_output.png" />
      </figure> 
            
        <para>
        The output from the compiler is automatically saved in a file in the same
        directory as the data file that was used to create it. The generated files
        are named with the firewall name and a .fw extension. In our example the
        generated configuration file is called asa-1.fw. You can copy and copy and
        paste the commands from this file to your ASA or PIX firewall or you can 
        use the built-in Firewall Builder installer.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Installing</bridgehead>

        <para>
        Firewall Builder can install the generated configuration file for you
        using SSH and SCP. To use the installer we need to identify one of the router
        interfaces as the “Management Interface”. This tells Firewall Builder
        which IP address to connect to on the router.
        </para>

        <para>
        Do this by double-clicking the firewall object to expand it, and then
        double-clicking on the interface name that you want to assign as the
        management interface. In this example this is interface Ethernet0/1
        which is the interface connected to the internal network.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_set_mgmt_interface">
        <title>Setting the Managment Interface</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_set_mgmt_interface.png" />
      </figure> 

      <note>
        <para>
        Any time you are changing access lists on your router
        you face the risk of locking yourself out of the device.  Please be
        careful to always inspect your access lists closely and make sure that
        you will be able to access the ASA / PIX after the access list is installed.
        </para>
      </note>

        <para>
        To install your access lists on the firewall, click on the install icon
        <imagedata fileref="gs/install_icon.png" />. This will
        bring up a wizard where you will select the firewall to install. Click
        Next > to install the selected firewall.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_install_checkbox">
        <title>Setting Compile and Install Actions</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_install_checkbox.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        Firewall Builder will compile your rules converting them in to
        Cisco access list command line format. After the compile completes
        successfully click Next >. Enter your username, password and enable
        password.
        </para>

      <figure id="gs_asa_install_screen">
        <title>Install Dialog</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/install_screen.png" />
      </figure> 

        <para>
        After the access list configuration is installed you see a message
        at the bottom of the main window and the status indicator in the
        upper left corner of the wizard will indicate if the installation
        was successful.
        </para>
            
      <figure id="gs_asa_install_success">
        <title>Successful Install</title>      
        <graphic fileref="gs/asa_install_success.png" />
      </figure> 
            
        <para>
        By default Firewall Builder will use SCP to copy the generated config 
        file to the firewall. Once the file is copied to the firewall, Firewall 
        Builder will connect using SSH to load the transferred config file from 
        memory using the "copy" command to merge the Firewall Builder generated 
        command with the current running configuration.
        </para>

        <para>
        Firewall Builder requires ssh version 2 to be enabled on the firewall.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    </sect1>
 
