<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

  <chapter id="interfaces">
    <title>Configuration of interfaces</title>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder 4.0 introduces support incremental management
      of the configuration of interfaces. It can add and remove ip
      addresses, create and destroy vlan interfaces, add and remove
      bridge ports and bonding interface members. Incremental
      management means generated script can add or remove interfaces
      or addresses only when needed, whithough having to blow
      configuration completely first and then re-add it back. For
      example, in case of IP addresses of interfaces, the script
      checks if address configured in fwbuilder GUI really exists on
      the interface it should belong to. If it is not there, the
      script adds it, but if it exists, the script does
      nothing. Running the script again therefore does not disturb the
      configuration at all. It is not going to remove addresses and
      then add them back. The same happens with VLAN interfaces,
      bridge ports and bonding interfaces.
    </para>

    <para>
      Not all of these features available on all supported OS.
      <xref linkend="interface_mgmt_support"/> shows this:
    </para>

    <table frame='none'  tabstyle='reg_table' id='interface_mgmt_support'>
      <title></title>
      <tgroup cols='5' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="5*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" colwidth="1*"/>

	<thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Linux</entry>
            <entry>OpenBSD FreeBSD</entry>
            <entry>Cisco IOS</entry>
            <entry>Cisco ASA (PIX)</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>IP address manageemnt</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
	    <entry>Incremental IP address management</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>VLAN interfaces</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Incremental manegement of VLAN interfaces</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Bridge ports</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Incremental manegement of bridge ports</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Bonding interfaces</entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="greentext">yes</emphasis></entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Incremental manegement of bonding interfaces</entry>
            <entry>partial</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
            <entry>no</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      The most complete implementation is available on Linux where
      generated script can incrementally manage ip addresses, vlan
      interfaces, bridge ports and partially bonding interfaces.
    </para>

    <sect1 id="ip_address_management">
      <title>IP address management</title>

      <!-- TODO: need examples -->

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Generated script includes shell code to manage ip
               addresses if checkbox "Configure interfaces" is
               turned on in the "Script" tab of the firewall object
               "advanced" settings dialog. By default, it is tuned
               off.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Script uses <emphasis>ip</emphasis> tool which
              should be present on the friewall. The script checks if
              it is available and aborts if it can not find it.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Script checks if ip address of each interface configured
              in the GUI exists on the firewall and adds it if
              necessary.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              If the script finds ip address on the firewall that is
              not configured in the fwbuilder GUI, it removes it.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              If checkbox "Clear ip addresses and bring down
              interfaces not configured in fwbuilder" is tuned on in
              the "Script" tab of firewall settings dialog, the script
              deletes all ip address of all interfaces that are not
              configured in fwbuilder GUI and brings interfaces that
              are missing in fwbuilder but are found on the firewall
              down. The goal is to ensure that firewall rules operate
              in the environment that matches assumptions under which
              they were generated. If the program generated rules
              assuming some address does not belong to the firewall,
              but in reality it does, packets may show up in the wrong
              chain that will lead to the wrong behavior of the
              firewall. This feature is off by default.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="vlan_management">
      <title>VLAN interfaces</title>

      <!-- TODO need examples -->

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Generated script includes shell code to manage VLAN
              intrfaces if checkbox "Configure VLAN interfaces" is
              turned on in the "Script" tab of the firewall object
              "advanced" settings dialog. By default, it is tuned off.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Script uses <emphasis>vconfig</emphasis> tool which
              should be present on the friewall. The script checks if
              it is available and aborts if it can not find it.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Script checks if vlan interface configured in the GUI
              exists on the firewall and creates it if necessary.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              If the script finds vlan interface on the firewall that
              is not configured in the fwbuilder GUI, it deletes it
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </sect1>



    <sect1 id="bridge_management">
      <title>Bridge ports</title>

      <!-- TODO need examples -->

      <para>
        Support for bridge interfaces and bridge ports is only
        available for Linux firewalls. Generated script can manage
        bridge interfaces as follows:

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Generated script includes shell code to manage bridge
              interfaces if checkbox "Configure bridge interfaces" is
              turned on in the "Script" tab of the firewall object
              "advanced" settings dialog. By default, it is tuned off.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Script uses <emphasis>brctl</emphasis> tool which
              should be present on the friewall. The script checks if
              it is available and aborts if it can not find it.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Script checks if bridge interface configured in the GUI
              exists on the firewall and creates it if necessary.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              It then checks if bridge interface on the firewall is
              configured with bridge ports that were defined in the
              GUI. It adds those that are missing and removes those
              that are not configured in the GUI.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Adding VLAN interfaces as bridge ports, as well as mix
              of regular ethernet and vlan inetrfaces is
              supported. That is, the following configuration can be
              configured in fwbuilder and generated script will create
              it:

              <screen>
bridge name bridge id    STP enabled    interfaces
br0  8000.000c29f6bebe   no             eth4.102
                                        eth5
              </screen>
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              In order to use VLAN interface as bridge port, it needs
              to be created twice in the GUI. First time it is created
              as a child of the regular ethernet interface and has
              type "VLAN". The second interface object with the same
              name should be created as a child of a bridge interface
              with a type "ethernet".
              <!-- TODO need example here -->

            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            </para>
          </listitem>


        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="bonding_intf_management">
      <title>Bonding interfaces</title>

      <para>
        Support for bonding interfaces is currently available only for
        Linux firewalls. Generated iptables script can incrementally
        update bonding interfaces:

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Generated script includes shell code to manage bonding
              interfaces if checkbox "Configure bonding interfaces" is
              turned on in the "Script" tab of the firewall object
              "advanced" settings dialog. By default, it is tuned off.
            </para>
          </listitem>


          <listitem>
            <para>Script uses <emphasis>ifenslave</emphasis> tool which
              should be present on the friewall. The script checks if it
              is available and aborts if it can not find it.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Script creates new bonding interfaces with parameters
	      configured in the GUI if module 'bonding' is not
	      loaded. This is what happens if fwbuilder script runs
	      after reboot.
            </para>

            <para>
	      if there are no bonding interfaces in fwbuilder
	      configuration, the script removes bonding module to kill
	      any bonding interfaces that might exist on the machine
            </para>

            <para>
	      if you add second bonding interface in fwbuilder, the
	      script checks if it exists on the machine. It will not
	      create it because to do so, it would have to remove the
	      module which kills other bonding interfaces. If this
	      second bonding interface exists, it will be configured
	      with slaves and addresses. If it does not exist, script
	      aborts. In this case you need to either 1) reload module
	      manually or 2) add max_bonds=2 to /etc/modules.conf and
	      reboot or 3) unload module and run fwbuilder script
	      again (if module is not loaded, the script loads it with
	      correct max_bonds parameter)
            </para>

            <para>
	      if a bonding interface exists on the machine but not in
	      fwbuilder configuration, the script removes all slaves
	      from it and brings it down. It can not delete it because
	      to do so it would need to remove the module, which kills
	      other bonding interfaces.
            </para>

            <para>
	      Limitation: currently all bonding interfaces will use
	      the same protocol parameters. This is because module
	      loading with parameter "-obond1" that is supposed to be
	      the way to obtain more than one bonding interface and
	      also the way to specify different parameters for
	      different interfaces causes kernel panic in my
	      tests. Tested with bonding module v3.5.0 and kernel
	      2.6.29.4-167.fc11.i686.PAE on Fedora Core 11. The only
	      working way to get two bonding interfaces I could find
	      is to load the module with parameter max_bonds=2, but
	      this means all bonding interfaces work with the same
	      protocol parameters. If bond interfaces are configured
	      with different parameters in fwbuilder, compiler uses
	      the first and issues warning for others.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </sect1>

  </chapter>
