<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introducing Firewall Builder</title>

    <para>Firewall Builder simplifies the firewall policy management
      for a number of firewall platforms, including
      Netfilter/iptables, ipfw, PF, Cisco PIX, and others. Firewall
      Builder provides a professional-grade GUI to these platforms,
      simplifying administration tasks.</para>

    <para>With Firewall Builder, you can manage the security policy of your
      firewall efficiently and accurately, without the learning curve usually
      associated with command line interfaces. Instead of thinking in terms of
      obscure commands and parameters, you simply create a set of objects
      describing your firewall, servers, and subnets, and then implement your
      firewall policy by dragging objects into policy rules. You can also take
      advantage of a large collection of predefined objects describing many
      standard protocols and services. Once a policy is built in the GUI, you
      can compile it and install it on one, or several, firewall
      machines.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="overview">
    <title>Overview of Firewall Builder Features</title>

    <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Over 100 predefined objects for the most popular and widely
            used protocols and services</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ability to create custom objects describing IP,ICMP,TCP,UDP
            or custom services</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ability to create objects to describe hosts, networks and
            address ranges</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Templates to help you jumpstart your
            firewall policy, and do it right the first time. Templates
            implement standard policies for typical network layouts, which can
            later be extended and edited by hand</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Network discovery tool that automates the
            creation of multiple objects by reading a hosts file, by
            crawling your network via SNMP, or by importing an
            existing firewall policy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An object oriented approach to the policy management: any
            change made to an object gets immediately reflected in all policy
            rules of all firewalls using that object. The configuration for
            multiple firewalls shares the same object database.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The ability to turn a firewall policy into a configuration
            file or a script and then install it on a firewall with just a few
            clicks of the mouse.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Convenient GUI that supports standard Copy/Paste operations
            for both text strings and network objects and allows for policy
            editing using drag and drop</para>
        </listitem>

	<listitem>
          <para>Find and Replace functionality that can be used
            within a policy or across a set of policies</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for several firewall platforms, including Cisco PIX
            and Open Source firewalls iptables, ipfilter and pf.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The ability to print a single object, a firewall policy, the
            whole hierarchy, or export it to the text file in either plain
            text or html format</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
	  <para>Built-in, platform-specific help. Different
	    firewalls provide different features and options. The
	    Firewall Builder GUI provides help in appropriate dialogs
	    to assist you in choosing the right options for your
	    platform.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <figure id="example1">
      <title>Sample firewall policy</title>
      <graphic scale="60" fileref="scrn2.png" />
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
