<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introducing Firewall Builder</title>

    <para>Firewall Builder simplifies the firewall policy management
      for a number of firewall platforms, including
      Netfilter/iptables, ipfw, PF, Cisco PIX, and others. Firewall
      Builder provides a professional-grade GUI to these platforms,
      simplifying administration tasks.</para>

    <para>With Firewall Builder, you can manage the security policy of your
      firewall efficiently and accurately, without the learning curve usually
      associated with command line interfaces. Instead of thinking in terms of
      obscure commands and parameters, you simply create a set of objects
      describing your firewall, servers, and subnets, and then implement your
      firewall policy by dragging objects into policy rules. You can also take
      advantage of a large collection of predefined objects describing many
      standard protocols and services. Once a policy is built in the GUI, you
      can compile it and install it on one, or several, firewall
      machines.
    </para>

    <figure id="example1">
      <graphic scale="60" fileref="overview_screenshot_1.png" />
    </figure>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="overview">
    <title>Overview of Firewall Builder Features</title>
    
    <para>
      Firewall Builder helps you write and manage configuration for
      your firewalls. It writes iptables shell script, pf.conf file,
      Cisco router access lists or PIX configuration for you. You can
      then copy and paste configuration generated by Firewall Builder,
      copy the file manually or using your own scripts, or use
      built-in function to configure the firewall.  Firewall Builder
      provides change control and search functions. It allows you to
      reuse the same address and service objects in rules of many
      firewalls. It simplifies coordinated changes of the rules in
      multi-vendor environments and helps avoid errors in generated
      configurations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder can generate complex <emphasis>iptables</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>PF</emphasis>, <emphasis>Cisco IOS extended access
        lists</emphasis>, <emphasis>Cisco ASA (PIX)</emphasis>
      configurations. You do not have to remember all the details of
      their syntax and internal operation. This saves time and helps
      avoid errors.
    </para>

    <para>
      Rules built in the GUI look exactly the same and use the same set of
      objects that describe your network regardless of the actual firewall
      platform you use. You only need to learn the program once to be able
      to build or modify basic configuration for iptables, PF, or Cisco
      routers or firewalls. Already an expert in one or several firewall
      platforms? Firewall Builder can help you utilize advanced features
      too.
    </para>

    <para>
      Configuration files for the target firewall are auto-generated so
      they don't have syntax errors and typos. Firewall Builder has
      information about features and limitations of supported firewall
      platforms. Avoid detecting errors when you actually enter commands
      on the firewall, when it is already too late. Fwbuilder helps you
      avoid many types of errors in the first place, for example it can
      detect rule shadowing, one of the signs of errors in the policy
      structure.
    </para>

    <para>
      Create an object to represent your network, a server or service once
      and use it many times. Port number or an address changes ? No need
      to scan all rules of all routers and firewalls to find it. Just
      change it in the object, recompile and push updated configuration
      and you are done. At the same time, the GUI provides
      <emphasis>powerful search functions</emphasis> that help you find all
      rules of all firewalls that use some object and
      perform <emphasis>search and replace</emphasis> operations.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you work for a large distributed organization with many
      administrators, you can assemble address and service objects that
      describe your network in a library and save it to a data file, then
      distribute it for other administrators to use. You can create your
      own templates for the firewall objects and rules and use them to
      quickly create new configurations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder helps perform transitions between different
      versions of the same firewall
      (<emphasis>iptables</emphasis>, <emphasis>PF</emphasis>, <emphasis>PIX</emphasis>);
      from one platform to another; from <emphasis>IPv4 to IPv6</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      You work with an abstract policy that operates with objects. We
      spend time studying differences between iptables and PIX or between
      different versions of each so that you don't have to.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder makes it easy to add IPv6 rules to the existing
      firewall policy. Create objects describing your IPv6 network, add
      them to the same rule set that defines your security policy for
      IPv4 and configure it as "mixed IPv4+IPv6 rule set". The program
      will generate two configurations from it, one for IPv4 and another
      for IPv6, using correct objects for each. There is no need to
      maintain two policies in parallel for the whole time of transition
      from IPv4 to IPv6.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can generate configuration for a range of devices starting from
      small <emphasis>Linksys</emphasis>, <emphasis>D-Link</emphasis> and other
      routers running <emphasis>DD-WRT</emphasis> or <emphasis>OpenWRT</emphasis>,
      to firewalls running <emphasis>Linux</emphasis>, <emphasis>FreeBSD</emphasis>
      or <emphasis>OpenBSD</emphasis> on a regular or purpose-built PC,
      to <emphasis>Cisco routers</emphasis> and <emphasis>Cisco ASA
        (PIX)</emphasis> firewalls.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder has been designed to manage both <emphasis>dedicated
        remote firewalls</emphasis> and <emphasis>local firewall
        configurations</emphasis> for servers, workstations and laptops.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder can generate scripts that set
      up <emphasis>interfaces</emphasis>, <emphasis>ip
        addresses</emphasis>, <emphasis>snmp</emphasis>, <emphasis>ntp</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>logging</emphasis> parameters and other aspects of the
      general configuration of the firewall machine.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Make coordinated changes in multi-vendor
        environments</emphasis>: Do you have Cisco routers with extended
      ACLs, dedicated Cisco ASA (PIX) firewalls, Linux or BSD firewalls
      and servers and need to make changes in configurations of all
      these devices to enable new service ? Firewall Builder helps you
      make coordinated changes in an environment like this.
    </para>

    <para>
      Have all the advantages of the GUI and object-oriented policy design
      with your existing firewalls and routers, be it Linux, BSD or Cisco
      devices. Protect your investment, there is no need to throw them
      away if you are happy with their performance. You can import
      existing configuration into Firewall Builder (currently only
      iptables and Cisco routers configurations).
    </para>

    <para>
      Built-in policy installer is flexible, uses ssh for secure
      communication channel to the firewall and has many safeguards to
      make sure you never cut yourself off the firewall in case of a
      mistake in the policy. It can deploy to one firewall or to many
      firewalls and routers in a batch job.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Is this new stuff?</emphasis> Not at all. The project
      has been registered
      on <ulink href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fwbuilderr/">SourceForge</ulink>
      in 2000 and
      on <ulink href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/fwbuilderr">Freshmeat</ulink>
      in 2001. Since then it went through several major releases. Open
      Source version is distributed under GPL and is included in major
      Linux distributions and is part of FreeBSD and OpenBSD ports
      system. Firewall Builder is dual licensed, packages for Windows
      and Mac OS X are distributed under traditional EULA for
      reasonable
      fee. <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilderr.org/docs/firewall_builder_licensing.html">More...</ulink>
    </para>

    <para>
      We have lots of documentation online. Start with Firewall Builder
      Users Guide (available in <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilderr.org/UsersGuide3.pdf">pdf</ulink>
      and <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilderr.org/docs/users_guide/book1.htm">html</ulink> formats). Users
      Guide explains the program in details and includes large "CookBook"
      section that presents typical problems of firewall rules design and
      demonstrates how they can be solved with Firewall Builder. There is
      also <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilderr.org/docs/firewall_builder_faq.html">FAQ</ulink>,
      <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilder.org/docs/firewall_builder_installation.html">Installation
        Guide</ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://www.fwbuilder.org/docs/firewall_builder_release_notes.html">Release
        Notes</ulink> for each version.
    </para>

    <para>
      We provide support via email, we also have
      active <ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/fwbuilderr-discussion">mailing
        list</ulink>
      and <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/fwbuilderr/forums/forum/16372">online
        forum</ulink>. Follow <ulink url="http://blog.fwbuilderr.org/">Firewall
        Builder blog </ulink> to get the latest project
      news. 
    </para>

  </sect1>
</chapter>
