<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

	<chapter id="remote-management">
		<title>Manage your firewall remotely</title>
		<subtitle>How to set up a firewall on a small machine
		and use a separate workstations to manage
		it</subtitle>
		
		<para> The best way to utilize the flexibility of
		Firewall Builder and to minimize the risk to your
		network is to run Firewall Builder on a dedicated
		management workstation. This workstation will have the
		near-full installation of Linux or FreeBSD, complete
		with X11 and Gnome or KDE. Alternatively, it can be a
		Mac or Windows PC.</para>

		<para>The reason we do not recommend running X11 and
                  GUI environment on the firewall is actually rather
                  simple. It is well known that complex programs are
                  more prone to errors than simple and short ones. X11
                  and GUI environments are
                  <emphasis>very</emphasis> complex programs, rivaling
                  or exceeding the Linux kernel in size. Granted, you
                  may be safe if you run these on the firewall
                  provided you install all the latest patches and keep
                  your software up-to-date. This, however, means a lot
                  of effort and time spent on maintaining software
                  that is not essential to the operation of the
                  firewall and is being used only once in a while. You
                  may add protection using firewall rules to block all
                  access to the firewall itself from outside (a very
                  good idea regardless whether you run X11 on it), but
                  then you need to carefully watch your policy to make
                  sure you don't drop these rules accidentally. The
                  rules may get more complex if you ever need to
                  manage your firewall remotely, making verification
                  difficult. All this adds up to the risk factor, so
                  it is just a lot simpler to not have X11 and GUI on
                  the firewall at all.
                </para>

                <para>In other words, run X11 and GUI environment on
                the firewall machine only when you have a definite
                reason to do so, and keep an open eye on it.</para>

		<para>We will look at configuring the dedicated
		firewall machine and then at configuring the
		management workstation.</para>
		
		<sect1 id="firewall_setup_for_remote_management">
		  <title>The Firewall</title>
                  
		  <para>The choice of the hardware for the firewall
		    depends on how much bandwidth is needed by the
		    network it protects. Our experience indicates that
		    a Pentium-II or Celeron machine running at 233 MHz
		    or above is more than enough for a group of 2-5
		    people doing regular web surfing, sending and
		    receiving email and doing some other
		    not-very-demanding tasks. We have run firewalls
		    like that at various times using Linux/iptables,
		    FreeBSD/ipfilter and OpenBSD/pf combinations and
		    can't say that any particular platform has better
		    performance. They all just work. A firewall like
		    one of these won't slow down file transfer on a
		    DSL or a cable network, easily supporting download
		    speeds of 1.5 - 2 Mbit/sec. Since hardware like
		    this is very obsolete and can be had for almost
		    nothing, we never saw the need to investigate
		    which OS and firewall performs better on a slower
		    CPU. People have had good results using old
		    notebooks as their firewalls, too. The advantage
		    of the notebook is that is has a monitor which
		    makes troubleshooting easier in case you make a
		    mistake in the policy rules and block your own
		    access to the firewall over the network.</para>

		  <para>For a larger installation (more people or long
		  policy) a faster CPU is needed.</para>

		  <para>The OS installed on the firewall machine
		    should be minimal. Basically, all you need is the
		    kernel, basic tools usually found in /bin, and
		    ssh. This is true regardless of what OS you
		    choose, so just follow installation instructions
		    appropriate for your OS. Do not install
		    development tools, X11, editors, graphics software
		    and so on and you'll be fine. Make sure you get
		    ssh, though, and in some cases you may need
		    Perl.</para>

		  <para>Once you install the firewall machine, check
		    if the ssh daemon is running. It usually is, but
		    some OS have different installation options and if
		    you choose "workstation" install, they may not
		    start ssh daemon automatically. Use <command>ps
		    -ax | grep sshd</command> to check if the daemon
		    is running, and if it is not, activate it.</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="diskless_firewall_configuration">
		  <title>Using Diskless Firewall Configuration</title>
                  
		  <para>Several projects came up with a decent
		  distributions intended for a small diskless
		  router/firewall. We have experience
		  with <ulink url="http://www.zelow.no/floppyfw/"><citetitle>floppyfw</citetitle></ulink>
		  and <ulink url="http://www.devil-linux.org"><citetitle>Devil
		  Linux</citetitle></ulink>, consequently Firewall
		  Builder has policy install scripts for these. The
		  advantage of using either one of these is that you
		  won't have to install OS and software on the
		  firewall machine; you just pop in a floppy or a
		  CD-ROM and boot from it. This is as close as it
		  comes to the firewall appliance, yet you get a
		  modern Linux kernel and iptables with both. The
		  whole OS is stored on the write-protected media and
		  can be easily replaced or upgraded simply by
		  changing the disk. Floppy FW comes on a single
		  floppy. (These guys managed to pack a kernel, a
		  busybox application and bunch of other programs on a
		  single compressed ram disk.) You don't get ssh with
		  floppyfw though. The firewall configuration is
		  located in a text file that can be edited off-line
		  and then written to the floppy. Firewall Builder's
		  install script also writes the firewall policy to
		  this floppy when you call main menu
		  item <guimenuitem>Rules/Install</guimenuitem>. Once
		  configuration is written to the floppy, you insert
		  it in the firewall and reboot. That's it.</para>

		  <para>Devil Linux comes on a CD-ROM and obviously
		  has lot more stuff on it. They also keep
		  configuration on a floppy disk. Firewall Builder's
		  install script writes firewall policy to this
		  floppy, which you then need to insert in the
		  firewall. See detailed documentation on
		  using <ulink url="http://www.devil-linux.org/home/index.php"><citetitle>Devil
		  Linux</citetitle></ulink> on their web site.</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="management_workstation">
		  <title>The Management Workstation</title>
                  
		  <para>The management workstation runs fwbuilder, so
		  it needs X11 and all other libraries fwbuilder
		  depends upon. Follow Installation instructions in
		  <xref linkend="install" /> to install fwbuilder on
		  the machine. Start fwbuilder by
		  typing <command>"fwbuilder"</command> at a shell
		  prompt to test it.</para>

		  <para>Once you get the Firewall Builder GUI up and
                    running on the management workstation, you need to
                    build a firewall policy and, eventually, compile
                    it and install on the firewall. Other sections of
                    this Guide describe all steps of this
                    process. Configuration of the built-in policy
                    installer and different ways to use it to install
                    and activate generated policy on the dedicated
                    firewall can be found in
                    <xref linkend="compile-install-detail" />.
		  </para>
		  
	        </sect1>
</chapter>
