    <sect2 id="using-action-reject">
      <title>Using Action 'Reject': blocking Ident protocol</title>

      <para>Suppose we want to block connections to certain ports on the
      server behind the firewall, but want to do it in a "polite" manner that
      lets the sender host know right away that the connection attempt
      was blocked so our server would look like nothing is listening on that
      port at all. One of the practical applications of this setup would be
      blocking Ident connections to a mail relay or a mail server. Sendmail
      and many other MTA's (Mail Transport Agents) attempt to connect to Ident
      port (TCP port 113) on the mail relay every time they accept email from
      that relay. Many believe Ident protocol is practically useless and does
      not really serve as a protection against SPAM or for any other useful
      purpose. Unfortunately silent blocking of ident connections on the
      firewall using a rule with action <emphasis>"Deny"</emphasis> adds a
      delay in the email delivery. This happens because when sender host tries
      to establish Ident connection to the recipient, it sends TCP SYN packet
      to it (the first packet in three-way TCP handshake) and then waits for
      TCP ACK packet in response. However, it never sees it because
      recipient's firewall blocked its first TCP SYN packet. In situations
      like this, the sender host assumes the reply packet got lost and tries to
      send TCP SYN packet again. It repeats this for a few seconds (usually 30
      sec) before it gives up. This adds 30 sec delay to email delivery. Our
      intent is to show how one can construct a policy rule to block Ident
      without causing this delay.</para>

      <para>The simplest way to block any protocol is to use "Deny"
      action in the policy rule. Since "Deny" causes firewall to
      silently drop the packet, sender never knows what happened to it
      and keeps waiting for response. To avoid this delay we will set
      rule Action to "Reject".  Normally "Reject" makes firewall to
      send ICMP "unreachable" message back to sender, thus indicating
      that access to requested port is denied by the firewall. This
      may be insufficient in some cases because the host trying to
      connect to our Ident port won't understand this type of ICMP
      message and will keep trying. In fact, most OS do not recognize
      ICMP "administratively prohibited" message and do keep
      trying. To make host on the other side stop its attempts right
      away we need to send TCP RST packet back instead of ICMP
      message. This can be done by setting the appropriate parameter
      for the "Reject" action. To set an Action parameter, change the
      Action to "Reject," then double-click the Reject icon to get the
      parameters dialog. (see <xref linkend="f-policy-7" />). It is
      also safe to turn stateful inspection off on this rule since we
      do not want connection to be established and therefore do not
      need to keep track of it.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Using action "Reject" with rule option</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="policy-6.png" />
      </figure>

      <figure id="f-policy-7">
        <title>Adding rule option to make send TCP RST packet</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="action-parameters-reject.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        Supported firewall platforms use different syntax for rules
        that should drop packets and send icmp or tcp rst back. Here
        is what Firewall Builder generates for the rule shown above
        for iptables:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# Rule 0 (global)
# 
$IPTABLES -A FORWARD -p tcp -m tcp  -d 192.168.1.100 --dport 113 \
    -j REJECT  --reject-with tcp-reset 
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        For PF it uses "return-rst" option:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# Rule  0 (global)
# 
block return-rst  quick inet proto tcp  from any  to 192.168.1.100 port 113 
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        There is no equivalent configuration option for PIX
      </para>


    </sect2>

