    <sect1 id="working_with_objects">
    <title>Working With Objects</title>

    <para>
    Firewall Builder is based on the concept of objects. There are
    a variety of different object types that can be used to define
    IP objects that can be used as the Source and Destination in
    your router access lists. Two of the most common IP objects used
    in firewall rules are <emphasis>Networks</emphasis> and 
    <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <bridgehead>Network Objects</bridgehead>

    <para>
    To create a Network object, for example a network to represent the
    10.10.10.0/24 network called "Production" shown in the diagram on 
    the previous page, go to the object tree on the left side of the 
    screen and double-click the folder labeled <emphasis>Objects</emphasis> 
    to expand it. Right click on the folder called <emphasis>Networks
    </emphasis> and select “New Network”. This creates a new network 
    object. In the lower portion of your screen, called the Editor 
    Panel, you can modify the properties of this object.
    </para>

    <para>
    Change the object name to something that matches the function, in 
    this example we are going to call it “Production Network” to represent 
    the network connected to the interface on the router that we configured 
    with the label "production". The address is set to 10.10.10.0 and the 
    netmask is 255.255.255.0.
    </para>

  <figure id="new_network">
    <title>New Network Object</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/ios_new_network.png" />
  </figure> 

  <note>
    <para>
    When editing the attributes of an object there is no Apply
    or Submit button. Once you edit an attribute as soon as you move 
    away from the field you were editing the change will take effect 
    immediately.
    </para>
  </note>

    <bridgehead>Address Objects</bridgehead>

    <para>
    To create an object that represents a single IP address, similar 
    to the host parameter in a Cisco access list, go to the object tree 
    and right-click on the <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis> folder and 
    select "New Address". In the Editor Panel change the name of the 
    object to something that reflects its function, for example “POP3 
    Server”, and set the IP address.
    </para>

  <figure id="new_address_steps">
    <title>New Address Object</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/new_address_steps.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  You may have noticed that we did not create any objects for the 
  TCP services, like HTTP and SSH, that will be needed for the 
  firewall rules shown in the example. This is because Firewall 
  Builder comes with hundreds of predefined objects for commonly 
  used objects like TCP services.
  </para>
        
 </sect1>

