<sect1 id="ios_creating_firewall">
  <title>Define The Router</title>

  <para>
  Firewall Builder refers to devices that support filtering rules as
  firewalls. To create a firewall object to represent your router
  click on the “Create new firewall” icon on the main window of
  Firewall Builder. This will launch a wizard that walks you through
  creating your router.
  </para>

  <para>
  Enter a name for the firewall object, in this example we will use
  <emphasis>la-rtr-1</emphasis>. Change the drop down menu for software 
  that is running on the firewall to be “Cisco IOS ACL”.
  </para>

  <figure id="gs_acl_create_router">
  <title>New Firewall Dialog</title>      
  <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/create_router.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  Click the "Next >" button to continue to the next step in the wizard.
  </para>

  <para>
  When creating a firewall in Firewall Builder you have a choice of
  configuring interfaces manually, or you can use SNMP discovery if you
  have SNMP enabled on your router and you have know the Read-Only or
  Read-Write community string. For this example we are going to configure
  the router interfaces manually.
  </para>

  <figure id="gs_acl_interface_discovery">
  <title>Select Interface Configuration Method</title>      
  <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/interface_discovery.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  Click the "Next >" button to continue to the next step.
  </para>

  <para>
  The firewall that you create in Firewall Builder needs to match the router
  that you want to deploy the access lists on.  This means that the <emphasis>interface 
  names</emphasis> and <emphasis>IP addresses</emphasis> in the firewall object that you are
  creating must <emphasis>match exactly</emphasis> to what is configured on the router.
  </para>

  <para>
  Click the green <imagedata fileref="images/green_plus.png" /> 
  icon to add a new interface to the router.  Enter the name of the router
  exactly as it is shown on a router command line when you run “show ip
  interfaces brief” command. In our example the interfaces are
  FastEthernet0/0 and FastEthernet0/1.
  </para>

  <para>
  Set the interface name as FastEthernet0/0 and set the label to outside. Click
  on the Add address button and set the IP address to 192.0.2.1 with a netmask
  of 255.255.255.240.
  </para>

  <figure id="gs_acl_interface_address">
  <title>Set Interface IP Address</title>      
  <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/interface_address.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  Click the green <imagedata fileref="images/green_plus.png" /> 
  icon to add another interface to the router.  Enter the information
  in to the wizard to match the second interface as follows:
  </para>
     
  <figure id="gs_acl_interface_address2">
  <title>Interface Tabs</title>      
  <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/interface_address2.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  Click on the Finish button.
  </para>

  <para>
  After you create the firewall object representing the router that
  you will be installing the access lists on will be displayed in
  the object tree on the left side.  The Policy object, which is where
  the access list rules are configured, is automatically opened in
  the main window.
  </para>

  <figure id="gs_acl_firewall_object_tree">
  <title>Firewall Displayed in Object Tree</title>      
  <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/firewall_object_tree.png" />
  </figure> 

  <para>
  Before moving on you should save our data file that contains the new
  firewall object that you just created.  Do this by going to the
  File -> Save As menu item.  Choose a name and location to save the
  file to.
  </para>

</sect1>

