    <sect1 id="import_firewall">
      <title>Importing Existing Firewall Configurations into Firewall Builder</title>

          <para>
            Existing firewall configurations can be imported into 
            Firewall Builder using the Import Firewall wizard. Import 
            is supported for the following platforms.
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>iptables</listitem>
            <listitem>Cisco IOS router access-lists</listitem>
            <listitem>Cisco ASA / Cisco PIX (requires Firewall Builder V4.2 or greater)</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
            
      <sect2 id="import_firewall_overview">
      <title>Importing Existing Firewall Configurations</title>

      <para>
        To start the Import Firewall wizard select the File -> 
        Import Firewall menu item. This launches the wizard 
        as shown in <xref linkend="import_firewall_dialog-1"/>.
      </para>

      <figure id="import_firewall_dialog-1">
        <title>Main Import Firewall Wizard</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/import_firewall_dialog-1.png"/>
      </figure>
              
      <para>
        To start the import process, use the Browse function to select 
        the file that contains the firewall configuration that you want 
        to import.
      </para>

      <note>
      <bridgehead>iptables</bridgehead>
        <para>
          The configuration file format must be in the iptables-save 
          format. For example, run the "iptables-save > myfirewall.conf" command 
          on the firewall you want to import, transfer that file to the system 
          running the Firewall Builder application and select this file in the 
          import wizard.
        </para>

      <bridgehead>Cisco IOS router access-lists</bridgehead>
        <para>
          Cisco IOS router access-lists must be in the format displayed when 
          the "show run" command is executed. Copy the output from the "show 
          run" command to a file on the system that Firewall Builder is running 
          on.
        </para>

      <bridgehead>Cisco ASA / Cisco PIX</bridgehead>
        <para>
          Cisco ASA and Cisco PIX configurations must be in the format displayed 
          when the "show run" command is executed. Copy the output from the "show 
          run" command to a file an the system that Firewall Builder is running 
          on.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        After you have selected the configuration file to import click on the 
        Continue button. 
      </para>
          
      <para>
        Firewall Builder will automatically detect the type of configuration 
        file that is being imported and will display a preview of the file 
        in the window.
      </para>

      <figure id="import_firewall_dialog-2">
        <title>Import Firewall Wizard - Configuration Preview</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/import_firewall_dialog-2.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>
        Click the Continue button. On the next page, shown in 
        <xref linkend="import_firewall_dialog-3"/>, enter a name for the firewall 
        object that will be created.
      </para>

      <figure id="import_firewall_dialog-3">
        <title>Import Firewall Wizard - Set Firewall Name</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/import_firewall_dialog-3.png"/>
      </figure>

      <note>
      <para>
        By default, the option to "Find and use existing objects" is enabled. 
        When this option is enabled Firewall Builder will attempt to match elements 
        in in the firewall's configuration file with objects that are already 
        configured in the Firewall Builder object tree. This includes both Standard 
        Library objects and objects the user has created.
      </para>

      <para>
        For example, if an imported firewall configuration file has an object 
        or rule that uses TCP port 22, SSH, Firewall Builder will match that to 
        the pre-existing Standard ssh object instead of creating a new TCP service 
        object.
      </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        After entering the firewall object name, click Commit. Firewall Builder 
        will show a log of the import process and will include any warning messages 
        in blue colored text and any error messages in red colored text. 
      </para>
        
      <figure id="import_firewall_dialog-4">
        <title>Import Firewall Wizard - Import Process Log</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/import_firewall_dialog-4.png"/>
      </figure>
        
       <para> 
        Depending on the platform, this will either be the final step of the 
        wizard or the user will be guided through platform specific 
        configuration activities.
      </para>
      
      <bridgehead>Cisco ASA/PIX/FWSM</bridgehead>

      <note>
      <para>
        Firewall Builder will not properly import objects whose names start 
        with a number instead of a letter.  For example, an object group with 
        the name "10-net" will not be imported, but the object group with the 
        name "net-10" will be imported.
      </para>
      </note> 
              
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>iptables Import Example</title>

        <para>
          For this example we are going to import a very basic iptables 
          configuration from a firewall that matches the diagram in 
          <xref linkend="iptables_import_diagram"/>.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables_import_diagram">
          <title>Firewall Example</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_diagram.png"/>
        </figure>

          <para>
            Firewall Builder imports iptables configs in the format of 
            iptables-save. Script <command>iptables-save</command> is part
            of the standard iptables install and should be
            present on all Linux distribution. Usually this
            script is installed in <emphasis>/sbin/</emphasis>. 
          </para>
            
          <para>
            When you run this script, it dumps the current iptables 
            configuration to stdout. It reads iptables rules directly form 
            the kernel rather than from some file, so what it dumps is what 
            is really working right now. To import this into Firewall Builder, 
            run the script to save the configuration to a file:
          </para>
  
<programlisting>
iptables-save &gt; linux-1.conf
</programlisting>

          <para>
            As you can see in the output below, the linux-1.conf iptables 
            configuration is very simple with only a few filter rules and one 
            nat rule.
          </para>
          
<programlisting>
# Completed on Mon Apr 11 21:23:33 2011
# Generated by iptables-save v1.4.4 on Mon Apr 11 21:23:33 2011
*filter
:INPUT DROP [145:17050]
:FORWARD DROP [0:0]
:OUTPUT DROP [1724:72408]
:LOGDROP - [0:0]
-A INPUT -m state --state RELATED,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth1 -s 10.10.10.0/24 -d 10.10.10.1/32 -p tcp -m tcp --dport 22 -m state --state NEW -j ACCEPT
-A FORWARD -m state --state RELATED,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
-A FORWARD -o eth0 -s 10.10.10.0/24 -p tcp -m tcp --dport 80 -m state --state NEW -j ACCEPT
-A FORWARD -o eth0 -s 10.10.10.0/24 -p tcp -m tcp --dport 443 -m state --state NEW -j ACCEPT
-A FORWARD -j LOGDROP
-A LOGDROP -j LOG
-A LOGDROP -j DROP
COMMIT
# Completed on Mon Apr 11 21:23:33 2011
# Generated by iptables-save v1.4.4 on Mon Apr 11 21:23:33 2011
*nat
:PREROUTING ACCEPT [165114:22904965]
:OUTPUT ACCEPT [20:1160]
:POSTROUTING ACCEPT [20:1160]
-A POSTROUTING -s 10.10.10.0/24 -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
COMMIT
# Completed on Mon Apr 11 21:23:33 2011
</programlisting> 

          <para>
            If you are running Firewall Builder on a different system than the 
            one that is running iptables copy <filename>linux-1.conf</filename> 
            from the firewall to the system where Firewall Builder is running.
          </para>

          <para>
            Launch the Import wizard by selecting the File -> Import Firewall menu 
            item.
          </para>

          <para>
            Click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> to find <filename>linux-1.conf</filename>. 
          </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-example-1">
          <title>Select File containing iptables-save data</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_select_file.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Click <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> to move to the next window which 
          shows a preview of the configuration file that will be imported and the 
          type of firewall that Firewall Builder has detected it to be.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-preview-1">
          <title>Preview showing detected platform and configuration data</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_preview.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Next you need to enter a name for the firewall. This is the name that will 
          be used in Firewall Builder to refer to the firewall after it is imported. When 
          you click the Commit button the configuration data will be read.
        </para>

        <para>
          By default, Firewall Builder attempts to detect if there are items, like IP 
          addresses, used in the rules that match existing items in the object tree. 
          If there is a match the existing item is used, if there is no match a new 
          object is created. This feature can be disabled by unchecking the box next 
          to "Find an use existing objects" which will result in objects being 
          created for evry item used in the imported rules regardless of whether it 
          already exists in the object tree or no.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-name-1">
          <title>Entering the Name of the Firewall</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_name_fw.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          After the import is complete, Firewall Builder displays a log showing 
          all the actions that were taken during the import. Warning messages are 
          displayed in blue font and Error messages are displayed in red.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-log-1">
          <title>Import Log with Status and Warning/Error Messages</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_log.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          The program tries to interpret the configuration file rule by rule 
          and recreates the equivalent rule in Firewall Builder. The progress 
          window displays warning and error messages, if any, as well as some 
          diagnostics that shows network and service objects created in the 
          process. 
        </para>

        <note>
        <para>
         Firewall Builder detected that there are rules in the iptables configuration 
         that allow RELATED and ESTABLISHED traffic through the firewall. This behavior 
         can be controlled by a setting in Firewall Builder, so a warning message is 
         shown.
        </para>
        </note>

        <para>
          Click the Done button to complete the firewall import.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          After the import is completed, the newly created firewall object will be 
          displayed in the object tree. If you expand the Objects system folder, as 
          shown in <xref linkend="iptables-import-object-tree-1" />, you can also see 
          the Address and Network objects that were created during the import process.
        </para>
        
        <figure id="iptables-import-object-tree-1">
          <title>Imported Firewall and Created Objects in Object Tree</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_object_tree.png"/>
        </figure>

        <sect3 id="iptables-import-post-processing">
        <title>Common iptables Post-Import Actions</title>

        <para>
          After the firewall object is created in the object tree there are typically 
          a few more steps required in order to be able to manage your firewall 
          configuration using Firewall Builder.
        </para>

        <bridgehead>Interfaces</bridgehead>
         
        <para>
          There is not enough information in the iptables configuration for Firewall 
          Builder to deterministically determine what interfaces and IP addresses are 
          configured on the firewall. During the import if a rule contains either "-i" 
          or "-o" interface references Firewall Builder will add the interface to the 
          firewall object, but some interfaces may not be used in rules and therefore 
          will not be detected.
        </para>

        <para>
          In the example configuration that was imported for linux-1, both the eth0 and 
          eth1 interfaces were used in the configuration, so the firewall object includes 
          these interfaces. By default Firewall Builder marks these interfaces as 
          Unnumbered.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          To update the eth0 interface, double-click it to open it for editing. 
          <xref linkend="iptables-import-update-interface-1"/> shows how to set a label 
          for the interface and to identify that it should have a static IP address.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-update-interface-1">
          <title>Editing Parameters for eth0</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_edit_interface_params.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Right-click the interface and select New Address to add an IP address 
          to the interface as shown in <xref linkend="iptables-import-update-interface-2"/>. 
          Set the IP address and netmask to match your environment.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-update-interface-2">
          <title>Setting IP Address for eth0</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_edit_interface_params-2.png"/>
        </figure>

        <note>
        <para>
          You may also need to add additional interfaces to the firewall object depending 
          on what Firewall Builder was able to detect from the iptables rules. To add a 
          new interface right-click the firewall object (in our example linux-1) and 
          select New Interface. Add the interface name and label and set the type. The 
          default type is Static IP address.
        </para>
        </note>

        <bridgehead>Rules</bridgehead>

        <para>
          During the import of the linux-1.conf file. Firewall Builder displayed a 
          warning message that there were rules defined to allow RELATED and ESTABLISHED 
          traffic to the firewall. Instead of having to explicitly have a rule for 
          this, Firewall Builder has a configuration option controlling this behavior.
        </para>

        <para>
          To view the configuration option controlling RELATED and ESTABLISHED traffic 
          double-click on the firewall object and click on the Firewall Settings button 
          in the Editor Panel. The dialog window will open with the Compiler tab selected. 
          About halfway down the window is the checkbox that controls RELATED and 
          ESTABLISHED traffic, which is enabled by default.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-settings">
          <title>Firewall Settings Option for Controlling RELATED and ESTABLISHED Traffic</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_options.png"/>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Since the default is to allow RELATED and ESTABLISHED traffic, the imported 
          rules 0 and 2 are not necessary. To remove these rules right-click the rule 
          number and select Remove Rule. 
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-remove-rules">
          <title>Removing Unnecessary Rules for RELATED and ESTABLISHED</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_remove_rule.png"/>
        </figure>

        <note>
        <para>
          The specific rule numbers will vary based on your configuration, but the rules 
          created for matching RELATED and ESTABLISHED traffic are identifiable by the use 
          of the predefined ESTABLISHED objct in the Service field of the rule.
        </para>
        </note>

        <bridgehead>NAT rules</bridgehead>

        <para>
          To view the imported NAT rules, double-click the NAT object under the linux-1 
          object in the tree. In this example, there is a single source NAT rule that translates 
          inside addresses to the eth0 (outside) interface of the firewall.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-nat-rules">
          <title>NAT Rules</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_nat_rules.png"/>
        </figure>

        <bridgehead>User-Defined Chains</bridgehead>
        
        <para>
          If your iptables configuration includes user-defined chains, Firewall Builder will 
          create a new Policy object for each user chain and will use the Branch feature to 
          jump from the main Policy to the user chain Policy. In our example linux-1.conf 
          configuration there is a user chain called LOGDROP that has 2 rules. The first 
          rule logs the packet and the second rule drops it.
        </para>

        <para>
          To view the rules in the LOGDROP policy, double-click the LOGDROP policy object 
          located under the linux-1 firewall object. This will open the rules in the Rules 
          Editor as shown in <xref linkend="iptables-import-logdrop-rules"/>.
        </para>

        <figure id="iptables-import-logdrop-rules">
          <title>Rules in LOGDROP policy</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="network_discovery/images/iptables_import_logdrop_rules.png"/>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

     </sect2>
    </sect1>
