    <sect1 id="network-discovery">
      <title>Network Discovery</title>

      <para>
        Another powerful way to find addresses of subnets and hosts on
        the network is to use the SNMP crawler.
      </para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-seed">
        <title>Initial Parameters for the Network Discovery Program</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid2.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        The Network Discovery program (sometimes referred to as the
        "Network Crawler") needs a host from which to start. This host is called the
        "seed host"; you enter it in the first page of the Druid (
        <xref linkend="discovery-snmp-seed" />). The crawler implements the following
        algorithm (this is a somewhat simplified explanation):</para>

      <para>
        First, it runs several SNMP queries against the seed host
        trying to collect the list of its interfaces and its ARP and
        routing tables. This host is then added to the table of
        discovered network objects, together with the host's interfaces,
        their addresses and netmasks, and the host's "sysinfo"
        parameters. Then the crawler analyses the routing table of
        that host; this allows it to discover the networks and
        subnets, which in turn are also added to the list of
        discovered objects. Then it analyses the ARP table, which
        holds MAC and IP addresses of neighboring hosts. It takes one
        host at a time from this table and repeats the same algorithm,
        using the new host as a seed host. When it pulls an ARP table
        from the next host, it discards entries that describe objects
        it already knows about. However, if it finds new entries, it
        tries them as well and thus travels further down the
        network. Eventually, it will visit every host on all subnets on
        the network.
      </para>

      <para>
        This algorithm relies on hosts answering SNMP
        queries. If the very first host (the "seed" host) does not run
        an SNMP agent, the crawler will stop on the first run of its
        algorithm and won't find anything. Therefore, it is important
        to use a host which does run an SNMP agent as a "seed" host. Even
        if most of the hosts on the network do not run SNMP agents,
        but a few do, the crawler will most likely find all of
        them. This happens because it discovers objects when it reads
        the ARP tables from the host which answers; so even if
        discovered hosts do not answer to SNMP queries, the crawler
        can discover them.
      </para>

      <para>
        One of the ways to limit the scope of the network that the
        crawler visits is to use the "Confine scan to the network"
        parameter. You need to enter both a network address and a
        netmask; the crawler will then check if the hosts it discovers
        belong to this network and if they do not, discard
        them.
      </para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-options">
        <title>Parameters for Network Discovery: Page 1</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid3.png" />
      </figure>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-options2">
        <title>Parameters for Network Discovery: Page 2</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid4.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        There are a few settings that affect the crawler's algorithm (see
        <xref linkend="discovery-snmp-options" /> and
        <xref linkend="discovery-snmp-options2" />). Here is the list:
      </para>

      <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Run network scan recursively</para>

            <para>As was described above, the crawler starts with the "seed"
            host and then repeats its algorithm using every discovered host as
            a new "seed". If this option is turned OFF, then the crawler runs
            its algorithm only once and stops.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Follow point-to-point links</para>

            <para>If a firewall or router has a point-to-point interface
            (for example, PPP interface), then the crawler can automatically
            calculate the IP address of the other side of this interface. It
            then continues the discovery process by querying a router on the
            other side. Very often, the point-to-point link connects the
            organization's network to an ISP and you are not really interested
            in collecting data about your ISP network. By default, the crawler
            does not cross point-to-point links, but this option, if activated,
            permits it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Include virtual addresses</para>

            <para>Sometimes servers or routers have more than one IP address
            assigned to the same interface. If this option is turned on, the
            crawler "discovers" these virtual addresses and tries to create
            objects for them.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run reverse name lookup queries to determine host
            names</para>

            <para>If a host discovered by the crawler answers to SNMP
            queries, it report its name, which the crawler uses to
            create an object in Firewall Builder. However, if the host does
            not answer the query, the crawler cannot determine its name and
            only knows its IP address. The crawler can use DNS to back-resolve
            such addresses and determine host names if this option is turned
            ON.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>SNMP (and DNS) query parameters</para>

            <para>You must specify the SNMP "read" community string
            to be used for SNMP queries. You can also specify
            the number of retries and a timeout for the query. (The
            number of retries and timeout parameters also apply to DNS
            and reverse DNS queries.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Once all parameters are entered, the crawler actually gets to
      work, which may take a while. Depending on the size of the network and
      such parameters as the SNMP timeout value, scanning may take minutes or
      even hours. The progress of the scanner can be monitored on the page in
      the Druid (<xref linkend="discovery-snmp-crawler" />) and (<xref linkend="discovery-snmp-crawler2" />). You can always
      stop the crawler using the <guibutton>"Stop network scan"</guibutton>
      button. Data does not get lost if you do this as the Druid will use
      whatever objects the crawler discovered before you stopped it.</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-crawler">
        <title>The SNMP Crawler Status</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid6.png" />
      </figure>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-crawler2">
        <title>The SNMP Crawler Status (More)</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid7.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>The <guibutton>"Save scan log to file"</guibutton> button saves
      the content of the progress window to a text file and is mostly used for
      troubleshooting and bug reports related to the crawler.</para>

      <para>
        If the crawler succeeded and was able to collect information
        it needed to create objects, you can switch to the next page
        where you choose and create objects.
      </para>

      <figure id="discovery-druid-8">
        <title>Creating Networks Using Gathered Information</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid8.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>This part of the Druid is the same for all discovery methods.</para>

      <para>The left column shows the networks that were
      discovered. The right column shows the network objects that will
      be created. To start with, the right column is empty.</para>

      <para>This page of the Druid also has the following buttons:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><guibutton>Select All</guibutton></para>

            <para>Selects all records in the column.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guibutton>Unselect All</guibutton></para>

            <para>Deselects all records in the column.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guibutton>Filter</guibutton></para>

            <para>Brings up a filter dialog. Filtering helps manage long lists
            of objects.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guibutton>Remove Filter</guibutton></para>

            <para>Removes the currently applied filter and shows all records
            in the table.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Druid can filter records in the table either by their address,
      by their name, or by both. To filter by address enter part of it in the
      "Address" field. The program compares the text entered in the filter
      dialog with an address in the table and shows only those records whose
      address starts with the text of the filter. For example, to only filter
      out hosts with addresses on the net 10.3.14.0 we could use the filter
      "10.3.14". Likewise, to remove hosts "bear" and "beaver" (addresses
      10.3.14.50 and 10.3.14.74) we could use the filter "10.3.14.6". Note
      that the filter string does not contain any wildcard symbols like "*".
      The filter shows only records that have addresses which literally match
      the filter string.</para>

      <para>Filtering by the object name uses the POSIX regular expressions
      syntax described in the manual page regex(7). For example, to find all
      records whose names start with "f" we could use the regular expression
      "^f". The "^" symbol matches the beginning of the string, so this
      regular expression matches any name that starts with "f". To find all
      names that end with "somedomain.com", we could use the regular
      expression ".*somedomain.com$"</para>

      <para>Once you have reviewed the discovered networks, decide
      which ones you want to turn into Network objects. Then, copy
      those networks to the right column.</para>

      <para>To populate the right column with objects, select the
      networks you want, then click the right arrow (--&gt;) to put
      them in the right column.</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-2a">
        <title>Creating Networks Using Gathered Information (more)</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid9.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. The discovered hosts list displays:</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-2b">
        <title>Creating Hosts Using Gathered Information</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid10.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Again, populate the right column with the objects you want to create:</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-2c">
        <title>Creating Hosts Using Gathered Information (More)</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid11.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. The final object list displays:</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-2d">
        <title>List of Objects</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid12.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Here you can specify which type of object will be created
      for each discovered item: address, host, or firewall. Here, we
      are changing the object "sveasoft (10.3.14.202)" from a host to
      a firewall:</para>

      <figure id="discovery-snmp-2e">
        <title>Specify Type of Object</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid13.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. The target library control appears:</para>

       <figure id="discovery-snmp-2f">
        <title>Target Library</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid14.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Here you can specify which library the objects will appear
      in. Normally this would be User, unless you have created a
      user-defined library. Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>The wizard finishes processing, and your new objects appear in your library:</para>

       <figure id="discovery-snmp-2g">
        <title>Target Library</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="network_discovery/images/discovery-druid15.png" />
      </figure>


    </sect1>

