<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

  <sect1 id="object-types">
    <title>Types of Objects</title>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder supports a variety of object types, both
      simple and complex. Simple object types include Address,
      Network, Host, and IP, TCP, UDP and ICMP service objects. More
      complex object types are Firewall, Address Table, DNS Name, and
      User Service.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are the following types of objects in Firewall
      Builder:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Addressable objects:
          <xref linkend="addressable-objects" /> describes
          objects that have, either directly or indirectly, an
          address of some kind. This category includes the
          physical objects (firewalls, hosts, interfaces) as
          well as some logical objects (networks, address
          ranges, individual addresses). Addressable objects can
          be grouped together into Object groups.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Service objects:
          <xref linkend="working-with-services" /> describes
          objects that represent services. They include IP, TCP,
          UDP, and ICMP services, as well as user
          services. Service objects can be grouped together into
          Service groups.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Time Interval objects: Described in
          <xref linkend="time-interval-objects" />, these
          represent a discreet or recurring period of time. They
          can be used as part of a rule in the firewall. For
          example, you could have a rule that matches on
          weekends, but not during the week.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Rule set objects: Described in
	  <xref linkend="rule-set-objects" />, these represent
	  the various rule sets in a firewall. By default, a
	  firewall starts with one access policy, one NAT, and
	  one routing rule set, but you can add more of
	  each. Rule set objects only exist as child objects of
	  a firewall.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      All objects in Firewall Builder have some characteristics
      in common.
    </para>

    <para>
      All objects have a <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field and
      a <guilabel>Comment</guilabel> field. The Name field can contain
      white spaces and can be arbitrarily long (though shorter names
      work better in the GUI). The Comment field can contain any text
      of any length.
    </para>

  </sect1>
