  <sect1 id="diskless_firewall_configuration">

    <title>Using Diskless Firewall Configuration</title>
    
    <para>
      Several projects came up with a decent distributions intended
      for a small diskless router/firewall. We have experience
      with <ulink url="http://www.zelow.no/floppyfw/"><citetitle>floppyfw</citetitle></ulink>
      and <ulink url="http://www.devil-linux.org"><citetitle>Devil
      Linux</citetitle></ulink>, consequently Firewall Builder has
      policy install scripts for these. The advantage of using either
      one of these is that you won't have to install OS and software
      on the firewall machine; you just pop in a floppy or a CD-ROM
      and boot from it. This is as close as it comes to the firewall
      appliance, yet you get a modern Linux kernel and iptables with
      both. The whole OS is stored on the write-protected media and
      can be easily replaced or upgraded simply by changing the
      disk. Floppy FW comes on a single floppy. (These guys managed to
      pack a kernel, a busybox application and bunch of other programs
      on a single compressed ram disk.) You don't get ssh with
      floppyfw though. The firewall configuration is located in a text
      file that can be edited off-line and then written to the
      floppy. Firewall Builder's install script also writes the
      firewall policy to this floppy when you call main menu
      item <guimenuitem>Rules/Install</guimenuitem>. Once
      configuration is written to the floppy, you insert it in the
      firewall and reboot. That's it.
    </para>

    <para>
      Devil Linux comes on a CD-ROM and obviously has lot more stuff
      on it. They also keep configuration on a floppy disk. Firewall
      Builder's install script writes firewall policy to this floppy,
      which you then need to insert in the firewall. See detailed
      documentation on
      using <ulink url="http://www.devil-linux.org/home/index.php"><citetitle>Devil
      Linux</citetitle></ulink> on their web site.
    </para>
  </sect1>

