<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="remote-management">
  <title>Manage your firewall remotely</title>

  <para>
    This chapter explains how to set up a firewall on a small
    dedicated machine and use a separate workstations to manage it.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The best way to utilize the flexibility of Firewall Builder and to
    minimize the risk to your network is to run Firewall Builder on a
    dedicated management workstation. This workstation will have the
    near-full installation of Linux or FreeBSD, complete with X11 and
    Gnome or KDE. Alternatively, it can be a Mac or Windows PC.
  </para>

  <para>
    The reason we do not recommend running X11 and GUI environment on
    the firewall is actually rather simple. It is well known that
    complex programs are more prone to errors than simple and short
    ones. X11 and GUI environments are
    <emphasis>very</emphasis> complex programs, rivaling or exceeding
    the Linux kernel in size. Granted, you may be safe if you run
    these on the firewall provided you install all the latest patches
    and keep your software up-to-date. This, however, means a lot of
    effort and time spent on maintaining software that is not
    essential to the operation of the firewall and is being used only
    once in a while. You may add protection using firewall rules to
    block all access to the firewall itself from outside (a very good
    idea regardless whether you run X11 on it), but then you need to
    carefully watch your policy to make sure you don't drop these
    rules accidentally. The rules may get more complex if you ever
    need to manage your firewall remotely, making verification
    difficult. All this adds up to the risk factor, so it is just a
    lot simpler to not have X11 and GUI on the firewall at all.
  </para>

  <para>
    In other words, run X11 and GUI environment on the firewall
    machine only when you have a definite reason to do so, and keep an
    open eye on it.
  </para>

  <para>
    We will look at configuring the dedicated firewall machine and
    then at configuring the management workstation.
  </para>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="firewall_setup.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="diskless_firewall_config.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="mgmt_workstation.xml"/>

</chapter>
