  <sect1 id="compile-and-install-options">
    <title>Different ways to compile</title>

    <para>
      There are several ways to compile and install a policy,
      summarized here. The actual results are described in more detail
      in later sections of this chapter.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <figure id="top-toolbar-icons-1">
            <title>Icons in the main toolbar</title>
            <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/top-toolbar-icons.png" />
          </figure>

          The hammer icon in the topmost toolbar (on the left) lets
          you compile, but not install, one or more of the firewalls
          or clusters in the object file. The arrow-and-wall icon lets
          you both compile and install firewalls.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The main menu items <guimenuitem>Rules >
          Compile</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Rules >
          Install</guimenuitem> menu selections also let you compile,
          or compile and install, one or more firewalls or clusters.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <figure id="small-toolbar-icons-1">
            <title>Icons in the toolbar specific to the currently opened firewall</title>
            <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-2b.png" />
          </figure>

          The hammer icon in the policy (on the right) toolbar
          lets you compile, but not install, the firewall of the
          current policy. The arrow-and-wall icon in the policy
          toolbar lets you both compile and install
          it. <emphasis>Note that this compiles the firewall of
            the shown policy. Double-clicking a different firewall
            to bring up that firewall's object editor does not
            change the policy shown, and does not change which
            firewall will be compiled.</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <guimenuitem>Compile</guimenuitem>
          and <guimenuitem>Install</guimenuitem> menu selections in
          the right-click context menu
          (<xref linkend="compile-install-firewall-options1"/>) let
          you do a compile or compile-and-install on the firewall that
          you selected. You can ctrl-click or shift-click to select
          more than one firewall or cluster.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          To compile a single rule, select it in the rule set, right-click it and select
          <guimenuitem>Compile</guimenuitem>. Or, select a rule, then press X on the keyboard.
          This only compiles the single rule and shows the result. This function does
          not produce a firewall script.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-options1">
      <title>Compile and install options in the context menu that appears when you right-click on a firewall or cluster object in the t
ree</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-options1.png"/>
    </figure>

  </sect1>

