  <sect1 id="bsd">
    <title>OpenBSD and FreeBSD</title>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder supports configuring pf, ipfilter, and ipfw 
      rules for OpenBSD and FreeBSD systems. 
    </para>

    <sect2 id="bsd-pf">
    <title>PF</title>

    <para>
    To create a new pf firewall, select the PF platform option on 
    the first page of the New Firewall wizard. You must also choose 
    whether the firewall will be running on OpenBSD (the default) or 
    FreeBSD.
    </para>

    <figure id="new-pf-fw">
      <title>New Firewall Wizard - PF Firewall</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_os/images/new-pf-fw.png" />
    </figure>

    <sect3 id="bsd-pf-freebsd">
    <title>FreeBSD</title>

    <para>
    Starting in Firewall Builder V4.2 there are two supported modes 
    for generating pf firewall configurations on FreeBSD systems.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>Standard Mode - in this case, Firewall Builder generates 
      both a pf.conf-style configuration file and a .fw activation script.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>rc.conf Mode - in this case, Firewall Builder generates 
      both a pf.conf-style configuration file and an rc.conf.local style 
      configuration file.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <note>
    <para>
    By default, file names use the name of the firewall object as the 
    base of the filename. For example, a firewall named "guardian" would 
    generate files called guardian.conf (pf.conf-style commands) and 
    guardian.fw (bash shell activation script OR rc.conf.local-style 
    settings).
    </para>

    <para>
    You can override the default file names by changing the settings 
    in the Firewall Settings on the Compiler tab.
    </para>
    </note>

    <figure id="file-names">
      <title>Firewall Settings - Changing File Names</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_os/images/file-names.png" />
    </figure>

    <bridgehead>Standard Mode</bridgehead>

    <para>
    In this mode, Firewall Builder generates a firewall.conf file that 
    uses the same style as pf.conf. By default, Firewall Builder will 
    install this file in /etc. You can update the installation location 
    by clicking the Installer tab in the Firewall Settings. The first 
    entry is directory location on the firewall.
    </para>

    <para>
    Firewall Builder also generates a firewall.fw file when it is 
    configured in Standard mode. This is a bash shell script file that 
    sets interface IP addresses, create static routes, etc., if these 
    options have been selected in Firewall Settings.
    </para>

    <para>
    This is the default mode and you don't need to change any settings 
    to use Firewall Builder in this mode with your PF firewall running 
    on FreeBSD.
    </para>

    <bridgehead>rc.conf Mode</bridgehead>

    <para>
    To switch from Standard Mode to rc.conf mode open the Firewall 
    Settings window. Click onthe tab labeled Script. If your host OS 
    is set to FreeBSD you will see two radio buttons at the top of 
    the window to set the initialization mode. Select the radio button 
    next to the "file in rc.conf format" option.
    </para>
     
    <figure id="rc-conf-mode">
      <title>Firewall Settings - Changing Mode</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_os/images/rc-conf-mode.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>
    In this mode, the generated firewall.conf file is the 
    same as the firewall.conf file that is generated in the Standard 
    Mode.
    </para>

    <para>
    Instead of a bash shell script in this mode the initialization file, 
    firewall.fw, will be in rc.conf settings format as shown below.
    </para>

    <figure id="rc-conf-output">
      <title>Example Generated firewall.fw in rc.conf Format</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_os/images/rc-conf-output.png" />
    </figure>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="bsd-pf-openbsd">
    <title>OpenBSD</title>

    <para>
    Firewall Builder only supports Standard Mode, which is where a bash 
    script file is generated to configure system parameters such as interface 
    IP addresses, for OpenBSD systems. The rc.conf option format is 
    disabled for OpenBSD systems as shown below.
    </para>

    <figure id="openbsd-init-options">
      <title>rc.conf Format Option Disabled for OpenBSD</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_os/images/openbsd-init-options.png" />
    </figure>

    </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bsd-ipfilter">
    <title>ipfilter</title>

    <para>
      For <emphasis>ipfilter</emphasis>, Firewall Builder generates
      three files: the firewall-ipf.conf file with filter rules,
      firewall-nat.conf file with NAT rules, and firewall.fw with
      a policy activation script.
    </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bsd-ipfw">
    <title>ipfw</title>

    <para>
      For <emphasis>ipfw</emphasis>, a single script, firewall.fw, is
      generated. This script does all the prepararory work and then
      loads ipfw rules.
    </para>

    </sect2>

    <para>
      By default, generated scripts are installed in the /etc/fw/
      directory on the firewall and the work of making sure they are
      executed on system start-up is left for the administrator. See
      <xref linkend="load_policy_on_reboot"/> for some recommended
      ways to do this.
    </para>

  </sect1>

