    <sect1 id="rpm_installation">
      <title>RPM-Based Distributions (Red Hat, Fedora, OpenSUSE, and Others)</title>
      <para>Using pre-built binary RPMs</para>

      <para>You need to download and install two RPMs:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Example: <filename>libfwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.rpm</filename>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Example: <filename>fwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.rpm</filename>
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To satisfy dependencies, you need the following packages installed on your system:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>libxml2 v2.4.10 or newer
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>libxslt v1.0.7 o newer
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>ucd-snmp or net-snmp
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>QT 4.3.x, 4.4.x, 4.5.x, 4.6.x. Firewall Builder uses
            features available in QT 4.3 and later; the system does not support version 4.2 and earlier.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
        <para>Pre-built binary RPMs for RedHat Enterprise Linux 5 (RHEL 5) and CentOS 5.x</para>

        <para>These distributions do not come with QT4, and third-party
          binary RPMs of QT v4.3.x and 4.4.x can be difficult to obtain. For these distributions, we
        distribute binary RPMs of Firewall Builder 4.0 statically
        linked with QT 4.4.1. These RPMs are
        posted in the Downloads area of the SourceForge project
        site. These RPMs have the same standard
        names (<filename>libfwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.el5.rpm</filename>
        and <filename>fwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.el5.rpm</filename>), but they
         have no dependency on QT RPMs.</para>

      <para>If a Firewall Builder distribution statically linked with QT crashes on start
        on your CentOS system, check to make sure you have the following font
        packages installed: <filename>bitmap-fonts</filename> or
        <filename>bitstream-vera-fonts</filename>. Either one resolve the issue and allow Firewall Builder work.
        (The <filename>bitstream-vera</filename> fonts are often preferred.) For more information on this issue, refer to bug
        report <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail%26aid=2595205%26group_id=5314%26atid=1070394"><citetitle>#259520
5</citetitle></ulink>
        on SourceForge for more details.</para>

      <para>To install Firewall Builder, navigate to your download directory
      and execute the following command (replacing the filenames with the
      names of the files you actually downloaded):</para>

      <programlisting>rpm -i libfwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.rpm fwbuilder-4.0.0-1.i386.rpm</programlisting>
    </sect1>

