    <sect1 id="iptables_modules">
      <title>iptables modules</title>

      <sect2 id="iptables_install_ipset">
        <title>Installing the iptables ipset Module Using xtables-addons</title>

            <para>
              Instructions for installing the iptables ipset module using xtables-addons. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
              On Ubuntu, the module ipset and corresponding command-line
              tools are packaged in either
              package <emphasis>ipset</emphasis> and
              <emphasis>ipsed-module-source</emphasis> or as part of
              an <emphasis>xtales-addons</emphasis> bundle. The latter
              includes many other useful iptables modules and tools
              besides ipset. You can use just ipset packages if you do
              not need other modules; otherwise, it probably makes
              sense to install xtables-addons. These packages are
              motually exclusive, that is, if you install ipset and
              ipset module packages and then later will try to install
              xtables-addons to get some other module, you are going
              to have to deinstall ipset packages to avoid conflict.
              The instructions below illustrate method
              using <emphasis>xtables-addons</emphasis>.
            </para>

            <para>
              First, you need to obtain the ipset module source.  You can
              do this by running the commands shown
              below.  <emphasis>Note:</emphasis> you will need to be
              root or have sudo access to run these commands.
              Depending on what is already installed on your system
              you might see slightly different command outputs.
            </para>

            <para>
              Two packages xtables-addons that we need to install have
              the following descriptions

              <programlisting>
# aptitude search xtables
p   xtables-addons-common  - Extensions targets and matches for iptables [tools, libs]     
p   xtables-addons-source  - Extensions targets and matches for iptables [modules sources]
              </programlisting>

              We need to install both using the following commands  (as root):

              <programlisting>
# aptitude install xtables-addons-common
# aptitude install xtables-addons-source
              </programlisting>

            </para>

            <para>
              Next, you will need to build the iptables modules
              installed by the package xtables-addons-source from
              source.  We use the convenient module-assistant for
              this.  You will see a window pop-up that displays the
              status of the module being built.

              <programlisting>
# module-assistant build xtables-addons
              </programlisting>

              This command builds binary package with all the modules
              but does not automatically install it. You need to
              install it manually. The command prints module file name
              and path at the end of its run., like this:

              <programlisting>
root@lucid:~# module-assistant build xtables-addons
Extracting the package tarball, /usr/src/xtables-addons.tar.bz2, please wait...
Done with /usr/src/xtables-addons-modules-2.6.32-22-generic-pae_1.21-1+2.6.32-22.36_i386.deb .
              </programlisting>
              
              Package name is "/usr/src/xtables-addons-modules-2.6.32-22-generic-pae_1.21-1+2.6.32-22.36_i386.deb",
              we can install it using dpkg -i command:

              <programlisting>
# dpkg -i \
  /usr/src/xtables-addons-modules-2.6.32-22-generic-pae_1.21-1+2.6.32-22.36_i386.deb
              </programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
              Command line tool ipset was installed previously as part
              of the <emphasis>xtables-addons-common</emphasis> package.
            </para>

            <para>
              Your ipset module installation should now be complete.
              To confirm that the installation was successful try
              running the following commands.

              <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --version
ipset v4.1, protocol version 4.
Kernel module protocol version 4.
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ 
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset -N test iphash
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ 
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --list
[sudo] password for fwbuilder: 
Name: test
Type: iphash
References: 0
Default binding: 
Header: hashsize: 1024 probes: 8 resize: 50
Members:
Bindings:

fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset -X test
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --list
              </programlisting>

              If something did not work right, the command <emphasis>"ipset
              --version"</emphasis> will print an error message. One typical
              problem is when kernel module was not compiled and
              installed or could not be loaded. In this case, this
              command prints something like this:

              <programlisting>
# ipset --version
ipset v4.1, protocol version 4.
FATAL: Could not open '/lib/modules/2.6.32-22-generic-pae/extra/xtables-addons/ipset/ip_set.ko': No such file or directory
ipset v4.1: Couldn't verify kernel module version!
              </programlisting>

            </para>

        </sect2>

      <sect2 id="iptables_install_ipset2">
        <title>Installing the iptables ipset module</title>

        <para>
        On some versions of Ubuntu, including Lucid (and others?), the ipset tools included with xtables-addons does not properly suppo
rt
        the ipset setlist set type which Firewall Builder relies on.  Here are instructions for installing only the iptables ipset modu
le and tools.
        </para>
            
            <para>
            First, you need to get the ipset module source.  You can do this by running the
            commands shown below.  <emphasis>Note:</emphasis> you will need to be root or
            have sudo access to run these commands.  Depending on what is already installed on
            your system you might see slightly different command outputs.
            <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo aptitude install ipset-source

            </programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
            Next, you will need to build the ipset module from source.  We use the convenient module-assistant for this.
            You will see a window pop-up that displays the status of the module being built.
            <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo module-assistant build ipset
Extracting the package tarball, /usr/src/ipset.tar.bz2, please wait...
Done with /usr/src/ipset-modules-2.6.32-21-generic-pae_2.5.0-1+2.6.32-21.32_i386.deb .

            </programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
            Once this is complete you need to install the debian package that was created by module-assistant.
            <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo dpkg -i \
/usr/src/ipset-modules-2.6.32-21-generic-pae_2.5.0-1+2.6.32-21.32_i386.deb

            </programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
            Now you need to install the ipset tools.
            <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo aptitude install ipset

        </programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
        Your ipset module installation should now be complete. To confirm that the installation was successful
        try running the following commands.
        <programlisting>
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --version
ipset v2.5.0 Protocol version 2.
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ 
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset -N test iphash
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ 
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --list
[sudo] password for fwbuilder: 
Name: test
Type: iphash
References: 0
Default binding: 
Header: hashsize: 1024 probes: 8 resize: 50
Members:
Bindings:

fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset -X test
fwbuilder@guardian:~$ sudo ipset --list
        </programlisting>
        </para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>

