    <sect1 id="startup_problems">
      <title>Program Startup Issues</title>

      <sect2 id="cannot-connect-to-x">
        <title>"fwbuilder: cannot connect to X server localhost:0.0"</title>

        <para><emphasis>The Firewall Builder binary does not start. Error "fwbuilder: cannot
        connect to X server localhost:0.0" or similar</emphasis></para>

        <para>The Firewall Builder GUI is an X application, that is, it needs X
        server to display it on the screen. The program determines how to
        connect to the X server using environment variable DISPLAY; you
        probably do not have this environment variable if you get an error
        like that. The simplest way to avoid this problem is to start
        fwbuilder from the shell window in Gnome or KDE environment.</para>

        <para>It may also be that the environment variable DISPLAY is set, but
        the program fwbuilder cannot connect to the X server. In this
        situation you won't be able to run any application using X, check if
        that's the case by trying to start "xclock". This may be happening
        because of many different reasons, such as X server is not running, X
        authentication failure, or DISPLAY variable reassigned its value by
        the shell login script or many others. This problem falls outside the
        scope of this document, please search on the Internet for the answer.
        Here are few URLs to make troubleshooting easier:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>http://www.openssh.org/faq.html</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/XDMCP-HOWTO/ssh.html</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>http://en.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/sect_10_03.html</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="error-loading-shared-lib">
        <title>"fwbuilder: error while
        loading shared libraries: libfwbuilder.so.0: cannot load shared
        object file: no such file or directory."</title>

        <para><emphasis>fwbuilder binary does not start. Error "fwbuilder: error while
        loading shared libraries: libfwbuilder.so.0: cannot load shared
        object file: no such file or directory."</emphasis></para>

        <para>Then the GUI binary (fwbuilder) cannot find API library
        libfwbuilder. If you are using our binary packages, then make sure you
        download and install package called libfwbuilder. If you compiled from
        sources, then perhaps you installed libfwbuilder with default prefix
        /usr/local/, therefore library went to /usr/local/lib. Dynamic linker
        ldd cannot find it there.</para>

        <para>You have the following options:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>create environment variable LD_LIBRARY_PATH with value
              /usr/local/lib and run fwbuilder from this environment.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>add /usr/local/lib to the file /etc/ld.so.conf and run
              ldconfig so it will rescan dynamic libraries and add them to its
              cache.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>recompile libfwbuilder and fwbuilder with prefix /usr/,
              this will install libfwbuilder.so.0 in /usr/lib. ldd will find
              it there without any changes to environment variables or
              /etc/ld.so.conf file. To change prefix you need to run
              autogen.sh with command line parameter "--prefix=/usr". Do this
              both for libfwbuilder and fwbuilder.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="error-loading-shared-lib-2">
        <title>"fwbuilder: error while loading shared libraries: /usr/local/lib/libfwbuilder.so.8: cannot restore segment prot after re
loc: Permission denied"</title>

        <para><emphasis>fwbuilder binary does not start. Error "fwbuilder: error while loading shared libraries: /usr/local/lib/libfwbu
ilder.so.8: cannot restore segment prot after reloc: Permission denied"</emphasis></para>

          <para>The problem is caused by SELinux security settings, to work around it try the following command:</para>

          <para><command>chcon -t texrel_shlib_t /usr/lib/libfwbuilder.so*</command></para>
        </sect2>         
    </sect1>

