<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

  <sect1 id="object-keywords">
    <title>Object Keywords</title>

      <para>
        Keywords can be added to all object types and help you quickly find 
        and organize the objects in your object tree. To set the keywords for 
        an individual object open the object for editing and then click on the 
        Keywords button in the lower right corner of the Editor panel.
      </para>

      <para>
        For an example of how you could use Keywords, let's assume that you have 
        two datacenters, one in New York (NY) and one in London (LON). For objects 
        that represent items in the datacenter you could add a keyword, called 
        "datacenter", to each of the objects. You could also add another keyword, 
        for example "trusted" or "DMZ", to identify the security zone of the object.
      </para>

      <para>
        <xref linkend="ny-datacenter-net-1" /> shows the editor panel for an object 
        called NY Datacenter-Net-1.
      </para>

      <figure id="ny-datacenter-net-1">
          <title>Datacenter Network Object</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/ny_datacenter_net_1_editor.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        Click the Keywords button to set the keywords for the active object. 
        This will bring up the dialog window shown in <xref linkend="keyword-dialog-1"/>.
      </para>
      
      <figure id="keyword-dialog-1">
          <title>Keywords Dialog</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/keywords_dialog_1.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        As you can see no Keywords have been configured yet, so there are 
        no existing keywords that can be assigned to the object. To create 
        a new keyword type the name of the keyword in the text box labeled 
        "New Keyword:".
      </para>
      
      <para>
        In this example we want to add the "datacenter" and "trusted" keywords to 
        the network object. <xref linkend="keyword-dialog-2"/> shows the 
        dialog after the keywords have been entered. Click OK to apply the 
        keywords to the object.
      </para>

      <figure id="keyword-dialog-2">
          <title>Keywords Dialog After Creating Some Keywords</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/keywords_dialog_2.png" />
      </figure>

      <note>
      <para>
        After you apply keywords to an object the keywords will be displayed 
        in the Editor panel next to the Keywords button.
      </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        What if you have a lot of objects that need to have the same keywords 
        applied? To apply a keyword to muliple objects at the same time select 
        the objects in the tree, remember to use the CTRL or Shift keys to 
        select more than one object, right-click on the selected objects and 
        select Keywords, then Add and then select the keyword you want to apply.
        <xref linkend="keywords-multiple-objects-1"/> shows applying the 
        "datacenter" keyword to multiple Network objects.
      </para>

      <figure id="keywords-multiple-objects-1">
          <title>Applying Keywords to Multiple Objects at Once</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/keywords_multiple_objects_1.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        You can also remove keywords from multiple objects by selecting multiple 
        objects, right-clicking and selecting Keywords -> Remove and then selecting 
        the keyword that you want to remove.
      </para>

      <para>
        After you have configured keywords for your objects you can type the 
        keyword into the filter box at the top of the object tree and only the 
        objects that match that keyword, or have an object name that matches 
        the keyword, will be displayed.
      </para>

      <para>
        <xref linkend="filter-datacenter-keyword"/> shows the filtered view after 
        the "datacenter" keyword has been typed into the filter box.
      </para>

      <figure id="filter-datacenter-keyword">
          <title>Filtering Based on Keyword - datacenter</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/filter_datacenter_keyword.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        Another example is shown in <xref linkend="filter-trusted-keyword"/> where 
        all the objects are being filtered for the "trusted" keyword. Only objects 
        that have had the "trusted" keyword applied will be displayed. In this example 
        only one of the two networks at each datacenter is considered trusted.
      </para>

      <figure id="filter-trusted-keyword">
          <title>Filtering Based on Keyword - trusted</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="objects/images/filter_trusted_keyword.png" />
      </figure>

   </sect1>
