    <sect2 id="dnat_to_same_network">
      <title>Destination NAT Onto the Same Network</title>

      <para>This situation is described in iptables HOWTO <ulink
      url="http://www.netfilter.org/documentation/HOWTO//NAT-HOWTO.html">
      http://www.netfilter.org/documentation/HOWTO//NAT-HOWTO.html</ulink></para>

      <para>This problem occurs when machines on an internal LAN try to access a
      server (let's say a web server) that is actually located on the same
      LAN and NAT'ed through the firewall for external access. If internal
      users access it by its external NAT'ed address, then they send their TCP
      packets through the firewall, which translates them and sends them to
      the server on LAN. The server, however, replies back to the clients
      directly because they are on the same network. Since the reply has
      server's real address in the source, clients do not recognize it and
      the connection cannot be established.</para>

      <para>To resolve this problem you need to make NAT rule to replace the source
      address of the packet with the address of firewall's internal interface.
      This should happen in addition to the translation of the destination
      address described in the previous chapters. If the source address of the
      packet that hits the server belongs to the firewall, the server replies
      to it; the firewall then translates again before sending the packet back
      to the client. Client sees the address it expects and the connection gets
      established.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, Firewall Builder supports this kind of a dual-translation NAT rule. Rule #0 in <xref
      linkend="dnat-back-to-same-net" /> does just that: it translates both the 
      source and destination addresses of the packet.</para>

      <para>The firewall's <emphasis>eth0</emphasis> interface is internal and is
      connected to the same subnet the <emphasis>web server</emphasis>
      belongs to. For any packet headed for any address of the firewall, TCP
      port 80, the rule #0 substitutes its source address with the address of
      interface <emphasis>eth0</emphasis> and its destination address with the
      address of the <emphasis>web server</emphasis>. The packet reaches the
      server because its destination address has been changed. This also makes
      the server reply back to the firewall, which in turn provides reverse
      translation before it sends these reply packets back to client
      hosts.</para>

      <figure id="dnat-back-to-same-net">
          <title>DNAT back to the same LAN</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="cookbook/nat_rules/images/dnat-back-to-same-net.png" />
        </figure>

      <para>Rule in <xref linkend="dnat-back-to-same-net" /> replaces source
      address of all packets regardless of their origin. Because of this, the
      web server sees all connections as if they were coming from the firewall
      rather than from the real clients. If having real client addresses in
      the web server log is necessary, the scope of this rule can be narrowed
      by placing object representing internal network in the
      <emphasis>Original Src</emphasis>. Since the source address needs to
      be translated only in the connections coming from the internal net, dual
      translation rule should only be needed for these connections.
      Connections coming from the Internet can be translated as usual.
      Combination of rules that implement this configuration is shown in <xref
      linkend="dnat-back-to-same-net-2" />. Rule #0 does dual translation,
      while rule #1 does a simple destination address translation. Dual
      translation rule must be the first in the pair because if it weren't,
      another one would match connections coming from the internal net and
      translate destination address without changing the source address.</para>

      <figure id="dnat-back-to-same-net-2">
          <title>Using dual translation only for connections coming from
          internal network</title>
              <graphic scale="60" fileref="cookbook/nat_rules/images/dnat-back-to-same-net-2.png" />
        </figure>

      <note>
        <para>Not all firewall platforms provide features Firewall Builder
        needs to implement dual translation rules. Currently dual translation
        rules are supported only with iptables and OpenBSD PF.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

