    <sect1 id="pix_cluster_overview">
      <title>PIX cluster configuration with Firewall Builder</title>

      <para>
        Firewall Builder supports PIX "lan based" failover configuration.
        Unlike in Linux or BSD, where each interface of the firewall runs
        its own instance of failover protocol, PIX runs one instance of
        failover protocol over dedicated interface. PIX can also run state
        synchronization protocol over the same or another dedicated
        interface. These dedicated interfaces should be connected via
        separate switch and do not see regular traffic. Here is how this is
        implemented in Firewall Builder:
      </para>


      <para>
        Like with all other supported firewall platforms, interface
        objects that belong to a cluster object serve to establish
        association between actual interfaces of the member
        firewalls. Cluster interface object should have the same name as
        corresponding member firewall interfaces. It should have
        Failover Group child object which should be configured with
        interfaces of the member firewalls. You can create Failover
        Group object using context menu item "Add Failover Group", the
        menu appears when you right mouse click on the cluster interface
        object. Here is an example of correct interface mapping between
        cluster and member firewalls:

        <figure id="pix_cluster_example1">
          <title>Failover group objects and mapping between
            cluster and member interfaces</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/pix-failover-groups-mapping.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The Failover Group object "cluster1:e0.101:members" is
        configured with interfaces "Ethernet0.101" of both members:

        <figure id="pix_cluster_failover_group_example_1">
          <title>Example of failover group object</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/pix-failover-group-1.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Interface that is configured for the failover on the member
        firewall should be marked as "Dedicated Failover". Use checkbox
        with this name in the interface object dialog to do this.
      </para>

      <para>
        Cluster interface that corresponds to the failover interface
        of the members should be configured with protocol "PIX
        failover protocol". Click on the "Edit protocol parameters"
        button to edit timeout, poll time and the key.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Cluster interfaces that represent regular interfaces of the
        members also must have failover group objects; that is where
        you add interfaces of the member firewalls. There is no need
        to configure protocol in these failover groups because PIX
        does not run it over these interfaces. Regular interfaces
        should not be marked as "Dedicated Failover".
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Cluster object should have State Synchronization group child
        object. Create it using context menu "Add State
        Synchronization Group" item if this object does not
        exist. In this object you need to configure member
        interfaces that should be used for state
        synchronization. You can use separate dedicated interfaces
        or the same interfaces used for failover. If these are
        separate, corresponding interface objects of the member
        firewalls must be marked as "Dedicated Failover".
      </para>

      <para>
        One of the member firewall interfaces used in the State
        Synchronization group must be marked as "master". This is
        where you define which PIX unit is going to be the primary
        and which is going to be the secondary in the HA pair.
      </para>

      <para>
        Here is an example of the state synchronization and failover using
        the same interface Ethernet2:

        <figure id="state_sync_conf_1">
          <title>Example of the state synchronization and failover
            using the same interface Ethernet2</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/pix-statesync-group-mapping.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The State Synchronization Group object "State Sync Group" is
        configured with interfaces "Ethernet2" of both members:

        <figure id="pix_cluster_statesync_group_example_1">
          <title>Example of state synchronization group object</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/pix-statesync-group-1.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>


      <para>
        Dedicated failover interfaces of the member firewalls must
        have IP addresses and these addresses must be different but
        belong to the same subnet.
      </para>

      <para>
        Built-in policy installer treats PIX clusters in a special way:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              For the PIX cluster, built-in installer installs
              generated configuration only on the master PIX unit. It
              determines which one is the master by looking in the
              StateSyncGroup object (state synchronization cluster
              group).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Dialog where user enters authentication credentials and
              other parameters for the installer has a checkbox that
              makes installer initiate copy of the configuration to
              the standby PIX if installation was successful.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </sect1>

