    <sect2 id="blocking-packets">
      <title>Blocking unwanted types of packets</title>

      <para>Fragmented IP packets, although useful in certain situations, are
      often used as a tool to probe and penetrate simple packet filters.
      Particular kinds of fragmented packets, namely those with incorrect
      length specifications, are especially bad because they can cause some
      operating systems to crash (for example Windows NT was known to crash
      before a fix was developed and published by Microsoft). These packets
      therefore are considered potentially harmful and should be blocked on
      the perimeter of your network. Many firewall platforms provide ways to
      deal with such packets.</para>

      <para>In Firewall Builder, we provide a way to set flags or options in
      the IP service object. Two options deal with fragments: one is called
      "all fragments" and another "short fragments". <xref
      linkend="f-policy-2" /> shows how a user-defined object called "fragments" looks
      with both options turned on. Policy compilers recognize this object and
      generate correct code for underlying firewall software platform.</para>

      <figure id="f-policy-2">
        <title>IP Service object which represents fragmented
          packets.</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-2.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>Object "ip_fragments", which is included in the section "Services/IP" of
      the Standard objects tree, is set to block 'short' fragments only.</para>

      <para>Another potentially harmful type of packets is so called
      "Christmas tree" packet. This one is just a TCP packet with impossible
      combination of TCP flags or even all TCP flags turned on at once (for
      example SYN, ACK, FIN, RST, PSH). This combination is never used in real
      communications, so if a packet like that appears at the boundary of your
      network, it should be considered illegal and blocked. Object "tcp-xmas"
      is included in the section "Services/TCP" of the standard objects
      database coming with Firewall Builder.</para>

      <para>Some platforms provide a mechanism to turn on and off stateful
      inspection on individual rules. Turning it off on those rules which do
      not require it may improve performance of the firewall. Obviously we do
      not need stateful inspection while analysing fragmented packets as we do
      not really want any session to be established, so we can safely use this
      option on this rule. One example of firewall platform which supports
      stateful inspection but provides a way to turn it on and off is
      iptables. In Firewall Builder, this can be done in the rule options
      dialog (which is platform-sensitive and shows different options for
      different platforms). <xref linkend="f-policy-3" /> shows rule logging options
      dialog for iptables:</para>

      <figure id="f-policy-3">
        <title>Rule options dialog for iptables firewall</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/iptables-options-logging.png" />
      </figure>
      
      <para>Here is an example of the policy rule which is intended to block
      short fragments and TCP "Christmas scan" packets. The icon in the Options column indicates that logging is turned on.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Rule blocking short fragmented packets and TCP "Christmas scan"
          packets</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-4.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>This rule applies to
      all packets crossing the firewall regardless of their origin. This means
      that it will block such packets originating in your network, too. If by
      some reason you might want to be able to send this kind of packets out,
      then specify your external interface in the <guilabel>Interface</guilabel> column.</para>

    </sect2>

