    <sect2 id="control-access-to-fw">
      <title>Controlling access to the firewall</title>

      <para>
        Suppose we need to permit SSH access to the firewall. In the
        simplest case we just create a rule with firewall object (fw)
        in Destination and a service object SSH in Service. Service
        object SSH can be found in the Standard objects tree, under
        Services/TCP. Here is the rule:
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-14">
        <title>SSH from anywhere</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-14.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        This almost trivial rule compiles into configurations using
        entirely different concepts depending on the chosen target
        firewall platform. Generated iptables rule is rather simple:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# Rule 0 (global)
# 
$IPTABLES -A INPUT -p tcp -m tcp  --dport 22  -m state --state NEW  -j ACCEPT 
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        Generated PF configuration uses tables to list all ip
        addresses that belong to the firewall:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
table &lt;tbl.r0.d&gt; { 192.0.2.1 , 192.168.1.1 } 

# Rule  0 (global)
# 
pass in   quick inet proto tcp  from any  to &lt;tbl.r0.d&gt; port 22 keep state 
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        Iptables has concept of chains that separate different packet
        flow paths inside netfilter engine and packets headed for the
        firewall itself are always processed in the INPUT chain. This
        means generated iptables script could be optimized. If
        comparison is done in the INPUT chain, the script does not
        have to verify destination address to make sure it belongs to
        the firewall since this has already been done by the
        kernel. PF does not have mechanism like this, therefore
        generated PF configuration must compare destination address of
        the packet with all addresses of the firewall. This can be
        done in a more elegant way using PF tables, but still, we make
        the firewall compare destination address of the packet against
        a list of addresses.
      </para>

      <para>
        Ipfw offers a shortcut for this, it is called configuration
        option <emphasis>"me"</emphasis>. Here is how generated ipfw
        script looks like for the same simple rule controlling ssh
        access to the firewall:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# Rule 0 (global)
# 
"$IPFW" add 10 set 1 permit tcp  from any  to me 22 in  setup keep-state  || exit 1
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        <emphasis>"me"</emphasis> here means any address that belongs
        to the firewall.
      </para>

      <para>
        The rule #0 on <xref linkend="policy-14"/> matches
        service <emphasis>ssh</emphasis> which has special meaning in
        case of PIX. There, control to the firewall for protocols such
        as <emphasis>ssh</emphasis> and <emphasis>telnet</emphasis> is
        configured using special configuration commands <emphasis>"ssh"</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>"telnet"</emphasis> instead of generic access
        lists. Here is what we get when we compile exactly the same
        rule for PIX:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
! Rule  0 (global)
! 
ssh    0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 outside
ssh    0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 dmz50
ssh    0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 inside
      </programlisting>


      <para>
        The rule in this example leaves source address "any", which is
        why generated PIX commands match "0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0".  Fwbuilder
        generated "ssh" command for all interfaces of the PIX for the
        same reason.
      </para>

      <para>
        Obviously this rule makes our firewall too open because it
        permits SSH connections to it from any host on the
        Internet. It would be a good idea to restrict it so that it
        permitted connections only from the internal LAN. This is
        easy, we just put object "LAN" in the source of the
        corresponding rule:
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-15">
        <title>SSH from LAN</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-15.png" />
      </figure>


      <para>
        Generated configuration for all supported firewall platforms
        will follow the same pattern but add matching of the source
        address of the packet to make sure it comes from local LAN. In
        case of PIX, there is only one "ssh" command attached to the
        internal interface because the program determined that network
        object used in "Source" of the rule matches only this
        interface of the firewall:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
! Rule  0 (global)
! 
ssh    192.168.1.0 255.255.255.0 inside
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        This is better, but we should be careful not to permit more
        protocols to the firewall than we really intend to. Let's look
        at the simple rule permitting connects from internal LAN to
        the Internet (rule #0 on the screenshot below):
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-16">
        <title>LAN to anywhere</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-16.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        Logic says that destination "any" should match any address,
        including the ones that belong to the firewall itself. In
        Firewall Builder this can actually be changed using a checkbox
        in the <guilabel>Compiler</guilabel> tab of
        the <guilabel>Firewall Settings</guilabel> dialog of the
        firewall object. If the checkbox <guilabel>"Assume firewall is
        part of any"</guilabel> is checked, then the compiler
        generates rules assuming that "any" matches the firewall as
        well. So, if this option is on, then this rule permits any
        connections from internal LAN to the firewall, regardless of
        the protocol! Here is how we can modify the rule permitting
        access to the Internet to exclude firewall from it:
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-17">
        <title>Negating the firewall as a destination from the LAN</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-17.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        We are now using negation in the destination; the meaning of
        this rule is "permit connections on any protocols from
        machines on the network 'LAN' to any host except the
        firewall". We still need a rule described above to permit ssh
        to the firewall, but the rule permitting access from LAN to
        anywhere does not open additional access to the firewall
        anymore. I am going to demonstrate generated iptables and pf
        configurations for rules with negation like this later.
      </para>

      <para>
        But is there any way to make it even more restrictive? Of
        course there is. It is always a good idea to restrict access
        to the firewall to just one machine and use that machine to
        compile the policy and manage the firewall. Let's call this
        machine a management station "fw-mgmt". Here is more
        restrictive combination of rules that permits ssh access to
        the firewall only from <emphasis>fw-mgmt</emphasis>, permits
        access from LAN to anywhere except the firewall on any
        protocol and blocks everything else. This combination of rules
        works the same regardless of the setting of the option "Assume
        firewall is part of any".
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-18">
        <title>Firewall access from only one machine</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-18.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        Three rules shown above are very good at restricting access to
        the firewall from all sources except for the dedicated
        management workstation. The problem with them is that the
        firewall policy is never this simple and short. As you add
        more rules, you can add a rule with a side effect of
        permitting access to the firewall sooner or later. This is one
        of the reason many administrators prefer to keep option
        "Assume firewall is part of any" turned off. In any case, it
        may be a good idea to build rules for the access to the
        firewall explicitly and group them together. It would look
        like something like this:
      </para>

      <figure id="policy-18-a">
        <title>Firewall access from only one machine; all other
        access to the firewall explicitly denied</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-18-a.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        I do not include generated iptables, pf, pix code because it
        should be clear by now how should it look like. It is more
        important that rules in Firewall Builder GUI look exactly the
        same regardless of the chosen target firewall platform.
      </para>

      <para>
        Policy rules demonstrated in these examples are good at
        restricting access to the firewall while making it possible to
        manage it remotely via ssh. The problem with these rules is
        that administrator has to be careful to not break them in any
        way. One would think it should be hard to make an error in a
        policy fragment consisting of two rules, but this
        happens. These two rules are just a small part of a much
        larger rule set and may not be located in a prominent place
        right on top of it. As new rules are added to the policy, at
        some point some rule located above may block access to the
        whole network or range of addresses that accidentally includes
        management address of the firewall. This means even though the
        rules are there, the access to the firewall gets blocked as
        soon as updated policy is uploaded and activated. This is
        really bad news if the firewall machine is located far away in
        a remote office or data center.
      </para>

      <para>
        To help avoid this bad (but all too familiar) situation,
        Firewall Builder offers yet another feature. To access it,
        select firewall object in the tree and open it in the editor,
        then click "Firewall Settings" button. This is described in
        more details in <xref linkend="firewall-object"/>.  In the
        dialog that appears, locate controls shown on
        <xref linkend="ssh-access-from-mgmt"/>
      </para>

      <figure id="ssh-access-from-mgmt">
        <title>Option that enabled automatic rule to permit ssh access from management workstation</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/ssh-access-from-mgmt.png" />
      </figure>


      <para>
        Enter single IP as shown on the screenshot or subnet
        definition in the input field and hit "OK", then recompile the
        policy. Here is what gets added on the top of the generated
        iptables script:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
$IPTABLES -A INPUT   -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
$IPTABLES -A OUTPUT  -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
$IPTABLES -A FORWARD -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT

# backup ssh access
#
$IPTABLES -A INPUT  -p tcp -m tcp  -s 192.168.1.110/255.255.255.255 \
     --dport 22  -m state --state NEW,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
$IPTABLES -A OUTPUT  -p tcp -m tcp  -d 192.168.1.110/255.255.255.255 \
     --sport 22  -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        I included rules matching "ESTABLISHED,RELATED" states in the
        screenshot to demonstrate that automatic rule for ssh access
        is added right after them. In other words, the ssh access rule
        is added at the very beginning of the script before any other
        rule. There are actually two rules, one to permit inbound
        packets in chain INPUT, it matches protocol tcp, destination
        port 22 and states "NEW,ESTABLISHED". The other rule permits
        outbound packets in chain OUTPUT, also protocol tcp, source
        port 22 and states "ESTABLISHED,RELATED". The purpose of this
        complexity is to make sure not only newly established ssh
        sessions are permitted, but also "old" ones, established
        before iptables rules are purged and reinstalled during
        firewall configuration reload. This helps ensure ssh session
        used to activate updated firewall policy does not get blocked
        and stall in the middle of the policy update process.
      </para>

      <para>
        The same option is provided in the "Firewall settings" dialog
        for all supported firewall platforms. Firewall Builder always
        generates command to permit ssh to the firewall and makes it
        the very first in the access control rule set.
      </para>

      <para>
        Now all administrator needs to do is enter ip address of the
        management workstation or address block it belongs to in the
        "Firewall Settings" dialog, then recompile and update
        generated policy on the firewall. There is no need to remember
        to add special rule to permit ssh to the firewall in the
        policy ruleset since this rule is now generated
        automatically. Generated rule is always on top of all other
        rules, so any mistake in the policy rule set will never block
        ssh access to the firewall. This is a good way to reduce the
        risk of locking yourself out of your own firewall. Using this
        feature is highly recommended.
      </para>

    </sect2>

