      <sect2 id="firewall-as-dhcp-dns-server">
	<title>Using firewall as DHCP and DNS server for the local net</title>

	<para>It is often convenient to use a firewall as a DHCP and
	DNS server for the local net, especially in small
	installations like that in a home office. It is not really
	difficult, but building rules properly requires understanding
	of how DHCP and DNS work.</para>

	<para>The following combination of rules permits machines on
	the local net to use the firewall as DHCP server:</para>

        <figure id="policy-10-2">
          <title>Rules with DHCP</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-10-2.png" />
        </figure>

	<para> The first rule permits two types of DHCP requests: the
	initial discovery request that is sent to the broadcast
	address 255.255.255.255 and the renewal request that is sent
	to the firewall's address. The address range object
	"broadcast" can be found in the Standard objects tree, under
	Objects/Address Ranges; this object defines broadcast address
	255.255.255.255. The second rule in the pair permits DHCP
	replies sent by the firewall. The Service object "DHCP" can be
	found in the "Standard" objects tree, under
	Services/Groups.</para>

	<para>We could make these rules more narrow if we used the
	internal interface of the firewall in place of the firewall
	object. Assuming interface eth0 is connected to internal net,
	the rules would look like this:</para>

        <figure id="policy-11">
          <title>Rules with DHCP using Firewall interface</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-11.png" />
        </figure>

	<para>To permit the local network to use the firewall as a DNS
	server, we need to permit DNS queries directed to the
	firewall, DNS replies sent by the firewall, DNS queries sent
	by the firewall to servers on the Internet and replies sent
	back to it. The following pair of rules does just that:</para>

        <figure id="policy-12">
          <title>Rules with DNS</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-12.png" />
        </figure>

	<para>The Service object group object DNS can be found in the
	"Standard" objects tree, under Services/Groups. This group
	consist of both the UDP object domain and TCP object
	domain. Both objects define destination port 53 and ignore
	source port. Since we do not specify the source port, these
	objects match both queries sent by the domain name server
	(source port is 53) and the resolver on the workstations on
	the local net (source port is >1024). We need to use objects
	representing both UDP and TCP protocols because DNS falls back
	to TCP if the answer for the query is too big and won't fit in
	the standard UDP datagram. DNS zone transfers also use TCP
	protocol.</para>
      </sect2>

