    <sect2 id="matching-source-and-service">
      <title> Letting certain protocols through from specific source.</title>

      <para>
        In this example, we look at the rule that is similar to the
        previous one, but also matches source address. This rule
        permits access to the mail server inside from mail relay on
        DMZ and from no other source. Generated rules for iptables and
        pf are very similar, they just add source address
        matching. Generated rules for PIX are different because now
        the program can intelligently pick the right access list and
        avoid generating redundant rules.
      </para>


      <figure>
          <title>Example of a rule permitting only certain protocols
          from limited set of sources to the server.</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-1-2.png" />
        </figure>


      <para>
        Here is the code generated for iptables from this rule:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# Rule 0 (global)
# 
$IPTABLES -A FORWARD -p tcp -m tcp  -s 192.168.2.22   -d 192.168.1.100  \
     --dport 25  -m state --state NEW  -j ACCEPT 
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        Since source rule element was limited to the host on DMZ,
        generated iptables rule is placed only in the FORWARD chain
        and also matches the source using "-s" clause.
      </para>

      <para>
        Lets look at the configuration generated for PIX from the same rule:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
! Rule  0 (global)
! 
access-list dmz50_acl_in  remark 0 (global)
access-list dmz50_acl_in permit tcp host 192.168.2.22 host 192.168.1.100 eq 25 


access-group dmz50_acl_in in interface dmz50
access-group inside_acl_in in interface inside
access-group outside_acl_in in interface outside
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        the rule was placed only in the access list attached to the
        DMZ interface because packets with source address of the host
        on DMZ can only cross this interface of the firewall, assuming
        spoofed packets are blocked by special rule, which will
        discuss below.
      </para>


    </sect2>

