      <sect2 id="outging-connections">
	<title>Controlling outgoing connections from the firewall</title>

	  <para>This example shows the rule that permits only certain
	  types of outgoing connections. To permit outgoing web access
	  but nothing else, we put the firewall object in Source and
	  corresponding service object in Service:</para>

        <figure id="policy-19">
          <title>HTTP only</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-19.png" />
        </figure>

	  <para>Rule #1 blocking packets going from any source to any
	  destination also blocks packet originating on the firewall
	  (provided option "Assume firewall is part of any" is
	  on). The combination of these two rules permits only
	  outgoing HTTP connections from the firewall and nothing
	  else.</para>

	  <para>Although we permit outgoing HTTP connections here, we
	  should probably permit outgoing DNS queries as well. The
	  browser running on this machine would not be able to connect
	  to a web site if it cannot resolve the name via DNS. Here is
	  the corrected policy:</para>

        <figure id="policy-20">
          <title>HTTP and DNS</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-20.png" />
        </figure>

	  <para> Service object DNS, which includes both the UDP and
	  TCP versions, can be found in
	  the <guilabel>"Standard"</guilabel> tree
	  under <guimenuitem>Services/Groups</guimenuitem>.</para>

	  <para>We may also want to permit protocols used for
	  troubleshooting, such as ping. In order to permit it, we
	  just add ICMP Service object "ping request" to the list of
	  services permitted by rule #0:</para>

        <figure id="policy-21">
          <title>HTTP,DNS and ping</title>
              <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/policy-21.png" />
        </figure>

	<note>
          <para>
            In Firewall Builder, a firewall object
	    represents any machine that runs firewall software. This is
	    not necessarily a dedicated firewall protecting a local
	    network, but may actually be a server or a laptop. For
	    example, rules permitting HTTP to the dedicated firewall
	    machine may not be very practical because running the web
	    server on it would be risky, but if the firewall object
	    represents a web server with iptables or ipfilter running on
	    it, such rules make perfect sense. The rule permitting
	    outbound HTTP access from the firewall machine explained in
	    this example can be used as a part of the policy protecting
	    a laptop or a workstation.
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect2>

