    <sect2 id="tag-rules">
      <title>Tagging packets</title>

      <para>
        Tagging packets can be a very useful strategy that allows you to
        match a packet at one point in the rule set but act on it
        later on. This can be combined with rule-branching for even
        more flexibility. Packet tagging is only supported in Firewall
        Builder for the firewall platforms that can do it; these are
        iptables and pf. Tagging sometimes can also be used to
        interact with packet processing not intended to enforce
        security policy, such as traffic shaping or QoS. Packet tags
        assigned by iptables can later be used for traffic shaping
        with the Linux utility "tc".
      </para> 

      <para>
        In Firewall Builder, tagging of packets is done using a special
        service object type. First, you create an object of this type
        and configure a tag number or a string. Once this is done, you
        can use this object to match tagged packets by just dropping
        the object to the "Service" column of a policy rule. To assign
        tag to a packet you choose action "Mark" (iptables) or "Tag"
        (PF) and drop the same tag service object to a well in the
        action options dialog. Let's use an example given in the "A
        Practical Guide to Linux Traffic Control"
        (http://blog.edseek.com/~jasonb/articles/traffic_shaping/index.html)
        to illustrate this. They show how packets can be tagged using
        iptables target "MARK" so that they can be placed in the right
        queue for traffic shaping later on. The iptables rule we will
        create looks like this:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
iptables -t mangle -A POSTROUTING -o eth2 -p tcp --sport 80 -j MARK --set-mark 1
      </programlisting>


      <para>
        Note how the rule should be placed in the table "mangle",
        chain "POSTROUTING". This is how the target MARK works;
        the administrator is expected to know this if they write iptables
        rules by hand.
      </para>

      <para>
        We start with a tag service object configured with tag "1":
      </para>

      <figure id="tag-service-1">
        <title>Simple Tag Service</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/tag-service-1.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        We also need a TCP service object to match source port 80:
      </para>

      <figure id="tcp-sport-80">
        <title>TCP Service to Match Source Port 80</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/tcp-service-sport-80.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        And now the rule:
      </para>

      <figure id="iptables-tag-rule-1">
        <title>Rule Matching the Tag Service</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/iptables-tag-rule-1.png" />
      </figure>

      <para>
        In order to replicate the rule from the Guide, I leave Source
        and Destination "any", put outside interface of the firewall
        in "Interface" column, set direction to "Outbound", set action
        to "Tag" and make it stateless. The following screenshots
        demonstrate how this is done:
      </para>

      <figure id="iptables-tag-rule-1-a">
        <title>Configuring the Tag Action</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/iptables-tag-rule-1-a.png" />
      </figure>

      <figure id="iptables-tag-rule-1-b">
        <title>Configuring Rule Options to Make the Rule Stateless</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cookbook/policy_rules/images/iptables-tag-rule-1-b.png" />
      </figure>


      <para>
        This configuration makes Firewall Builder generate an iptables command
        that is exactly the same as the one given in "A Practical
        Guide to Linux Traffic Control."
      </para>

      <para>
        The rule, reproduced from the Guide, is stateless and matches
        and tags every reply HTTP packet crossing the firewall. This
        is not very efficient in case the firewall has to forward
        heavy HTTP traffic because it has to work on every single
        packet. To make things more efficient, iptables can mark whole
        sessions which means individual packets can be marked
        automatically as long as they belong to the session that was
        marked once. To use this feature with Firewall Builder, turn
        on the checkbox "Mark connections created by packets that match
        this rule" in the dialog
        <xref linkend="iptables-tag-rule-1-a"/>, where you configure
        options for the rule action and where the well into which you
        had to drop the tag service object is located. This checkbox
        modifies generated iptables script by adding a call to
        CONNMARK iptables target that marks whole connection and also
        by adding the following rule on top of the script:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# ================ Table 'mangle', automatic rules
$IPTABLES -t mangle -A PREROUTING -j CONNMARK --restore-mark
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        This rule automatically restores mark on the packets that
        belong to the marked session.
      </para>

    </sect2>

