    <sect1 id="main_window">
      <title>The Main Window</title>

      <para>This image shows the Firewall Builder GUI with a single object file open. The panels in the GUI have been shrunk down to ma
ke the image fit on the page. On a computer screen, you'd be able to see much more.</para>

      <para>
      <figure id="main-win1">
        <title>The main window</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbMainWindow-wUndo.png" />

      </figure>
      </para>

      <para>The sections of the main window are as follows:</para>

      <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
        <title>Main Window</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left' rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Window area</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Menus and tool bar</entry>
                <entry>Firewall Builder comes
                with menus and a tool bar at the top of the
                window. 
      <para>
        <figure id="main-win-menus">
          <title>Menu and Tool Bars</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbMainWindow-3.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Object Tree</entry>
                <entry><para>Displayed on the
                left side of the window, holds firewall, host,
                interface, service, and other "objects" that you will
                use when creating your firewall. You can close the tree if you want more room for your policy by clicking the X button 
(re-open it using the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, or you can make it "float" as 
                its own window by clicking the float button next to the close button.</para>
                <para><xref linkend="object_tree" /> describes the objects in the tree, shows a picture of the object tree "floating", 
and shows how to filter the object tree.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="object-tree-small">
          <title>Object Tree</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/object-tree-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Policy Ruleset Workspace</entry>
                <entry>Displayed to the right of the object tree, this area holds the ruleset you're currently working on. This space i
s blank when you first load an object file. It only appears when you double-click a policy, NAT, or routing ruleset link in a firewall 
object. (So, you have to create a firewall object before you can work on a policy.)
      <para>See <xref linkend="firewall-object" /> for instructions on creating a firewall object. See <xref linkend="firewall-policies"
 /> for instructions on working with policies.</para>
        <para>The two buttons on the top of the ruleset let you compile (the hammer) or compile-and-install (arrow and wall) the curren
t firewall policy. <xref linkend="compile-install-detail" /> describes both compiling and compiling-and-installing a firewall policy.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="policy-small">
          <title>Policy Area</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/policy-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Object Editor Dialog</entry>
                <entry><para>The dialog area, across the bottom of the main window, 
                is where you make changes to object
                parameters, do finds-and-replaces, and see the output from single-rule compiles. 
                The dialog area, which is not visible at
                first, appears when you double-click an object.</para>
                <para>The dialog, which you can close by clicking the X, has three tabs and three uses: editing an object's parameters,
 doing a find or find-and-replace on an object, and displaying the output of a single-rule compile run.</para>
                <para>In the object editor dialog, you can make changes to an object's parameters. Changes made in to a field in the di
alog are saved whenever you click out of the field, or press the Tab or Enter key. (This does not change the data in the .fwb file unti
l you save the file itself.) If you wish to cancel a change, select Edit > Undo.See <xref linkend="working-with-objects" />for informat
ion on objects and their parameters.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="object-editor-small">
          <title>Object Editor, partial view</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/object-editor-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
        <para> You can search for objects and rulesets across your object files, plus do replacements of objects. See 
        <xref linkend="find-replace" /> for an explanation of the 
                find-and-replace tab.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="find-small">
          <title>Find-and-Replace Object dialog, partial view</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/find-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
        <para>You can compile individual rules and see how the rule gets converted into firewall instructions. See 
        <xref linkend="policy-and-nat-rules-for-the-cluster" /> for 
                details on compiling a single rule and viewing the results in the Output tab.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="output-small">
          <title>Output view, partial view</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/output-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Undo Stack</entry>
                <entry><para>Displayed on the
                right side of the window, the Undo Stack is not displayed by default. To activate it, select <guimenuitem>View > Undo S
tack</guimenuitem>.</para>
                <para>As you make changes to your object file, those changes show up in the <guilabel>Undo Stack</guilabel> window. You
 can "undo" an action by clicking the action above it (in other words, prior to it) in the window. Clicking any action in the window ro
lls back all changes after that action. However, the "future" changes stay in the Undo Stack until you make another edit. At that point
, all changes after the current point in the stack are removed.</para>
                <para>Like the object tree, the Undo Stack can "float" as its own window.</para>
      <para>See <xref linkend="using-undo" /> for a more detailed explanation of the Undo Stack window.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="undo-stack">
          <title>Undo Stack</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/undo-stack.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>You can open more than one object file window at a
      time, and you can copy objects between them. See <xref linkend="multiple-data-files" /> for an
      example of working with multiple data files.</para>
      </sect1>

