    <sect1 id="main_window">
      <title>The Main Window</title>

      <para>This figure shows the Firewall Builder GUI with a single object file open. (The panels in the GUI have been minimized
        so that the image fits on the page. On a computer screen, you'd be able to see much more.)</para>

      <para>
      <figure id="main-win1">
        <title>The Main Window</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbMainWindow-wUndo.png" />

      </figure>
      </para>

      <para>The sections of the main window are as follows:</para>

      <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
        <title>Main window</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left' rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Window area</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Menus and tool bar</entry>
                <entry>Firewall Builder comes
                with menus and a tool bar at the top of the
                window. 
      <para>
        <figure id="main-win-menus">
          <title>Menu and Tool Bars</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbMainWindow-3.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>The Object Tree</entry>
                <entry><para>Displayed on the
                left side of the window, the object tree displays firewalls, hosts,
                interfaces, services, and other "objects" that you will
                use when creating your firewall. You can close the tree if you want more room for your policy, by clicking the X button. 
(Re-open it using the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu; alternatively,  you can make it "float" as 
                its own window by clicking the <guimenu>Float</guimenu> button next to the <guimenu>Close</guimenu> button.</para>
                <para><xref linkend="object_tree" /> describes the objects in the tree, shows a picture of the object tree "floating", 
and shows how to filter the object tree.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="object-tree-small">
          <title>The Object Tree</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/object-tree-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>The Policy Rule Set Workspace</entry>
                <entry>Displayed to the right of the object tree, this area holds the rule set you are currently working on. This space i
s blank when you first load an object file. It only appears when you double-click a policy, NAT, or routing rule set link in a firewall 
object. (This means that you have to create a firewall object before you can work on a policy.)
      <para>See <xref linkend="firewall-object" /> for instructions on creating a firewall object. See <xref linkend="firewall-policies"
 /> for instructions on working with policies.</para>
        <para>The two buttons on the top of the rule set let you compile (the hammer) or compile-and-install (arrow and wall) the curren
t firewall policy. <xref linkend="compile-install-detail" /> describes how to compile a firewall policy as well
          as how to compile and install one.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="policy-small">
          <title>The Policy Area</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/policy-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>The Object Editor Dialog</entry>
                <entry><para>The dialog area, across the bottom of the main window, 
                is where you make changes to object
                parameters, perform find and replace operations, and view the output from single-rule compiles. 
                The dialog area is not visible until you 
                double-click an object.</para>
                <para>The dialog has three tabs and three uses: editing an object's parameters,
 doing a find or find-and-replace on an object, and displaying the output of a single-rule compile run. Close the dialog by clicking the X.</para>
                <para>In the object editor dialog, you can make changes to an object's parameters. Changes made 
                  to a field in the dialog are saved whenever you click out of the field, or when you press the Tab or Enter key. 
                  (Note that this does not change the data in the .fwb file 
                  until you save the file itself.) If you wish to cancel a change, select <guimenuitem>Edit > Undo</guimenuitem>. 
                  For more information on objects and their parameters, see <xref linkend="working-with-objects" />.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="object-editor-small">
          <title>Object Editor, Partial View</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/object-editor-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
        <para> You can search for objects and rule sets across your object files, plus do replacements of objects. See 
        <xref linkend="find-replace" /> for an explanation of the 
                Find-and-Replace tab.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="find-small">
          <title>Find-and-Replace Object dialog, Partial View</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/find-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
        <para>You can compile individual rules and see how the rule gets converted into firewall instructions. See 
        <xref linkend="policy-and-nat-rules-for-the-cluster" /> for 
                details on compiling a single rule and viewing the results in the Output tab.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="output-small">
          <title>Output View, Partial View</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/output-small.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Undo Stack</entry>
                <entry><para>Displayed on the
                right side of the window, the Undo Stack is not displayed by default. To activate it, select <guimenuitem>View > Undo S
tack</guimenuitem>.</para>
                <para>As you make changes to your object file, those changes show up in the <guilabel>Undo Stack</guilabel> window. You
 can "undo" an action by clicking the action above it (in other words, prior to it) in the window. Clicking any action in the window ro
lls back all changes after that action. However, the "future" changes stay in the Undo Stack until you make another edit. At that point
, all changes after the current point in the stack are removed.</para>
                <para>Like the object tree, the Undo Stack can "float" as its own window.</para>
      <para>See <xref linkend="using-undo" /> for a more detailed explanation of the Undo Stack window.</para>
      <para>
        <figure id="undo-stack">
          <title>Undo Stack</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/undo-stack.png" />
        </figure>
      </para>
                </entry>
              </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>You can open more than one object file window at a
      time, and you can copy objects between them. See <xref linkend="multiple-data-files" /> for an
      example of working with multiple data files.</para>
      </sect1>

