      <sect1 id="preferences">
        <title>Preferences Dialog</title>
<para>To open the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog,
      select <guimenuitem>Edit/Preferences...</guimenuitem>. The
      dialog has several tabs, described here.</para>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog">
        <title>The GUI Preferences Dialog</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefGeneral.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

      <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
        <title>Preferences>General Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>General Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Working Directory</entry>
                <entry>This option tells the program where it should store the
                data file. Policy compilers also store firewall configuration
                files and scripts they produce in this directory. If this
                parameter is left blank,  the policy compiler stores
                the firewall configurations it generates in the same directory
                as the original data file.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Do not show tips on startup</entry>
                <entry>If checked, the program does not show tips on start up.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Check for updates automatically</entry>
                <entry>If checked, the program checks for program updates every time it starts. If unchecked, the program will not chec
k for updates unless  specifically enabled by clicking the <guibutton>Check Now</guibutton> button.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Check Now</entry>
                <entry>Click if you want the program to check for updates at that moment.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Use http proxy while checking for updates (host:port)</entry>
                <entry>Whether you use the automatic or manual method
                to check for updates, if you are behind a proxy, enter
                the host IP and port of the proxy in this
                field. Separate the host IP and port number with a
                colon (:).</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog-objects">
        <title>GUI Preferences Objects Tab</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefObjects1.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Objects Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Objects Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Enable object tooltips</entry>
                <entry>Firewall Builder can show a summary of an
                object's properties in a quick pop-up window (a
                "tooltip") when you hover the mouse cursor over an
                object icon. If this feature is not enabled, then you must
                click on an object to get the same information. The
                <guilabel>Tooltip delay</guilabel> control sets the
                delay, in seconds, between the time you hover the
                cursor and the time the tooltip appears.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Show deleted objects</entry>
                <entry>Selecting this checkbox turns on a third object tree:
                Deleted Objects. Once enabled, the Deleted Objects tree acts
                like trash can (or recycle bin) for deleted objects. If you
                delete something by mistake, you can retrieve it.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Show object attributes in the tree</entry>
                <entry>Creates a second column in the object tree. The second column
                contains information about the object, such as how many objects a folder contains, whether a rule set is the top rule set
, IP addresses, and so on. See <xref linkend="object-attributes" /> for a description.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Clip comments in rules</entry>
                <entry>Comments in a rule can sometimes make the rule
                line taller, reducing the number of rules visible on a
                screen.  Select this if you want comments to be
                truncated in the view if they take up more than one
                line.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>DNS Name - Create new objects in "Compile Time" or "Run Time" mode by default</entry>
                <entry>These radio buttons set the default behavior for reading DNS Name object addresses from a file: 
                  when the firewall script is generated by Firewall Builder or when the firewall runs the script. Note that the default
                  value set here can be overridden for individual objects. <xref linkend="dns-name-object" /> has more information on DNS Name object creation.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>DNS Name - Use object name for the DNS record in all objects of this type</entry>
                <entry>If checked, Firewall Builder uses the DNS Name object's name for DNS lookups. If not checked,  
                  Firewall Builder uses the <guilabel>DNS Record</guilabel> field in the object for lookups. (If this checkbox is checked, the <guilabel>
DNS Record</guilabel> field will be grayed out in all DNS Name objects.)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Address Table - Create new objects in "Compile Time" mode or "Run Time" mode by default radio buttons</entry>
                <entry>These radio buttons set the default behavior for reading Address Table object addresses are read from a file: 
                  when the firewall script is generated by Firewall Builder or when the firewall runs the script. Note that the default
                  value set here can be overridden for individual objects. <xref linkend="address-table-object" /> has more information on Address Table object creation.</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog-datafile">
        <title>GUI Preferences Data File tab</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefDataFile1.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Data File tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Data File Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Periodically save data to file every ... minute</entry>
                <entry>If checked, data is automatically saved at the specified interval.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Do not ask for the log record when checking in the new
                file version</entry>
                <entry>Affects only RCS. If selected, the system does
                not prompt you for a "comment" when you check your
                file back into RCS.  See <xref linkend="rcs" /> for a
                detailed explanation on using revision control with
                Firewall Builder.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Enable compression of the data file</entry>
                <entry>If selected, the data file is compressed to save
                disk space.</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog-installer">
        <title>GUI Preferences Installer Tab</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefInstaller1.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Installer Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Installer Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>SSH and SCP paths</entry>
                <entry>These fields specify the paths to your
                  SSH and SCP programs, or their equivalents. If
                  these paths are already recorded in your PATH system variable, you need not
                  specify paths here. On Windows,
                  however, you must install putty. See
                  <xref linkend="install-windows"/> for
                  instructions.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Enable password caching</entry>
                <entry>If checked, the program can remember firewall
                passwords for the duration of the Firewall Builder GUI
                session. Passwords are never stored permanently in any
                form; they are only kept in memory for the working
                Firewall Builder GUI instance. You need to enter each
                password once when you activate a generated policy. If
                you keep the program open and need to modify and
                activate policy again, the password fields in the
                installer dialog can be filled automatically. Cached
                passwords are associated with the firewall object and
                account name used to activate the policy. To use this
                feature, you must also configure a user name in
                the <guilabel>Installer</guilabel> tab in
                the <guilabel>Firewall Settings</guilabel> dialog of
                the firewall object. Caution: using this feature
                creates a risk if a working Firewall Builder GUI is
                left unattended on an unlocked workstation.</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

     <para>
       <figure id="preferences-dialog-labels">
         <title>GUI Preferences Labels Tab</title>
         <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefLabels1.png" />
       </figure>
     </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Labels Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Labels Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Labels</entry>
                <entry>You can assign colors to particular rows in
                  your policies to make them stand out visually. You
                  can also change the text label associated with each color
                  using this tab. While the color shows up in the
                  rule set, the text label only appears in the label
                  list.
                </entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog-appearance">
        <title>GUI Preferences Appearance Tab</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefAppearance1.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Appearance Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Appearance Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Rules, Tree, and Compiler Output Panel Fonts</entry>
                <entry>Use these controls to set the font used for
                rules, the object tree, and the compiler output panel.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Show icons in rules</entry>
                <entry>If deselected, suppresses icon display for an object, showing only text. By default, objects 
                  such as interfaces, hosts, and networks are displayed as both an icon and text. </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Show text descriptions in columns
                "Direction","Action"</entry>
                <entry>If selected, displays text descriptions in addition to icons in the Direction and Action columns. By default, only
                icons are shown. </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Icon size</entry>
                <entry>By default, icons are 25x25
                pixels. Select <guilabel>16x16</guilabel> to make them
                somewhat smaller. (The larger icons are easier to see, but
                the smaller ones are useful for smaller displays,
                such as laptop screens.)</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
      <figure id="preferences-dialog-platformsandos">
        <title>GUI Preferences Platforms and OS Tab</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="fwbuilder_gui/images/fwbPrefPlatformsandOS1.png" />
      </figure>
      </para>

     <table frame='none' tabstyle='reg_table'>
       <title>Preferences>Platforms and OS Tab</title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colname='c1'  colwidth="120pt"/>
          <colspec colname='c2'/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Platforms and OS Preferences</entry>
                <entry>Explanation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Lists of Platforms and OSs</entry>
                <entry>Checked platforms and OSs appear in drop-down
                menus of platforms and OSs in the program. You can
                uncheck unneeded platforms and OSs to reduce clutter
                in GUI menus. Remember to recheck entries when you
                want them to reappear in the GUI, such as when you
                acquire a new type of firewall. Also, not all platforms
                and OSs supported by Firewall Builder are checked by
                default. If the firewall you have doesn't appear in
                your drop-down menus, make sure it is checked in this
                tab.</entry>
              </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      </sect1>

