  <sect1 id="compiling_cluster">
    <title>Compiling cluster configuration with Firewall Builder</title>

    <para>Cluster compilation works very much like it does for individual firewalls. However, there are a few things to keep in mind.</para>

    <para>
      Clusters are represented
      by objects of type "Cluster" located in the object group
      "Clusters". To a generate configuration for all cluster member
      firewalls and install it on each, you need to compile it just
      like you would compile a regular standalone firewall
      object.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Compile a Cluster, Install a Firewall</title>

      <para>
        In the compile dialog list there are two columns of
        checkboxes: "Compile" and "Install". When you compile a
        cluster, the "Compile" checkboxes appear next to
        the cluster objects only while "Install" checkboxes appear
        next to the member firewall objects only. This is
        because to compile, the policy compiler needs to read the
        cluster object to get all the information about the cluster
        configuration, including the list of member firewalls.
        However, when generated configuration is ready and needs
        to be installed on member firewalls, the program needs
        to communicate with each member firewall separately. So
        the "Install" checkboxes are next to the member
        firewalls in the list, letting you turn installation on
        and off on each member separately.
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="compile-cluster-2">
          <title>Compiling cluster object with two members</title>
          <graphic scale="70" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-cluster-2.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <tip>
        <para>
          A PIX cluster is an exception to this rule. In a PIX
          cluster, you only need to update configuration of the
          active unit in the failover pair. The active unit then
          pushes configuration to the second unit in the pair
          automatically. Firewall Builder is aware of this and the
          "Install" checkbox is only enabled next to the member
          firewall marked as "master" in the cluster configuration.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Mixed Object Files</title>

      <para>
        The data file used for this example has a mix of
        cluster objects with corresponding member firewalls and
        standalone firewall objects that do not belong to any
        cluster. The latter get both "Compile" and "Install"
        checkboxes as visible in <xref linkend="compile-cluster-6"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure id="compile-cluster-6">
          <title>Compiling all cluster and firewall objects</title>
          <graphic scale="70" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-cluster-6.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Compile a single firewall within a cluster</title>
      <para>
        You can try to compile a firewall object that is a member of
        a cluster by selecting it in the tree and using the context
        menu. When you do this, the program treats the object as
        standalone firewall rather than a cluster member and does not
        generate any cluster-related part of the configuration, such
        as policy rules for the failover protocols, the configuration
        script for failover interfaces, and so on. This is because a
        firewall object can actually be a member of several clusters,
        which is useful to test different cluster configurations or
        for transitions. In some cases a firewall object by itself may
        be so generic that it can describe member firewalls in
        different locations (if potential address collisions are not
        an issue or all addresses are dynamic). For these reasons, the
        program does not try to guess whether given a firewall object
        might be a cluster member and which cluster it is a member of
        and falls back to treating it as a simple standalone firewall
        object. However, the program shows a warning to indicate this as shown
        in <xref linkend="compile-cluster-7"/>. Here we selected
        firewall object "linux-test-1" in the tree and then used
        context menu to initiate compilation, forgetting that it is a
        member of two different cluster configurations:
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="compile-cluster-7">
          <title>Compiling a member firewall as standalone firewall objects</title>
          <graphic scale="70" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-cluster-7.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

