  <sect1 id="installer_on_pix">
    <title>Installing generated configuration onto Cisco ASA (PIX) firewalls</title>

    <para>
      Built-in installer can use command <command>scp</command> to
      copy generated configuration to the firewall and then
      command <command>"copy file running-config"</command> to
      activate it.  This method is much faster than running
      configuration line by line.  The firewall should be configured
      with ssh v2 and scp server. This method can be combined with
      rollback. To use this method, turn on checkbox in the
      tab <emphasis>"Installer"</emphasis> of
      the <emphasis>"advanced settings"</emphasis> dialog of the PIX
      firewall.  Since this option is configured separately for each
      firewall object, you can have a mix of installation methods if
      some firewalls do not support <command>scp</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To configure <command>scp</command> on the PIX firewall you
      need to do the following:

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Create RSA keys
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            enable ssh v2 using command <command>"ssh version
              2"</command> in configuration mode
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            enable scp using command <command>"ssh scopy enable"</command> in configuration
            mode
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            make sure user account used to copy configuration has
            "privilege 15": <command>"username fwadmin password XXXXXXX privilege
              15"</command>
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      To troubleshoot when scp is not working:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Test using command line scp tool rather than fwbuilder
            installer. Use
            <command>"scp"</command> on Linux and Mac OS X
            and <command>"pscp.exe"</command> on Windows like
            this: <command>"scp file.fw
              firewall:flash:file.fw"</command>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            check that ssh and scopy are enabled on the firewall
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            check that user account has privilege 15
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use command <command>"debug ssh 10"</command> on PIX to
            turn debugging on. Diagnostic messages that it prints to
            the console and to log may help you identify the problem
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Note that when fwbuilder uses command <command>"copy file.fw
        running-config"</command> to activate uploaded policy, the
      firewall does not print it. If there are errors, they are
      printed but the lines they refer to are not printed. Some
      configuration lines trigger lines because they try to
      configure things that are already configured, such as some
      parameters of interfaces, global pools etc.
    </para>

    <para>
      Generated PIX configuration will include commands that enable ssh v2
      and enable scopy if this option is turned on to make sure they stay
      enabled after configuration is reloaded from the file.
    </para>

  </sect1>

