    <sect1 id="cluster_rule_set_override">
      <title>Handling of the cluster rule set and member firewalls rule sets</title>

      <para>
        Normally, only the cluster object should have non-empty
        policy, NAT and routing rule sets, while member firewall
        objects should have empty rule sets. In this case, Firewall
        Builder policy compilers will use rules they find in the
        cluster. However, if a member firewall has rule set object
        of any type (Policy, NAT, Routing) with the name the same as
        the name of the cluster object and the same type, then
        compilers will use rules from the member firewall and ignore
        those found in the cluster. They also issue a warning that
        looks like shown in
        <xref linkend="cluster_rule_set_override_warning"/>:
      </para>

      <figure id="cluster_rule_set_override_warning">
        <title>A warning shown when a rule set that belongs to the member firewall overrides rule set that belongs to the cluster</title>
        <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/cluster-rule-set-override-warning.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>
        Suggested use case for this feature is to create a small
        non-top rule set in the cluster which can be used as a
        branch using a rule with action "Branch" to pass control to
        it. The cluster can define some rules in this rule set,
        these rules are going to be common for all member
        firewalls. However if for some reason you want to implement
        these rules differently for one member, you just create rule
        set with the same name in it and add some different rules
        there. Of course two members can have the rule set with this
        name and both will override the one that belongs to the
        cluster. The warning is only given if member firewall rule
        set is not empty. If it exists and has the same name as the
        one that belongs to the cluster, but has no rules, then the
        warning does not appear.
      </para>

    </sect1>

