    <sect1 id="linux_cluster_overview">

      <title>Linux cluster configuration with Firewall Builder</title>

      <para>
        Detailed walk-through examples for different Linux, BSD and
        PIX cluster configurations can be found in Firewall Builder
        Cookbook chapter <xref linkend="cluster-cookbook"/>
      </para>

      <para>
        High Availability (HA) configurations on Linux can be built
        using different software packages, such as vrrpd
        (<ulink url="http://off.net/~jme/vrrpd/"><citetitle>VRRPD home
        page</citetitle></ulink>) or heartbeat
        (<ulink url="http://www.linux-ha.org/"><citetitle>Linux-HA
        home page</citetitle></ulink>). Firewall Builder focuses on
        the firewall configuration and provides independent way of
        configuring iptables rules for Linux HA clusters and can be
        used with any HA software package, including home-grown
        scripts and packages that will appear in the future. At this
        time Firewall Builder does not generate configuration or
        command line for the HA software.
      </para>

      <para>
        Like with all other supported firewall platforms, interface
        objects that belong to a cluster object serve to establish
        association between actual interfaces of the member
        firewalls. Cluster interface object should have the same
        name as corresponding member firewall interfaces. It should
        have Failover Group child object configured with interfaces
        of the member firewalls. You can create Failover Group
        object using context menu item "Add Failover Group", the
        menu appears when you right mouse click on the cluster
        interface object. If you create new cluster using "New
        object" menu or toolbar button, the wizard that creates new
        cluster object will create Failober Group objects
        automatically. Here is how it should look like:
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="linux_cluster_interface_mappings">
          <title>Failover group objects and mapping between
            cluster and member interfaces</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/linux-cluster-interface-mappings.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Note that the name of the cluster interface should match
        the name of the member interfaces exactly, even if it may
        appear that HA software running on the firewall creates
        new interface such as eth0:0. Heartbeat daemon creates
        what looks like interface "eth0:0" when it becomes active
        and assumes virtual ip address. The "eth0:0" is in fact a
        label on the secondary ip address on the interface "eth0"
        which you can see if you use command "ip addr show dev
        eth0". Here is an example of the output of this command
        taken on the firewall running heartbeat that was active at
        the moment:
      </para>

      <para>
        <programlisting>
# ip addr show dev eth0
2: eth0: &lt;BROADCAST,MULTICAST,UP,LOWER_UP&gt; mtu 1500 qdisc pfifo_fast state UNKNOWN qlen 1000
    link/ether 00:0c:29:1e:dc:aa brd ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff
    inet 10.3.14.108/24 brd 10.3.14.255 scope global eth0
    <emphasis role="redtext">inet 10.3.14.150/24 brd 10.3.14.255 scope global secondary eth0:0</emphasis>
    inet6 fe80::20c:29ff:fe1e:dcaa/64 scope link 
       valid_lft forever preferred_lft forever
        </programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
        Secondary IP address 10.3.14.150 that was added by
        heartbeat is highlighted in red. The "eth0:0" at the very
        end of the output is the label assigned to this address,
        this label makes it appear as another inetrface in the
        output of ifconfig, however it is not real inetrface. Here
        is the output of ifconfig on the same machine at the same
        time when it was active in the HA pair:
      </para>

      <para>
        <programlisting>
# ifconfig 
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:0c:29:1e:dc:aa  
          inet addr:10.3.14.108  Bcast:10.3.14.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::20c:29ff:fe1e:dcaa/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:242381 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:41664 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000 
          RX bytes:40022382 (40.0 MB)  TX bytes:5926417 (5.9 MB)
          Interrupt:18 Base address:0x2000 
<emphasis role="redtext">
eth0:0    Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:0c:29:1e:dc:aa  
          inet addr:10.3.14.150  Bcast:10.3.14.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          UP BROADCAST RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          Interrupt:18 Base address:0x2000 </emphasis>
        </programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
        It is important to understand the distinction because
        iptables does not recognize eth0:0 as an interface and does
        not allow it in "-i" or "-o" clause. Firewall Builder
        follows the same rules as the target firewall platform it
        prepares configuration for. This means you should build
        configuration in fwbuilder using interface "eth0" and not
        "eth0:0".
      </para>

      <para>
        Each cluster interface should have a Failover Group child
        object configured with corresponding interfaces of the member
        firewalls. Configuration of this object implements interface
        mapping illustrated by
        <xref linkend="linux_cluster_interface_mappings"/> and is
        shown below:
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="linux_heartbeat_cluster_2">
          <title>Failover Group object configuration</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/linux-heartbeat-cluster-2.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Firewall Builder GUI proides a way to configure some
        parameters for the failover
        protocols <emphasis>heartbeat</emphasis>
        and <emphasis>OpenAIS</emphasis>. Click <emphasis>Edit
          protocol parameters</emphasis> button to open dialog for
        this:
      </para>
      
      <table frame='none' tabstyle='two_columns_layout_table'>
        <title></title>
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left'  rowsep='1'>
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
          <tbody valign='top'>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <figure id="heartbeat_parameters">
                    <title>Editing parameters for the heartbeat protocol</title>
                    <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/heartbeat-parameters.png"/>
                  </figure>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <figure id="openais_parameters">
                    <title>Editing parameters for the OpenAIS protocol</title>
                    <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/openais-parameters.png"/>
                  </figure>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
        Firewall Builder only supports multicast or unicast
        heartbeat configuration. You can enter the address and port
        number in the dialog. If you turn checkbox "Use unicast
        address" on, generated iptables commands will match source
        and destination addresses of the corresponding interface of
        both member firewalls. If this checkbox is off, it is
        assumed heartbeat is configured to use multicast and
        generated iptables commands will only match this multicast
        address in both INPUT and OUTPUT chains.
      </para>

      <para>
        As with heartbeat, you can configure ip address and port
        number for the OpenAIS protocol. There is no unicast option
        here.
      </para>

      <para>
        Cluster object should also have State Synchronization group
        child object. Create it using context menu "Add State
        Synchronization Group" item if this object does not
        exist. In this object you need to configure member
        interfaces that should be used for state synchronization. On
        Linux, state synchronization is done using conntrackd daemon
        (<ulink url="http://conntrack-tools.netfilter.org/"><citetitle>conntrack-tools
            home page</citetitle></ulink>). Configure State
        Synchronization group object with interfaces of the member
        firewalls used to pass conntrackd packets:
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="linux_cluster_statesync_mappings">
          <title>State synchronization group object in the tree</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/linux-cluster-statesync-mappings.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The State Synchronization group object should look like this:
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="linux_cluster_statesync_group">
          <title>State synchronization group object parameters</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/linux-cluster-statesync-group.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Member firewalls and their inetrfaces appear in the panel in
        the right hand side of the dialog. Firewall Builder uses
        this information to automatically generate iptables rules to
        permit conntrackd packets. Firewall Builder assumes
        conntrackd is configured to send synchronization packets
        over dedicated interface (which generally is a good idea
        anyway). You may use internal inetrface of the firewall for
        this purpose as well. See examples of conntrackd
        configuration in Firewall Builder CookBook. You can configure
        ip address and port number for the conntrack as well.
      </para>

      <para>
        <figure id="conntrack_parameters">
          <title>Editing parameters for the Conntrack state synchronization protocol</title>
          <graphic scale="50" fileref="cluster_config/images/conntrack-parameters.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>

    </sect1>

