<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="interface_names">
  <title>Interface Names</title>

  <para>
    By default Firewall Builder attempts to determine an interfaces 
    function based on the name of the interface. For example, on Linux 
    if an interface is named <emphasis>eth2.102</emphasis> based on 
    the interface name Firewall Builder will determine that the interface 
    appears to be a VLAN interface with parent interface <emphasis>eth2
    </emphasis> and VLAN ID 102.
  </para>

  <para>
    If a user tries to create an interface with a name that doesn't 
    match the expected patterns Firewall Builder will generate an error. 
    For example, attempting to create the same <emphasis>eth2.102</emphasis> 
    interface from our previous example as an interface object directly 
    under a firewall object Firewall Builder will generate the error shown 
    in <xref linkend="interface_name_error"/>.
  </para>

    <para>
      <figure id="interface_name_error">
        <title>Error message when incorrect VLAN interface is created</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="interface_config/images/interface_name_error.png"/>
      </figure>
    </para>
  
  <para>
    If instead the <emphasis>eth2.102</emphasis> interface were to be 
    created as a child object under the <emphasis>eth2</emphasis> interface 
    then Firewall Builder would not generate the error since the VLAN 
    interface eth2.102 should be a sub-interface of eth2. Note that 
    in this case Firewall Builder will automatically set the interface 
    type to VLAN and will set the VLAN ID to 102.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can view and edit the interface type and VLAN ID by clicking 
    on the "Advanced Interface Settings ..." button in the editor 
    panel of the interface. An example of the advanced settings for 
    eth2.102, when created as a child interface of eth2, is shown in 
    diagram <xref linkend="auto_vlan_interface_config"/>.
  </para>

    <para>
      <figure id="auto_vlan_interface_config">
        <title>Advanced settings for eth2.102 interface</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="interface_config/images/auto_vlan_interface_config.png"/>
      </figure>
    </para>

  <para>
    Sometimes you may want to override the default behavior where 
    Firewall Builder expects interface names to follow a specific 
    naming convention. To disable this feature, open the Firewall 
    Builder preferences window, click on the Objects tab and click 
    on the Interface sub-tab in the lower window. Uncheck the 
    checkbox labeled "Verify interface names and autoconfigure their 
    parameters using known name patterns".
  </para>

    <para>
      <figure id="disable_name_checks">
        <title>Disable automatic name checking</title>
        <graphic scale="70" fileref="interface_config/images/disable_name_checks.png"/>
      </figure>
    </para>

  <para>
    In this mode Firewall Builder will not auto populate any fields, 
    even if the interface name matches an expected pattern like 
    <emphasis>eth2.102</emphasis>.  All interface parameters, such as 
    interface type and VLAN ID, must be configured manually.
  </para>

</sect1>

