    <sect1 id="problems_after_policy_activation">
      <title>Issues after new policy activation</title>

      <sect2>
        <title>Cannot access only some web sites</title>

        <para><emphasis>Can access most web sites through the firewall just fine,
        except for a few.</emphasis></para>

        <para>The browser would state "waiting for www.somesite.com" for a
        while and then time out when you connect to one of these sites.</para>

        <para>This might be caused by a MTU problem if you are on a DSL
        connection using PPPoE. Here are couple of useful pages that describe
        the problem in details:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>http://www.dslreports.com/tweaks/MTU</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>http://www.internetweekly.org/llarrow/mtumss.html</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>If your firewall runs iptables you can use option "Clamp MSS to
        MTU" in the firewall settings dialog to work around it.</para>

        <para>For the PF firewalls similar option is called "Enforce maximum
        MSS" and is located in the "Scrub rule options" tab of firewall
        settings dialog. It allows for setting MSS value of TCP sessions
        opened through the firewall; try values between 1460 or 1464 (1464 is
        the maximum MSS value that can be used on PPPoE connections without
        fragmentation).</para>

        <para>There is no way to change MSS value on the ipf, ipfw and pix
        firewalls. If your firewall is one of these, you may need to change
        MTU on your workstation. See links above for recommendations on how to
        do it.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Firewall becomes very slow with new policy</title>

        <para>You compiled and started firewall policy script and then
        noticed that seemingly every operation on the firewall takes a
        lot longer than before. For example, it takes forever to log
        into it using telnet or ssh, different services take a few
        minutes to start or won't start at all.</para>

        <para>Most likely the firewall needs to be able to do DNS
        lookups but can't. Look in /etc/resolv.conf for the address of
        the name server it is using and make sure you have a rule in
        the policy to permit connections to it. Use firewall object in
        "Source", the name server object in "Destination" and a
        standard service object group "DNS" in the Service
        field.</para>

        <para>If your firewall runs caching name server and file
        /etc/resolv.conf lists "127.0.0.1" as a name server address,
        then you need to permit firewall to talk to itself. Here is
        how such /etc/resolv.conf file looks like:</para>

<programlisting>
    domain your_domain.com
    nameserver 127.0.0.1 
</programlisting>

        <para>You need to add a rule with the firewall object in both
        Source and Destination fields and the service object group
        "DNS" in the Service field to the loopback interface. This
        rule permits the firewall machine to communicate with the name
        server running on it, but you need another rule to permit the
        name server to send DNS queries and receive answers. This rule
        should have the firewall object in Source, Destination should
        be set to "any" and the same standard service object group
        "DNS" should be used in the Service element. Now not only
        firewall can query the name server process running on it, but
        the process in turn can send queries to other name servers on
        the Internet and receive answers.</para>

        <para>Here is the rule that should be added to the loopback
        interface:</para>

      <figure float="1" id="dns1">
        <title>DNS on loopback</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="troubleshooting/images/dns1.png" />
      </figure>

        <para>Here is the rule that permits the name server process to
        communicate with name servers on the Internet:</para>

      <figure float="1" id="dns2">
        <title>DNS on to name servers</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="troubleshooting/images/dns2.png" />
      </figure>

        <para> Depending on your policy design, you may want to permit
        all services rather than just DNS on the loopback interface
        because there are many other processes that need to be able to
        communicate with the same host, such as X11, RPC and
        others. The dedicated firewall machine should not run anything
        unnecessary, so there you may experiment with limiting the
        number of services in the rule on loopback the interface. On
        the other hand, if you use fwbuilder to protect a server that
        runs many different services, permitting any service on the
        loopback may be a simpler solution.</para>

        <para>The next rule permits processes running on the firewall
        to communicate with other processes running on the same
        machine on all protocols:
        </para>
        
        <figure id="dns3">
          <title>Any to any on firewall</title>
          <graphic scale="70" fileref="troubleshooting/images/dns3.png" />
        </figure>

      <para>
        
      </para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>X won't start on a server protected by the firewall</title>

        <para>You've built a firewall script to protect a server, but after you ran the script, X (KDE, Gnome) won't start anymore.</para>

        <para>The reason for this is the same as in the DNS problem -- you need a rule to permit processes to communicate with other
 processes running on the same machine. This can easily be achieved with the following rule added to the loopback interface:</para>

      <figure id="dns3-1">
        <title>Any to any on firewall</title>
            <graphic scale="70" fileref="troubleshooting/images/dns3.png" />
      </figure>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Cannot access Internet from behind firewall</title>

        <para><emphasis>I compiled and activated firewall policy, but workstations
        behind the firewall still cannot access the Internet.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Here are few troubleshooting steps:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Make sure you compiled, then installed and activated
              firewall policy. Were there any errors during compile and
              activation?</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>check if ip forwarding is turned on (pull down menu in the
              "Network" tab of the firewall object dialog).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>try to ping hosts on the Internet by their IP address, not
              their name. This helps isolate DNS problems. If you can ping by
              address but can't ping by name, then you need to add policy
              rules to permit DNS queries.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Look in firewall's log for records indicating that it
              drops packets. Error in the policy design can cause it to block
              connections that you really want to go through.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use option "Log everything" to make all rules generate log
              entries, this sometimes helps pinpoint a rule that drops
              packets.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>Things to check in the policy:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Check if you have a NAT rule if your protected network is
              using "private" IP addresses.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the NAT rule is there, then you may need to add a
              policy rule to actually permit connections from the protect
              network.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In case when NAT is not used, check if the routing is
              configured properly. If your firewall separates subnets A and B,
              and you are trying to connect from the host on subnet A to the
              host on subnet B, then both hosts should have routing to the
              opposite network. Host on the net A needs a route for the net B,
              pointing at the firewall. Similarly, host on the net B needs a
              route for the net A, also pointing at the firewall. If one (or
              both) host has a default route pointing at the firewall, then it
              won't need a special route for another network.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Installing updated firewall policy seems to make no difference</title>

        <para><emphasis>I compiled and activated firewall policy, but
            my tests seem to show no difference. If I add a rule to
            block some protocol, it remains permitted for some
            reason.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Here are few troubleshooting steps:</para>

        <para>
          First of all, make sure you compile the right firewall
          object and install on the right firewall machine, the same
          one you use for testing. It is all too easy to mix them up
          if you have several firewalls. Another case when this
          happens often is when you work on the firewall replacement
          and have both old and new firewall machines running
          simultaneously. You may be pushing updated policy to the new
          machine, while traffic is still routed through the old one.
        </para>

        <para>
          If you test by adding a rule to deny some protocol and then
          trying to connect with this protocol, but it remains
          permitted, check that you do not have any rules that permit
          it above the one you've added for testing. You can use
          "Find" function (<xref linkend="find-replace"/>) in Firewall
          Builder GUI to find all uses of any service object.  Keep in
          mind that there could be two objects with different names
          but the same port and protocol configuration. You can search
          for objects by their name, tcp/udp port number, ip address
          etc.
        </para>

        <para>
          If you use ssh access to test rules by adding a rule that
          denies ssh access to the firewall, keep in mind that
          automatic rule may override it. The automatic rule is added
          using checkbox "Always permit ssh access from the management
          workstation" in the firewall settings dialog. See
          <xref linkend="backup_ssh_access_rule"/>.
        </para>

        <para>
          Pay attention to the output that appears in the progress
          window of the policy installer when you install and activate
          updated policy. Iptables script generated by fwbuilder
          always prints the following information when it is activated
          (here is an example):

          <programlisting>
Activating firewall script generated Mon Aug 09 17:22:11 2010 by vadim
Running prolog script
Verifying interfaces: eth0 eth1 lo
Rule 0 (NAT)
Rule 0 (eth0)
Rule 1 (lo)
Rule 2 (global)
Rule 3 (global)
Rule 4 (global)
Rule 5 (global)
Rule 6 (global)
Rule 7 (global)
Rule 8 (global)
Rule 9 (global)
Running epilog script
          </programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
          Do you see the "Activating firewall script ... " line in the
          progress output of the installer? If not, you might be
          running different script on the firewall. Compare the date
          and time reported by the script, could it be too old ?
        </para>

        <note> 
          <para>
            Output shown above appears in the progress output of the
            installer when you run it with both "Quiet" and "Verbose"
            options turned off. Running it with "quiet" turned on
            suppresses these lines and running it in verbose mode
            produces a lot more output.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>
          Another reason updated policy may not be activated is if you
          tried an external activation script previously but perhaps
          forgot about it. In this case the installer will be running
          this script instead of newly generated firewall script. You
          can configure alternative command that installer should
          execute on the firewall in the "Installer" tab of the
          firewall settings dialog. If this option is set to some
          script on the firewall machine and this script does not in
          turn call script generated by fwbuilder, you might be
          reloading the same firewall policy every time you
          install. This is just another thing to check.
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

