    <sect1 id="rcs-troubleshooting">
      <title>RCS Troubleshooting</title>
      <sect2 id="error-adding-file-rcs">
        <title>Error adding file to RCS</title>

          <para><emphasis>Error adding file to RCS: Fatal error during initial RCS checkin of file</emphasis></para>

          <para>You will get this error if you do not have RCS set up on your system. To resolve it, install and configure RCS on the w
orkstation running Firewall Builder.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="error-checking-file-out">
        <title>"Error checking file out: co: RCS file c:/fwbuilder/RCS/file.fwb is in use"</title>

        <para><emphasis>I cannot open my data file, I get error "Error checking file out: co: RCS file c:/fwbuilder/RCS/file.fwb is in 
use"</emphasis></para>

        <para>A catastrophe (e.g. a system crash) can cause RCS to leave behind a semaphore file that causes later invocations of RCS t
o claim that the RCS file is in use. To fix this, remove the semaphore file. A semaphore file name typically begins with , or ends with
 _.</para>

        <para>If not that, then it could be another manifestation of bug #1908351</para>

        <para>See if there is a file with the name starting and ending with a comma in the RCS directory (like ",file.fwb,"). The file 
should have length of zero bytes. This file is a lock file, it is created and deleted by RCS tools. Bug 1908351 caused this lock file t
o be left behind. When that happens, ci won't check file in because it thinks another copy of ci is already running. Likewise, co won't
 check the file out for the same reason. If such file exists (zero bytes in length and name starting or ending with a comma), just dele
te it and try to check your data file out again.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="error-checking-file-out-2">
        <title>"Error checking file out:"</title>
        <para><emphasis>I cannot open my data file, I get error "Error checking file out:"</emphasis></para>

        <para>Such non-descriptive error message is usually caused by hard unrecoverable errors experienced by RCS tools. Unfortunately
 these tools not always report errors in the best way possible and when this happens, Firewall Builder GUI cannot provide any better di
agnostics than it gets from the tool. Such poor diagnostics of errors happens more frequently on Windows than on other platforms.</para>

        <para>Here are few things to check and try:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>First of all, check file permissions. The data file (.fwb) should be read-only. RCS repository file (.fwb,v) 
should also be read-only. Repository file may be located in subdirectory RCS but that depends on the OS. It may be located in the same 
directory with corresponding data file (.fwb) as well.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Try to check the file out manually to see if you can get better diagnostics:</para>
          <para>If you use Windows, start MS DOS window and in it navigate to the folder where you keep your files, then execute the fo
llowing command:</para>
          <programlisting>c:\FWBuilder\co.exe -l filename.fwb</programlisting>
          <para>If it checks the file out successfully, it just prints revision number and 'done'. Otherwise it will print some error.</para>
          <para>After you do that, you need to check the file in to RCS again. Do it like this:</para>
          <programlisting>c:\FWBuilder\ci.exe -u filename.fwb</programlisting>
          <para>Since the file hasn't changed, it should just check it in without asking you for the RCS log record. If you can success
fully check it out and then check it in again from the command line, then the GUI should work too.</para>
          <para>On Linux, *BSD and Mac OS X the process is exactly the same, except for the path to the checkout and checkin commands:</para>

          <para>To check the file out use</para>
          <programlisting>co -l filename.fwb</programlisting>
          <para>
      To check the file in use
          </para>
          <programlisting>ci -u filename.fwb</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

