    <sect1 id="troubleshooting-compiler-runtime">
      <title>Firewall Compiler and Other Runtime Issues</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Firewall Builder crashes</title>

        <para><emphasis>Firewall Builder or policy compiler crashes</emphasis></para>

        <para>Please file a bug on Sourceforge. Provide information we might need to fix the problem. See the <ulink url="http://www.fw
builder.org/contact.html"><citetitle>Firewall Builder Contact</citetitle></ulink> page for links to bug tracking and instructions for f
iling bugs.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
          <title>Older data file cannot be loaded in Firewall Builder</title>

        <para><emphasis>Data file created in the older version of fwbuilder cannot be loaded in the latest one</emphasis></para>

          <para>Sometimes this happens when you skip several versions trying to upgrade the program. There used to be a bug in the upgr
ade procedure somewhere around version 1.0.4 which broke automatic upgrades from versions before 1.0.4 to versions after that. If this 
happens to you, upgrade your data file using script fwb-upgrade.sh that you can find in Contrib/Scripts area on our SourceForge site.</para>
        </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>"I/O Error" while compiling policy. No other error.</title>

        <para><emphasis>"I/O Error" while compiling policy. There is no other indication of error though.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Did you install package with corresponding compiler ? Our pre-built compilers come in a separate RPMs named like this: fw
builder-ipt-2.0.2-1rh9.i386.rpm</para>

        <para>Check if compiler dumped core. If you can't find it, you may try to run compiler manually, providing the following comman
d line parameters:</para>

        <para><command>$ fwb_ipt  -f path_to_objects.xml   firewall_object_name</command></para> 
        <para>All policy compilers have the same command line format.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>ios_base::failbit set on Windows</title>

        <para><emphasis>Policy compiler stops with an error
        ios_base::failbit set on Windows</emphasis></para>

        <para>It looks something like this:</para>
        <programlisting>
---------------------------------------
fwb_ipfw -f C:/Documents and Settings/User/data.fwb -d C:/Documents
and Settings/User -r C:\FWBuilder\resources fw

 Compiling policy for fw ...
  Detecting rule shadowing
 Begin processing
 Policy compiled successfully 
ios_base::failbit set
------------------------------------------
        </programlisting>

        <para>First of all, check available free disk space. Also
        check if the output file ( fw.fw ) is opened in another
        program while compiler is running. That is, if you looked at
        it after the previous compiler run and opened it in Notepad,
        it becomes locked and compiler won't be able to overwrite it
        with the new copy until you close Notepad.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>"Cannot create virtual address NN.NN.NN.NN"</title>

        <para><emphasis>Policy compiler stops processing rules with
        error message "Cannot create virtual address
        NN.NN.NN.NN"</emphasis></para>

        <para>This happens when you are using an option "Create
        virtual addresses for NAT rules". The problem is that policy
        compiler needs to be able to determine interface of the
        firewall to assign virtual address to. In order to do that it
        scans all interfaces trying to find subnet requested NAT
        address is on. Sometimes firewall's interface has an address
        which belongs to a different network than NAT address
        specified in the rule; in this case compiler cannot identify
        an interface and aborts.</para>

        <para>The NAT rule still can be built without "-i" or "-o"
        option, but automatic assignment of virtual address is
        impossible. You need to turn off option "Create virtual
        addresses for NAT rules" in the tab "Firewall" of firewall
        dialog and configure this address manually. </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

