      <sect1 id="editing-policy-and-nat">
        <title>Editing Firewall Rule Sets</title>

        <sect2 id="adding-and-removing-rules">
          <title>Adding and Removing Rules</title>

          <figure id="editing-policy1">
            <title>Modifying Policy Rules</title>
            <graphic scale="60" fileref="firewall_policies/images/editing_policy1.png" />
          </figure>

          <para>
            Rules can be added, removed, or moved around in the rule set using 
            the <guimenu>Rules</guimenu> menu or the
            context menu shown in <xref linkend="editing-policy1" />. 
            To open the context menu, right-click 
            the rule number in the (the first column of the rule). 
          </para>

          <para>
            Using these functions, you can add new rules above or below the
            currently selected rule in the policy, remove rules, move
            the current rule up or down, or use standard copy and paste 
            operations on policy rules. Functions are appied to all selected
            rules.
          </para>

          <para>The following rule-related functions are available in the 
            <guimenu>Rules</guimenu> menu and the associated right-click context menu:</para>

          <para>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>New Group</para>

                <para>Groups contiguous rules together for
                easier handling. A group of rules can be collapsed in
                the display so that only the group name appears. This can
                make it easier to work with rule sets that have many
                rules. The <guimenuitem>New Group</guimenuitem> command opens
                a dialog that lets you create and name the new
                group. The currently selected rule is automatically added to the
                group. <xref linkend="using-rule-groups" /> provides 
                information on working with rule groups.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Add to the group</para>

                <para>This context menu selection appears only if you right-click 
                  a rule directly above or below an existing group. If
                selected, the current rule is added to the indicated
                group. <xref linkend="using-rule-groups" /> provides 
                  information on working with rule groups.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Remove from the group</para>

                <para>The context menu selection appears only if you right-click
                a rule that is currently in a group. This selection
                removes the rule from the group. If you remove a rule
                from the middle of a group, the group splits into two
                groups, one above and one below the selected rule. Both
                groups have the same name as the original
                group. <xref linkend="using-rule-groups" /> provides 
                  information on working with rule groups.</para>
              </listitem>
              
              <listitem>
                <para>Change Color</para>

                <para>
                  This menu item allows you to assign a color to the
                  rule background. Assigning colors is a good way to group rules
                  visually according to function.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Insert Rule</para>

                <para>
                  Inserts new rule above the current one.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Add Rule Below</para>

                <para>
                  Inserts a new rule below the current one.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Remove Rule</para>

                <para>
                  Removes the selected rule from the rule set.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Move Rule Up</para>

                <para>
                  Moves the selected rule up by one position. The keyboard
                  shortcut is "Ctrl-PgUp" on Linux and Windows or
                  "Cmd-PgUp" on Macintosh. If you select several
                  consecutive rules and use this menu item, all
                  selected rules move together.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Move Rule Down</para>

                <para>
                  Moves current rule down by one position. Keyboard
                  shortcut is "Ctrl-PgDown" on Linux and Windows or
                  "Cmd-PgDown" on Macintosh. If you select several
                  consecutive rules and use this menu item, all
                  selected rules move together.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Copy Rule</para>

                <para>
                  Copies the current rule to the clipboard.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Cut Rule</para>

                <para>
                  Copies current rule to the clipboard and removes it
                  from the rule set.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Paste Rule Above</para>

                <para>
                  Inserts the rule from the clipboard above the current
                  one.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Paste Rule Below</para>

                <para>
                  Inserts the rule from the clipboard below the current
                  one.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Disable Rule</para>

                <para>
                  Marks the rule as disabled; this makes the policy compiler
                  ignore it.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Compile rule</para>

                <para>This menu item compiles the selected rule and shows
                the result in the editor panel at the bottom of the
                main window.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="adding-removing-nat-rules">
          <title>Adding, Removing, and Modifying Objects in Policies and NAT
          Rules</title>

          <para>To add objects to a policy or NAT rule, you can either drag
          the objects from the obect tree and drop them into the corresponding rule
          element, or use a copy and paste operation.
          Objects can be copied into clipboard from the object tree
          or from another policy rule; in either case, use the right-click context menu or
          the main menu <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> option.</para>

          <para>Right-clicking when the cursor is over the rule
          elements "Source","Destination" or "Service" opens a
          context-sensitive pop-up menu ( <xref linkend="editing-policy2" />
          ). The same context menu appears when you hover the mouse over the "Original
          Source", "Original Destination", "Original Service", "Translated
          Source", "Translated Destination" and "Translated Service" rule
          elements in a NAT rule.</para>

          <figure id="editing-policy2">
            <title>Modifying Objects in a Policy Rule</title>
            <graphic scale="60" fileref="firewall_policies/images/editing_policy2.png" />
          </figure>

          <para>This menu provides items for the following functions:</para>

          <para>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>Edit</para>

                <para>This menu item opens the currently selected
                object in the dialog area.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Copy</para>

                <para>The object is copied into clipboard.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Cut</para>

                <para>The object is copied into clipboard and removed from the
                rule.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Paste</para>

                <para>The object on the clipboard is pasted into the
                field in the the rule. A copy of the object stays on
                the clipboard, so it may be pasted multiple
                times.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Delete</para>

                <para>The object is deleted (actually moved to the
                "Deleted Objects" library).
                  </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Where used</para>

                <para>Opens a dialog that shows a list of where the
                rule is used in all rule sets in the current
                firewall. In addition, simply clicking on an object
                puts a red rectangle around that object everywhere it
                occurs in the rule set.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Reveal in tree</para>

                <para>Shows the object in its location in the
                appropriate tree. Simply clicking on the object does
                the same thing.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Negate</para>

                <para>All objects in the selected rule element are negated.
                The rule element "Source" is negated in rule #1 in screenshot
                <xref linkend="editing-policy2" />.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Compile rule</para>

                <para>This menu item compiles selected rule and shows
                the result in the editor panel at the bottom of the
                main window.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="changing-action-for-rule">
          <title>Changing the Rule Action</title>

          <para>To change a rule action, right-click in the <guilabel>Action</guilabel> field 
            and select the new action from the context menu ( <xref
              linkend="editing-policy3" /> ). Depending on the action selected,
            the <guilabel>Action</guilabel> dialog may open for you to specify parameter settings. 
          </para>

          <figure id="editing-policy3">
            <title>Modifying the Action of a Policy Rule</title>
            <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_policies/images/editing_policy3.png" />  
          </figure>

          <para>Rule actions are described in detail in
          <xref linkend="action" />.</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="changing_direction">
          <title>Changing Rule Direction</title>

          <para>To change the traffic direction for a rule, right-click 
            in the <guilabel>Direction</guilabel> field and select the new direction
            from the context menu (<xref linkend="editing-policy4" />).
           </para>

          <figure id="editing-policy4">
            <title>Modifying the Direction of a Policy Rule</title>
            <graphic scale="50" fileref="firewall_policies/images/editing_policy4.png" />
          </figure>
          
          <para>Traffic directions are described in detail in
            <xref linkend="direction" />.</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="rule-options">
          <title>Setting Rule Options and Logging</title>

          <para>To change the options and log settings associated with a rule, 
            right-click in the <guilabel>Options</guilabel> field and select
            a menu tiem from the context menu.             
            Enable or disable logging by right-clicking the <guilabel>Options</guilabel> field and 
            selecting <guilabel>Logging On</guilabel> or <guilabel>Logging Off</guilabel>,
            respectively, from the context menu. Set rule options or change log settings
            by opening the 
            <guilabel>Options</guilabel> dialog. You can do this by double-clicking 
            within the Options field of the rule 
            or by right-clicking the <guilabel>Options</guilabel> field and 
            selecting <guilabel>Rule Options</guilabel> from the context menu.         </para>
          
          <figure id="editing-policy5">
            <title>Rule Options for Policies</title>
                <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/editing_policy5.png" />
          </figure>

          <para>Rule options and log settings are described in detail in
            <xref linkend="options" />.
          </para>
          
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2 id="multiple_operations_per_rule">
          <title>Configuring Multiple Operations per Rule</title>
          
          <para>Suppose you have a scenario where you want the firewall to 
            perform a number of operations on packets of a certain type. 
            For this traffic type, you want the firewall to mark (tag) the packet, 
            then classify it, and then accept the packet. Instead of 
            defining multiple single-action rules to accomplish this
            behavior, Firewall Builder allows
            you to combine a set of rule options with an action within 
            a single rule, so that the firewall performs all the specified operations
            when the rule is matched. The ability to specify 
            multiple operations for a single rule 
            helps keep the number of required rules to a minimum, 
            and keeps your rule set simpler and more readable.
          </para>
          
          <para>Some target firewall platforms, such as <application>PF</application>, natively support multi-action
            rules. Other firewall platforms, such as <application>iptables</application>, do not explicitly support
            configuring multiple operations per rule. For these
            platforms, Firewall Builder automatically transforms the configured policy
            into however many rules are required by the target platform.
          </para>

          <sect3 id="multiple_rule_actions_iptables">
            <title>Configuring an iptables rule to Accept and Classify</title>

            <para>Let's look at an example where traffic matching a particular 
            rule, such as the one shown in <xref linkend="iptables_rule_accept_classify" />.
            This rule matches SSH traffic to a specific address.
            </para>

            <figure id="iptables_rule_accept_classify">
              <title>Basic rule with no options set</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/iptables_rule_accept_classify.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>The way the rule is currently defined traffic matching the rule 
            will be accepted and no other action will be taken. However, if in 
            addition to accepting the traffic you also want to classify the 
            traffic into classful qdisc for use with tc, then you need to use 
            the Classify rule option to set the classify value that should be 
            set for traffic matching the rule.
            </para>

            <para>In this example we will use a qdisc value of 1:20 which matches 
            a value configured in tc for prioritizing SSH traffic.
            </para>
            
            <para>Steps for adding classify string to matching traffic.</para>
            
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>Right-click on Options section of rule and select
              Rule Options</listitem>
              <listitem>Click on Classify tab in the Editor panel at the bottom of 
              the screen</listitem>
              <listitem>Enter the value 1:20 in the text box for the Classify 
              string as shown in <xref linkend="iptables_rule_accept_classify_string" />
              </listitem> 
            </orderedlist>

            <figure id="iptables_rule_accept_classify_string">
              <title>Entering classify string in Editor panel</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/iptables_rule_accept_classify_string.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Notice that the Classify icon and classify string value are now 
            displayed in the rule's Options column. This lets you quickly and easily 
            see what options have been configured for a particular rule.
            </para>

            <figure id="iptables_rule_accept_classify_rule">
              <title>Rule with Classify option set</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/iptables_rule_accept_classify_rule.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Using the <xref linkend="compile-single-rule" /> feature you can 
            see that this rule will result in the following iptables commands being 
            generated.</para>

<programlisting>
$IPTABLES -A FORWARD -p tcp -m tcp -d 192.168.2.10 --dport 22 -m state --state NEW \
-j ACCEPT 
# Allow SSH to server
$IPTABLES -t mangle -A POSTROUTING -p tcp -m tcp -d 192.168.2.10 --dport 22 -m state \
--state NEW  -j CLASSIFY --set-class 1:20
</programlisting>

          </sect3>

          <sect3 id="multiple_rule_actions_pf">
            <title>Configuring a PF rule to Tag packets</title>

            <para>In this example traffic matching a rule on a PF firewall should be 
            tagged with a tag value that identifies the traffic is from an internal 
            network that entered the firewall inbound on its internal (em1) network 
            interface.
            </para> 

            <para>First, a TagService object needs to be created that will identify 
            the tag value that should be applied to the matching traffic. In this case 
            the tag value will be set to "Internal_Net".
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>In the object tree right-click on the TagServices folder and 
              select New TagService</listitem>
              <listitem>Enter a name for the TagService object</listitem>
              <listitem>Enter the tag value that should be applied, in this case 
              "Internal_Net"</listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>The TagService should like like <xref linkend="pf_tag_service"/>.
            </para>
            
            <figure id="pf_tag_service">
              <title>TagService object settings</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/pf_tag_service.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Next, a rule that matches the internal network traffic inbound on 
            networking interface em1 needs to be created. Since we only want to tag 
            the packets so they can be acted on by later rules the Action for the 
            rule will be set to Continue as shown in <xref linkend="pf_tag_rule_continue"/>
            .</para>

            <figure id="pf_tag_rule_continue">
              <title>Basic rule without tag being set</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/pf_tag_rule_continue.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>To set the tag value that will be added to packets that match 
            this rule, do the following:
            </para>
           
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>Right-click on the Options column of the rule and select 
              Rule Options</listitem>
              <listitem>Click on the Tag tab in the Editor panel at the bottom
              </listitem>
              <listitem>Drag-and-drop the TagService object created earlier from 
              the object tree to the the drop target in the Editor panel as shown 
              in <xref linkend="pf_tag_rule_continue_tag"/>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <figure id="pf_tag_rule_continue_tag">
              <title>Setting the TagService object to use in the rule</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/pf_tag_rule_continue_tag.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>After the TagService object has been added to the rule, the final 
            rule should look like <xref linkend="pf_tag_rule_complete"/>.
            </para>

            <figure id="pf_tag_rule_complete">
              <title>Completed tag rule for PF</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/pf_tag_rule_complete.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Using the <xref linkend="compile-single-rule" /> feature you can 
            see that this rule will result in the following PF commands being 
            generated.</para>

<programlisting>
# Tag internal traffic
pass in on em1 inet from 192.168.1.0/24 to any tag Internal_Net label "RULE 0 --  "
</programlisting>

          </sect3>
          
          
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="using-rule-groups">
          <title>Using Rule Groups</title>
          
          <sect3>
            <title>Creating Rule Groups</title>

            <para>If you have a rule set with quite a few rules, it can be
              useful to lump some of them together into rule groups. A rule
              group is a contiguous set of rules that you have grouped
              together and assigned a name to. Once you have a group, you can
              collapse it down visually to save screen real estate, then pop
              it back open when you need to look inside.</para>

            <para>Rule groups <emphasis>only</emphasis> affect how the rules
              are displayed visually. They have <emphasis>no affect</emphasis> 
              on how the rule set is compiled or how it works on the firewall.
             </para>

            <para>Let's look at a simple example of using rule groups.</para>

            <para><xref linkend="rule-group1" /> shows a fragment of a set
              of rules. There are two rules for packets destined for eth0,
              several rules for packets destined for eth1, and a couple rules
              for eth2-destined packets.</para>

            <figure id="rule-group1">
              <title>Rules without Grouping</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group1.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>The eth2 rules take up a lot of space, so let's group them
              together. We can then collapse the group so it uses less
              space.</para>

            <para>To create the group, right-click in the rule number
              cell of the first "eth1" rule and
              select <guimenuitem>New group</guimenuitem>. (You don't
              have to click the first rule. Any rule in the group
              will do.)</para>

            <figure id="rule-group2">
              <title>Creating a Group</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group2.png" />  
            </figure>
            
            <para>A dialog appears. Enter the name of the group. This name
              is for your convenience only, so it can be anything. Here we're
              naming the group after the interface, but a more descriptive
              name can be more useful.</para>

            <figure id="rule-group3">
              <title>Naming a Group</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group3.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Now we have a group with one entry. This doesn't provide
              much value, so let's add other rules to the group. You can add
              as many rules as you want, but they must all be contiguous in
              the rule set.</para>

            <figure id="rule-group4">
              <title>Group with One Entry</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group4.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>To add more rules, right-click a rule adjacent to the
              rule in the group, then select <guimenuitem>Add to the group
                eth1</guimenuitem>.</para>

            <figure id="rule-group5">
              <title>Adding a Rule to a Group</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group5.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>Do that to the rest of the "eth1" rows, and we now
              have a populated group. You can select several
              consequtive rules and add them to the group at once.</para>

            <figure id="rule-group6">
              <title>A Group of Rules</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group6.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>To collapse the group, just click the little minus
              (-) or a triangle icon (depends on the OS and visual
              style) in the upper left of the group.
            </para>

            <figure id="rule-group7">
              <title>Collapsed Group</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/rule-group7.png" />  
            </figure>

            <para>The group now takes up less room on your screen, though it
              has not changed in function.</para>
          </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Modifying Rule Groups</title>

          <para>
            You can modify a rule group after you have created
            it. Options are as follows:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Renaming a Group</para>

              <para>
                To rename a group, right-click the group name (or
                anywhere on the gray bar that heads the rule, and
                select <guimenuitem>Rename group</guimenuitem>. Then,
                change the name in the dialog and
                click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Add more rules to a group</para>

              <para>
                You can add an existing rule to a group if the rule is
                directly above or below the group. Simply right-click
                the rule and select <guimenuitem>Add to the group
                eth1</guimenuitem>.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove a rule from a group</para>

              <para>
                To remove a rule from the group while leaving it in
                the rule set, right-click in the number of the rule
                (left-most column) and select <guimenuitem>Remove from
                the group</guimenuitem>. You can only remove the first
                or the last rule in the group. Rules in the middle of
                the group can not be removed from it.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove a rule completely</para>

              <para>
                You can remove a rule in a group entirely by
                right-clicking the number of the rule (left-most
                column) and selecting <guimenuitem>Remove
                rule</guimenuitem>. This will remove the rule from the
                rule set entirely and works the same regardless of
                whether the rule is a member of a group or not. If you
                want to move the rule to anther part of the rule set,
                select <guimenuitem>Cut rule</guimenuitem> instead,
                and then paste the rule elsewhere.
              </para>
            </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rule-elements">
      <title>Support for Rule Elements and Features on Various Firewalls</title>

      <para>Certain fields in the rules are only available if the target
      firewall platform supports them. For example, the iptables firewall
      provides controls for logging of matched packets, while Cisco PIX does
      not; PIX always logs every packet it drops. Where possible, the policy
      compiler tries to emulate the missing feature. For example,
      OpenBSD PF does not support negation natively, but the policy compiler
      provides a workaround and tries to emulate
      this feature for PF. Another example is policy rules with "Outbound"
      direction. Cisco PIX supports only inbound access lists, so the policy
      compiler emulates outbound Access Lists while generating configuration
      for PIX. <xref linkend="policy-rule-elements" /> represents a list of
      fields in the rules and which firewall platforms support them.
      Information about these fields and features is available for Firewall Builder
      GUI that disables corresponding menu items and hides associated policy
      elements when they are not supported.</para>

      <para>
        <table id="policy-rule-elements" tabstyle='reg_table'>
          <title>Rule Features Available on Different Platforms</title>

          <tgroup cols="11">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Firewall Platform</entry>

                <entry>Source</entry>

                <entry>Destination</entry>

                <entry>Service</entry>

                <entry>Time Interval</entry>

                <entry>Direction</entry>

                <entry>Action</entry>

                <entry>Logging/ Options</entry>

                <entry>Comment</entry>

                <entry>Negation in Policy rules</entry>

                <entry>Negation in NAT rules</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>iptables</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>ipfilter</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>pf</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Cisco PIX</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </sect2>

    </sect1>

