    <sect1 id="policies-and-rules">
      <title>Policies and Rules</title>

      <para>Each firewall object has several sets of rules associated
      with it: Access Policy (just "Policy" in the GUI), Network
      Address Translation (NAT), and Routing rules. Rules in the
      access policy control access to and from the firewall machine
      and the machines behind it.  NAT rules describe address and port
      transformations that the firewall should make to packets flowing
      through it. Routing rules establish static routes in the
      firewall.</para>

      <para>Firewall software varies widely in the way it can process
      packets.  For example, some firewalls perform address and port
      transformations first and then apply policy rules, while some
      others do it the other way around. There are many other
      variations and features specific to particular
      implementations. In Firewall Builder though, you work with an
      abstract firewall that looks and behaves the same regardless of
      the target firewall platform. You can build and install firewall
      polices for one platform, then switch the target and use the
      exact same policies to generate rules for an entirely different
      platform. (This assumes both platforms support the features you
      need.)</para>

      <para>Firewall Builder compensates for differences in
      implementation between firewall platforms.  For example, Cisco
      PIX applies its Access List rules to the packet before it
      performs address and port transformations according to the NAT
      rules. As a result, a policy rule that controls access to a
      server behind the firewall doing NAT should be written using the
      firewall object instead of the server object. The meaning of
      such a rule is not obvious at a glance since you have to keep in
      mind all the NAT rules as well as remember that this policy rule
      controls access not to the firewall machine, but rather to the
      server behind it. Firewall Builder compensates for variations
      like this by using smart algorithms to transform rules defined
      in the GUI into rules that achieve the desired effect in the
      target firewall platform. Using Firewall Builder, you can write
      your rules as if NAT translation will happen before the access
      rules are applied.</para>


    </sect1>

