    <sect1 id="routing">
      <title>Routing Ruleset</title>

      <para>
        Though not strictly a firewall function, Firewall Builder
        also lets you configure the routing tables of Linux, BSD,  
        Cisco ASA/PIX and Cisco IOS firewalls. Routing rules are ignored 
        for other firewalls.
      </para>

      <para>
        Construct these rules the same way you construct access
        policy or NAT rules, by dragging the appropriate objects into
        the rules. When you run the compiled script on the target
        firewall, the routing rule set rules create static routes in the
        firewall.
      </para>

      <note>
      <para>
        When executing a firewall script, all existing
        routing rules previously set by user space processes are
        deleted. To see which rules will be deleted, you can use the
        <command>ip route show</command> command. All lines not
        including "proto kernel" will be deleted upon reload of the
        firewall script.
      </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        If you want to use ECMP (Equal Cost Multi Path) routing
        rules with your iptables-based firewall, make sure your kernel
        is compiled with the CONFIG_IP_ROUTE_MULTIPATH option. See
        <xref linkend="ecmp" /> for instructions on creating multiple
        paths to a destination.
      </para>

        <figure id="routing-rule1">
          <title>A Routing Rule</title>
              <graphic scale="70" fileref="firewall_policies/images/routing-rule1.png" />
        </figure>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Destination</para>

              <para>Can be any addressable object (hosts, addresses,
              address ranges, groups, networks.) The default
              destination ("Default") is 0.0.0.0/0.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Gateway</para>

              <para>Can be an IP address, an interface, or a host with only one interface.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Interface</para>

              <para>
                Specify an outbound interface for packets. This interface must be 
                a child interface of the firewall. This option is not available for 
                BSD firewalls.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Metric</para>

              <para>
                The metric of the route. The default metric for PIX is 1, so a "0" 
                in a rule is automatically changed to 1 at compilation. This option 
                is not available for BSD firewalls.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Comment</para>

              <para>A free-form text field.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>
          RedHat seems to reset routing rules explicitly upon
          system startup. Therefore, it's hard to distinguish
          interface routes from routes set up by the user. On RedHat
          systems, you need to include the interface basic routing
          rules into your Firewall Builder routing setup.
          </para>
          
          <para>
          IF YOU DO NOT FOLLOW THIS HINT, YOUR MACHINE WILL FREEZE 
          ANY NETWORK TRAFFIC UPON START OF THE FIREWALL SCRIPT. This 
          means, for example, if eth0 has network 192.168.3.0/24 
          attached to it, you need to add a route with 
          Destination=Network(192.168.3.0/24), Gateway empty, and
          Interface=eth0. 
          </para>
          
          <para> 
          This problem was encountered on RedHat 8.0, but other versions 
          and distributions might be affected too. (Debian sarge and SuSE 
          Linux work fine without interface routing rules being included 
          in Firewall Builder routing rules.)
          </para>
        </note>

      <sect2>
        <title>Handling of the Default Route</title>

          <para>
            "Default route" is special in that it is critical for
            your ability to access the firewall machine when it is
            managed remotely. To make sure you do not cut off access
            accidentally by not adding default to the routing rules in
            Firewall Builder, Firewall Builder treats the default route
            in a special way.
          </para>

          <para>
            If the default route is configured in the routing rule set 
            in Firewall Builder, then the default route found in the 
            routing table is deleted and replaced with the one configured 
            in Firewall Builder. However, if there is no
            default route in the routing rule set in Firewall Builder
            configuration, then the original default route found in the
            routing table is not deleted.
          </para>
         
          <para> 
            Additionally, the script checks if the installation of routing 
            entries was successful and rolls changes back in case of errors. 
            This ensures that the firewall machine will not be left with no 
            default route and therefore no way to access it remotely.
          </para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="ecmp">
        <title>ECMP routes</title>

          <para>Firewall Builder supports ECMP routes in Linux-based
          firewalls using iptables. To create an ECMP rule simply
          specify several rules with different paths (i.e., different
          combinations of Gateway and Interface, for the same
          Destination and with the same metric).</para>

          <para>In this example, there are three different paths to HostA.</para>

          <figure id="routing-rule2">
            <title>ECMP Routing Rule</title>
                <graphic scale="60" fileref="firewall_policies/images/routing-rule2.png" />
          </figure>

          <para>Rules are automatically classified in ECMP rules and
          non-ECMP.  The ECMP rules are written out in a separated
          section of the firewall script after the "normal" routing
          rules.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

