<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="working_with_objects">
  <title>Working With Objects</title>
  <para>
    Firewall Builder is based on the concept of objects. There are
    a variety of different object types used to define
    IP objects that can be used as the Source and Destination in
    your firewall rules. Two of the most common IP objects used
    in firewall rules are <emphasis>Networks</emphasis> and 
    <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis>.
    </para>
  <bridgehead>Network Objects</bridgehead>
  <para>
    To create the example Network object representing the
    internal 10.10.10.0/24 network shown in the diagram on the previous 
    page, go to the object tree on the left side of the screen and 
    double-click the folder labeled <emphasis>Objects</emphasis> to 
    expand it. Right click on the folder called <emphasis>Networks </emphasis> and select “New Network”. This creates a new network 
    object. In the lower portion of your screen, called the Editor 
    Panel, you can modify the properties of this new network object.
    </para>
  <para>
    Change the object name to something matching the function.  In 
    this example we  name it “Internal Network” to represent 
    the network connected to our &quot;inside&quot; interface. The address is set 
    to 10.10.10.0 and the netmask is 255.255.255.0.
    </para>
  <figure id="new_network">
    <title>New Network Object</title>
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/new_network.png"/>
  </figure>
  <note>
    <para>
    When editing the attributes of an object there is no Apply
    or Submit button. <emphasis role="bold">Once you edit an attribute, as soon as you move away from the field you were editing the change immediately takes effect.</emphasis>
    </para>
  </note>
  <bridgehead>Address Objects</bridgehead>
  <para>
    To create an object  representing a single IP address, similar 
    to the host parameter in a Cisco access list, go to the object tree,  right-click on the <emphasis>Addresses</emphasis> folder, and 
    select &quot;New Address&quot;. In the Editor Panel change the name of the 
    new address object to something that reflects its function, for example “POP3 
    Server”. Also set the IP address.
    </para>
  <figure id="new_address_steps">
    <title>New Address Object</title>
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/new_address_steps.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
  You may have noticed that we did not create any objects for the 
  TCP services like HTTP and SSH  needed for the 
  firewall object rules shown in the example. This is because Firewall 
  Builder comes with hundreds of predefined objects for commonly 
  used objects like TCP services.
  </para>
</sect1>
