  <sect1 id="compile-install-policy">
    <title>Compiling firewall policies</title>

    <para>Once you have a policy created, you need to compile it
      into a script that can run on your target device. You then
      need to install it on that device.</para>

    <para>Let's walk through compiling a iptables firewall. Below
      is the access policy of the firewall.</para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-1">
      <title>A policy to compile</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-1.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>To compile it use main menu item <guimenuitem>Rules >
    Compile</guimenuitem>.</para>

    <para>
      Alternatively, open the Policy, NAT or routing rules of the firewall
      you want to compile by double-clicking in the tree, then click
      the "Compile" icon (the hammer) in the policy window.
    </para>

    <para>To compile several firewalls, use Shift-left click or Ctrl-left click to select
      more than one firewall. Then, right-click on one of
      them to bring up the context menu and
      select <guimenuitem>Compile</guimenuitem>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Different ways to compile one or several firewall objects were
      described earlier in <xref linkend="compile-and-install-options"/>.
    </para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-3">
      <title>Select your firewall</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-3.png" />
    </figure>


    <para>
      Check the <guilabel>Compile</guilabel> checkbox next to the firewall you want to compile, and uncheck all the others.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firewall Builder keeps track of the last time the firewall was
      compiled and also keeps track of any changes since then. If the
      firewall has not changed since the last compile,
      that firewall is unchecked by default because no compile is
      needed. Any direct change done to the rules of the firewall, or 
      a change to any object used in rules, triggers the
      recompile. You can always force compile by checking the 
      <guilabel>Compile</guilabel> next to the object in the list or 
      skip it by unchecking it.
    </para>

    <para>
      In addition, you can see which firewalls and clusters
      have been modified since their last compile by looking at the
      object tree. If a firewall has been compiled since it was last
      modified, it appears in normal font. If it has not been
      compiled since its last modification, it appears in
      bold.
    </para>

    <para>As you can see in this image, firewalls that need compilation are in bold and are checked by default in the Compile dialog. F
irewalls that have been compiled since their last change are in regular font and are unchecked by default.</para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-8">
      <title>Uncompiled firewalls are in bold</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-8.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>
      To see the last time a firewall or cluster was compiled,
      double-click it to bring up its object editor.
    </para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-both2">
      <title>Object Editor Dialog with last modify and compile times</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-both2.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>
      Returning to <xref linkend="compile-install-firewall-3"/>.
      Since we are just doing a compile, the only
      checkbox is the <guilabel>Compile</guilabel> checkbox. If we were doing a compile
      and install in the same run, you would also see an <guilabel>Install</guilabel>
      checkbox.
    </para>

    <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para>

    <para>A dialog appears that tracks the status of the
      compile. In this case, we have an error:</para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-4">
      <title>Compile status messages</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-4.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>Errors appear in red, and warnings appear in blue. In
      this case, it turns out that one of our rules shadows one of
      our other rules. For other types of problems, see
      <xref linkend="troubleshooting-compiler-runtime" />.</para>

    <para>Errors and warnings are clickable. Clicking an error
      takes you to the portion of the policy where the error
      occurs.</para>

    <para>We fix the problem, then compile again.</para>

    <figure id="compile-install-firewall-4c">
      <title>Successful compile</title>
      <graphic scale="50" fileref="compile_install/images/compile-install-firewall-4c.png" />
    </figure>

    <para>To see the created script, look in the same directory as
      your .fwb file. The file will be called
      &lt;firewallName&gt;.fw. (If you changed your default
      directory in the Preferences, then the generated script will
      be there instead.)</para>

  </sect1>

