<sect1 id="asa_compile_install">
    <title>Compile and Install</title>

    <para>
    In Firewall Builder the process of converting the rules from the
    Firewall Builder GUI syntax to the target device commands is called
    <emphasis>compiling</emphasis> the configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
    To compile, click on the Compile icon which looks like a hammer
    <imagedata fileref="images/hammer_small.png" />. If you
    haven’t saved your configuration file yet you will be asked to do so. After
    you save your file a wizard will be displayed that lets you select which
    firewall(s) you want to compile. In this example we are going to complie
    the firewall called <emphasis>asa-1</emphasis> configured with the rules above.
    </para>

    <para>
    If there aren’t any errors, you should see some messages scroll by in the
    main window and a message at the top left stating Success.
    </para>

    <para>
    To view the output of the compile, click on the button that says Inspect
    Generated Files.  This will open the file that contains the commands in
    Cisco command format.  Note that any line that starts with “!” is a comment.
    </para>
        
  <figure id="asa_compiler_output">
    <title>Example Compiler Output</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/asa_compiler_output.png" />
  </figure> 
        
    <para>
    The output from the compiler is automatically saved in a file in the same
    directory as the data file that was used to create it. The generated files
    are named with the firewall name and a .fw extension. In our example the
    generated configuration file is called asa-1.fw. You can copy and copy and
    paste the commands from this file to your ASA or PIX firewall or you can 
    use the built-in Firewall Builder installer.
    </para>

    <bridgehead>Installing</bridgehead>

    <para>
    Firewall Builder can install the generated configuration file for you
    using SSH and SCP. To use the installer we need to identify one of the router
    interfaces as the “Management Interface”. This tells Firewall Builder
    which IP address to connect to on the router.
    </para>

    <para>
    Do this by double-clicking the firewall object to expand it, and then
    double-clicking on the interface name that you want to assign as the
    management interface. In this example this is interface Ethernet0/1
    which is the interface connected to the internal network.
    </para>

  <figure id="asa_set_mgmt_interface">
    <title>Setting the Managment Interface</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/asa_set_mgmt_interface.png" />
  </figure> 

  <note>
    <para>
    Any time you are changing access lists on your router
    you face the risk of locking yourself out of the device.  Please be
    careful to always inspect your access lists closely and make sure that
    you will be able to access the ASA / PIX after the access list is installed.
    </para>
  </note>

    <para>
    To install your access lists on the firewall, click on the install icon
    <imagedata fileref="images/install_icon.png" />. This will
    bring up a wizard where you will select the firewall to install. Click
    Next > to install the selected firewall.
    </para>

  <figure id="asa_install_checkbox">
    <title>Setting Compile and Install Actions</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/asa_install_checkbox.png" />
  </figure> 

    <para>
    Firewall Builder will compile your rules converting them in to
    Cisco access list command line format. After the compile completes
    successfully click Next >. Enter your username, password and enable
    password.
    </para>

  <figure id="asa_install_screen">
    <title>Install Dialog</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/install_screen.png" />
  </figure> 

    <para>
    After the access list configuration is installed you see a message
    at the bottom of the main window and the status indicator in the
    upper left corner of the wizard will indicate if the installation
    was successful.
    </para>
        
  <figure id="asa_install_success">
    <title>Successful Install</title>      
    <graphic scale="50" fileref="images/asa_install_success.png" />
  </figure> 
        
    <para>
    By default Firewall Builder will use SCP to copy the generated config 
    file to the firewall. Once the file is copied to the firewall, Firewall 
    Builder will connect using SSH to load the transferred config file from 
    memory using the "copy" command to merge the Firewall Builder generated 
    command with the current running configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
    Firewall Builder requires ssh version 2 to be enabled on the firewall.
    </para>

</sect1>

